{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "These agreements were condemned by the United Nations in Resolution 33/28 A. As a result of signing these agreements, one negotiator was killed by Khalid Islambouli and Islamic Jihad. These agreements established the border and a peace agreement between Egypt and Israel. For 10 points, name these 1978 agreements negotiated by Jimmy Carter at a Presidential retreat.",
      "answer": "Camp David Accords"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man rose to the head of his party after he was targeted by the Zhongshan Warship Incident. This man and his wife propounded the semi-fascist New Life Movement, and he was the first commandant of the Whampoa Military Academy. His wife Soong May-ling supposedly had an affair with Wendell Wilkie, and he succeeded Sun Yat-Sen as leader of the KMT. For 10, points, name this longtime president of Taiwan and nationalist leader during the Chinese Civil War.",
      "answer": "Chiang Kai-Shek"
    },
    {
      "question": "This text is the subject of the Supreme Court case Minersville v. Gobitis. This text was originally recited while saluting outward, a recommendation changed after World War II. Michael Newdow filed several lawsuits attempting to remove a phrase added in the 1950s, \"under God,\" from this text. For 10 points, name this Francis Bellamy-written ode to the U.S. flag.",
      "answer": "Pledge of Allegiance"
    },
    {
      "question": "This movement's \"first lady\" recorded \"Don't Sleep in the Subway\" and \"Downtown.\" Another\nact from this period, which sang \"Doo Wah Diddy,\" was Manfred Mann's Earth Band. This mid1960s movement included the Dave Clark Five, The Troggs, The Animals, as well as The\nRolling Stones. For 10 points, name this wave of England-based artists who achieved American\npopularity.",
      "answer": "British Invasion"
    },
    {
      "question": "Between political offices, this man was a law partner of future FCC commissioner Newton\nMinnow. This man snapped \"don't wait for the translation\" at Valerin Zorin during his time as\nU.S. ambassador to the United Nations. He was dubbed \"egghead\" during his two failed\nPresidential runs. For 10 points, name this man who lost twice to Dwight Eisenhower.",
      "answer": [
        "Adlai Stevenson",
        "Stevenson"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was once marooned on Bermuda in the wreck of the Sea Venture. He created the\nOrinoco cultivar of a product that he put into four barels during his return to England, where he\npresented his wife, under the new name \"Rebecca,\" to the royal court. For 10 points, name this\nhusband of Pocahontas who devised the financially viable form of American tobacco.",
      "answer": [
        "John Rolfe",
        "Rolfe"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "President-in-waiting Luis Donaldo Colosio was assassinated in this city in 1994. This city's\nAvenida Revolución (ah-veh-NEE-duh reh-voh-loo-see-OWN) was the location of Cesar\nCardini's restaurant, where the Caesar salad was invented. For 10 points, name this city in Baja\nCalifornia which attracts numerous American tourists from nearby San Diego.",
      "answer": "Tijuana"
    },
    {
      "question": "Gustave de Beamount and Alexis de Tocqueville originally went to the U.S. to observe these facilities, thoguh Tocqueville wrote Democracy in America instead. Jeremy Bentham proposed the \"panopticon\" design for these facilities. For 10 points, name these facilities which penologists study and which have been home to John Dillinger and Charles Manson.",
      "answer": "prisons"
    },
    {
      "question": "This President lost several Cabinet members, including Secretary of State Abel Upshur, when a cannon exploded on the USS Princeton. He refused to open mail addressed to the \"Acting President\" after he took office following the death of his popular war hero predecessor. For 10 points, name this man who completed the Presidential term of William Henry Harrison.",
      "answer": "John Tyler"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the 1940s, this man appeared on posters advocating that war workers use suggestion boxes, and he also was shown advocating the purchase of bonds alongside Lady Columbia, whom he largely replaced. This man, whose common image is based on Horatio Kitchener, says \"I want you!\" in a recruiting poster. For 10 points, name this personification of the United States.",
      "answer": "Uncle Sam"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man's little-used middle names are \"Plantagenet\" and \"Schicklgruber.\"His Social Security number is 000-00-0002, and he never forgave his mother for her affair with President Taft. He looted paintings from a Nazi stronghold as part of the Flying Hellfish. For 10 points, name this employer of Waylon Smithers and very old proprietor of the Springfield Nuclear Power Plant.",
      "answer": "Charles Montgomery Burns"
    },
    {
      "question": "A member of this family moved to Arkansas to become that state's first post-Reconstruction Republican governor. Another member of this family founded the University of Chicago, and another was criticized for his flippant handling of the Attica prison riot. For 10 points, what family included Standard Oil baron John and New York governor Nelson?",
      "answer": "Rockefeller"
    },
    {
      "question": "A major leader of this party defected to become the Republican governor of Massachussetts; that was Nathaniel Banks. This party often rioted against Catholics, including burning down a church in Maine, and it nominated Millard Fillmore for President in 1856. For 10 points, name this anti-immigrant party which briefly arose prior to the Civil War.",
      "answer": "Know-Nothing Party"
    },
    {
      "question": "Amos Akerman and Benjamin Bristow were appointed by this President as part of the Department of Justice, which this man created. This man put down the 1874 Brooks-Baxter War between two factions of the Republican Party. The Force Acts were passed by this President to safeguard African-Americans’ right to vote, and the end of his term marked the end of the Reconstruction Era. For ten points, name this U.S. President, a former general nicknamed “Unconditional Surrender” for his role in the U.S. Civil War.",
      "answer": "Ulysses S. Grant"
    },
    {
      "question": "The last U.S. battleship to be completed was named for this state and christened by Margaret, the daughter of a then-Senator from this state. That battleship, now a museum next to the USS Arizona memorial, sailed to Tokyo for the signing of the Japanese surrender ending World War II. For ten points, name this U.S. state where Harry Truman lived in Independence, just outside Kansas City.",
      "answer": [
        "Missouri",
        "USS Missouri"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This amendment was cited in Presser v. Illinois, which allowed states to ban groups like the ethnic German “Instruct and Defend Association.” The 2010 case McDonald v. Chicago incorporated this amendment to the states after D.C. v. Heller overturned a law requiring “trigger locks.” The phrase “A well regulated militia” begins, for ten points, what Constitutional amendment that protects the right to “keep and bear arms?”",
      "answer": "Second Amendment to the U.S. Constitution"
    },
    {
      "question": "On the campaign trail, this politician struggled to answer questions about a golf trip with Paula Parkinson. This politician claimed that Murphy Brown’s role as a single mother hastened America’s moral decline a month prior to misspelling potato as a spelling bee judge. In a debate, Lloyd Bentsen stated that this man was “no Jack Kennedy”. For ten points, name this oft-criticized vice president who served under George H.W. Bush.",
      "answer": "James Danforth “Dan” Quayle"
    },
    {
      "question": "This president tried to send John Slidell to negotiate the purchase of territory in modern New Mexico. He sent Nicholas Trist to negotiate a treaty that replaced the Nueces River with the Rio Grande as a national border and ended the Mexican-American War. For ten points, name this “dark horse” president during whose term the United States gained territory in present-day California.",
      "answer": "James K. Polk"
    },
    {
      "question": "This event disrupted plans to create a utopian society known as New Helvetia. Newspaper owner Samuel Brannan heavily promoted this event, which led Levi Strauss to sell dry goods and denim overalls. This event was started after James Marshall made a discovery at Sutter’s Mill, and it led to the growth of San Francisco. For ten points, name this economic event in which “forty-niners” traveled to California.",
      "answer": "California Gold Rush"
    },
    {
      "question": "Jonathan Baldwin Turner advocated for the creation of more of these institutions in the 1850s. The Smith-Lever Act was implemented to allow greater cooperation between these institutions and their surroundings, and HBCUs are examples of these institutions that were established for African-Americans after the Civil War. The Morrill Land-Grant Acts set aside land for the creation of these institutions, including one in Champaign, Illinois. For ten points, name these educational institutions, including Iowa State, Cornell, and MIT.",
      "answer": "colleges or universities"
    },
    {
      "question": "This leader is depicted in the Catalan Atlas sitting on a throne and inspecting a gold nugget. This leader commissioned the Djinguereber [jin-gah-ray-bear] Mosque and Sankore University, both located in Timbuktu, and he caused a massive deflation of the price of gold in Cairo while on an extravagant Hajj to Mecca. For ten points, name this Mali emperor, or Mansa, who ruled from 1312 to 1327.",
      "answer": "Mansa Musa or Musa I"
    },
    {
      "question": "Morgan Lewis defeated this man to become Governor of New York in 1804. James Wilkinson conspired with this man to create a monarchy in the American west with support from Spain. This man, Thomas Jefferson’s first Vice President, went to Weehauken, New Jersey to settle a personal dispute with a former Secretary of the Treasury. For ten points, name this man who killed Alexander Hamilton in an 1804 duel.",
      "answer": "Aaron Burr"
    },
    {
      "question": "Former President of Sears Julius Rosenwald was asked by this man to serve on the board of directors for an institute he headed. This man advised his people to “Cast down your bucket where you are” in his “Atlanta Compromise” speech, which was opposed by the formulator of the “Talented Tenth” doctrine, W.E.B. DuBois. For ten points, name this African-American leader of the Tuskegee Institute.",
      "answer": "Booker T. Washington"
    },
    {
      "question": "The goals of this agreement had been brought up earlier by John Slidell, and this treaty put an end to the war that began with the Thornton Affair. A failed clause in this treaty that would have outlawed slavery in the territories it acquired was known as the Wilmot Proviso, and the United States paid $15 million in this agreement to gain the lands north of the Rio Grande. For ten points, name this 1848 treaty that ended the Mexican-American War.",
      "answer": "Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo"
    },
    {
      "question": "Suzanne Massie taught this politician to “trust, but verify.” As governor, he signed the Therapeutic Abortion Act and banned public carry of firearms with the Mulford Act. As President, he launched an invasion to protect American medical students, Operation Urgent Fury, which deposed Maurice Bishop in Grenada. For ten points, name this U.S. President who served as Governor of California after his acting career.",
      "answer": "Ronald Reagan"
    },
    {
      "question": "One man involved in this scandal wrote “We want more friends in this Congress.” Aaron Perry investigated this scandal, which was exposed by a letter from Henry McComb to the New York Sun. It involved Congressman Oakes Ames’ use of stock in a railroad company as bribes, and was revealed during the 1872 Presidential election. For ten points, name this scandal that ended Schuyler Colfax’s political career but failed to prevent Ulysses Grant’s re-election.",
      "answer": "Credit Mobilier of America scandal"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s criticism of the Vietnam War led Lyndon Johnson to accuse him of playing “too much football without a helmet.” Though this man signed the Helsinki Accords, he asserted that “there is no Soviet domination of Eastern Europe” during a debate with Jimmy Carter, hampering his re-election bid. For ten points, name this president who succeeded, and controversially pardoned, Richard Nixon.",
      "answer": "Gerald Rudolph Ford or Leslie Lynch King"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Cascajal [kas-kah-hal] Block hints at a writing system for this culture. An excavation at this culture’s El Manati site unearthed the Las Limas figure, a prominent example of were-jaguar art. These people were the first to play the “ball game,” and their ability to extract latex from nearby trees led them to be known as the “rubber people.” For ten points, name this oldest Mesoamerican civilization, known for the construction of large stone heads.",
      "answer": "Olmec civilization"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was succeeded by Caleb Strong as Governor after the Boston Gazette published Elkanah Tisdale’s cartoon attacking him. This man, along with John Marshall and Charles Pickney, met agents of Talleyrand who demanded a bribe in the XYZ affair. A political cartoon of a dragon representing the unorthodox shape of Essex County lampooned, for ten points, what Massachusetts politician whose name now describes the practice of drawing congressional districts for political gain?",
      "answer": [
        "Elbridge Gerry",
        "gerrymandering"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Many immigrants of this ethnicity arrived in the U.S. by the credit-ticket system. Denis Kearney gained fame for speeches attacking members of this ethnicity, who entered the U.S. after the passage of the Burlingame Treaty. People of this ethnicity were brought to America to build the western legs of the Transcontinental Railroad, and their immigration was targeted by an 1882 Exclusion Act. For ten points, name this immigrant group who established namesake “towns” in cities like San Francisco.",
      "answer": "Chinese-Americans"
    },
    {
      "question": "After the ruling of this case, Calvin C. Chafee and Taylor Blow provided protection for the plaintiff. Justices McLean and Curtis dissented in this 7-2 ruling, after which Stephen Douglas formulated the Freeport Doctrine. The Missouri Compromise was deemed unconstitutional by, for ten points, what controversial 1857 Supreme Court case that determined slaves could not sue in court because they were not U.S. citizens?",
      "answer": "Dred Scott v. John F.A. Sandford"
    },
    {
      "question": "A member of this family was injured in a 1908 accident that killed Lieutenant Thomas Selfridge. A business formed by this family merged with the Curtiss company in 1929 and is still active today. Members of this family formed a bicycle company in 1892 in Dayton, Ohio. On December 17, 1903, near Kitty Hawk, North Carolina, two members of this family launched a plane. For ten points, name this family of American aviation pioneers that included Orville and Wilbur.",
      "answer": "Wright or the Wright Brothers"
    },
    {
      "question": "After tackling and beating a man named Wesley, this figure quipped “Sorry I had a fight in the middle of your Black Panther meeting.” After a Viet Cong bombing, this man rescued Lieutenant Dan and Bubba, acting against his girlfriend Jenny’s advice to “run.” The advice “life is like a box of chocolates” is given by the mother of, for ten points, what 1994 film character, played by Tom Hanks, who inexplicably experiences much of 20th century American history?",
      "answer": [
        "Forrest Gump",
        "either",
        "both"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This president affirmed the right to intervene in South American relations in his namesake corollary and sent the Great White Fleet around the world to showcase American naval power. This man, who claimed to “speak softly and carry a big stick,” broke with William Taft, and ran in the election of 1912 with the Bull Moose party. For ten points, name this early 20th century president who appears with Lincoln, Jefferson, and Washington on Mount Rushmore.",
      "answer": [
        "Theodore Roosevelt",
        "Teddy Roosevelt"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This U.S. state’s first constitution had a “whites only” clause. A national park in this state surrounds Mount Mazama, whose caldera filled with water after a prehistoric eruption. A wildlife refuge in this state’s Harney Basin was occupied in 2016 by a group led by Ammon Bundy. The Malheur Wildlife Refuge and Crater Lake are within, for ten points, what Western state whose Willamette Valley was the destination for pioneers traveling a 19th century trail?",
      "answer": "Oregon"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a story set during this conflict, a child falls asleep while playing with a wooden sword in a forest; later, that deaf and mute boy stumbles upon the corpse of his dead parent. During this war, a character is tricked by a disguised scout into attempting to blow up a transportation line, then hallucinates his escape before being hanged for treason. For ten points, name this setting of Ambrose Bierce’s stories “An Occurrence at Owl Creek Bridge” and “Chickamauga.”",
      "answer": "American Civil War"
    },
    {
      "question": "A “Forum” named after this animal was founded by Phyllis Schlafly to oppose passage of the Equal Rights Amendment. A depiction of this animal on posters was accompanied by the phrase “we do our part;” that blue type of this animal was the logo of the National Industrial Recovery Act. The lunar module of the Apollo 11 mission bore the name of this animal. For ten points, name this animal, whose bald type is the national emblem of the United States.",
      "answer": [
        "eagle",
        "Eagle Forum",
        "blue eagles, descriptions of the Eagle module, bald eagles, etc."
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Description acceptable. The non-fictional Battle of the Windmill took place as part of an effort to achieve this action, which was taken by Hunters’ Lodges in the early 19th century. Isaac Brock’s death at Queenston Heights prevented one of these efforts. John Burgoyne repulsed an earlier attempt at this action during the Revolutionary War, during which Richard Montgomery died. For ten points, name this military action, frequently performed by the early United States, which sought to gain more territory to the north.",
      "answer": "the U.S. invading Canada"
    },
    {
      "question": "The name of this practice was inspired by a Richard Outcault character, a bald child who appeared in Hogan’s Alley. That comic strip ran in both the Journal and World, respectively owned by William Randolph Hearst and Joseph Pulitzer, moguls who perfected this practice. Public support for the Spanish-American War was garnered via, for ten points, what questionable journalistic practice that uses anonymous sources, questionable facts, and sensationalist headlines to sell more newspapers?",
      "answer": "yellow journalism"
    },
    {
      "question": "This company gained a foothold in China by distributing lamps under the name Mei Foo. A Puck cartoon depicts this company as a snake fighting an infant. McClure’s magazine exposed the practices of this company via muckraking journalist Ida Tarbell. Chevron was formed from the breakup of the monopoly of this company in 1911. For ten points, name this American-based petroleum company founded by John D. Rockefeller.",
      "answer": "Standard Oil Company"
    },
    {
      "question": "This case was cited a decade later in Griffin v. Prince Edward County, which forbade a plank of the “Stanley plan” calling for a voucher system. Those vouchers were part of Harry Byrd’s plan of “massive resistance” against this Supreme Court ruling, which was decided unanimously. Thurgood Marshall argued for the NAACP in this case, which overturned Plessy v. Ferguson. For ten points, name this 1954 case that declared “separate but equal” segregation of public schools unconstitutional.",
      "answer": "Brown v. Board of Education of Topeka, Kansas"
    },
    {
      "question": "Ken Khachigian, this President’s chief speechwriter, penned an apology speech for this man to deliver at Bergen-Belsen following his involvement in the Bitburg controversy. This man’s doctor replied “Today, Mr. President, we are all Republicans” after he survived an assassination attempt conducted by John Hinckley. This former President of the Screen Actors’ Guild was succeeded in office by his Vice President, George H.W. Bush. For ten points, name this conservative U.S. President who led during much of the 1980s.",
      "answer": "Ronald Reagan"
    },
    {
      "question": "This was the surname of the most recent Vice President to die in office, a man known as “Sunny Jim,” as well as the surname of a Treasury Secretary known as the “Ohio Icicle.” In 1884, a man with this surname said “I will not accept if nominated and will not serve if elected.” That man, a former Civil War general, was the brother of John, whose 1890 law was used to break up Standard Oil in 1911. For ten points, give this surname of an Ohio Senator who sponsored an early Antitrust Act and of General William Tecumseh.",
      "answer": [
        "Sherman",
        "James Sherman, John Sherman, William Tecumseh Sherman"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In order to perform this action, numerous U.S. Presidents have joined the Burning Tree Club in Bethesda, Maryland. In April 1961, John F. Kennedy gave a Secret Service agent a head injury by performing this action badly. After repeatedly poorly performing this action, Dwight Eisenhower demanded the removal of a tall pine tree at Augusta National. For ten points, name this common athletic activity for U.S. Presidents, especially Eisenhower, who installed the White House putting green.",
      "answer": [
        "golfing",
        "anything related to golf, including more specific responses, like swinging a golf club, teeing off, etc."
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This leader argued that “the prospect of domination of the nation’s scholars by Federal employment [...] is gravely to be regarded.” This man delivered a “message of leave-taking and farewell” that explained “Americanmakersofplowsharescould[...]makeswordsaswell”andwarnedagainstthemilitary-industrial complex. For ten points, name this 20th century President whose advice regarding the defense industry derived from his service as Allied Commander in World War II.",
      "answer": "Dwight D. Eisenhower"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man met his business partner, Phineas Miller, while staying at the Mulberry Grove estate of Revolutionary War widow Catherine Greene. He received a government contract to produce ten thousand muskets in two years, during which he pioneered the use of replaceable parts in gun manufacturing. This man developed a machine that used a wire mesh to isolate seeds from the fibers of a crop widely grown in the American south. For ten points, name this inventor of the cotton gin.",
      "answer": "Eli Whitney"
    },
    {
      "question": "This leader survived a failed coup attempt, the February 26 Incident, which ended the period of “government by assassination.” The first time many of this ruler’s subjects heard his voice was during the Jewel Voice Broadcast. After defeat at the Battle of Saipan, this man ordered his subjects to commit suicide rather than be captured. Douglas MacArthur allowed this man to keep his position during the American post-war occupation. For ten points, name this emperor of Japan during World War II.",
      "answer": "Emperor Hirohito or the Showa Emperor"
    },
    {
      "question": "An amendment co-sponsored by this Senator and Mark Hatfield brought the chamber to a halt when this man accused each senator of sending 50,000 Americans to their premature deaths. This man co-chaired a commission with Donald Fraser that led to a surge in the amount and importance of presidential primaries. This man lost an election to an incumbent who promised “peace with honor” and claimed this man would settle for “peace at any price.” For ten points, name this anti-war South Dakotan Democrat who lost every state but Massachusetts to Richard Nixon in 1972.",
      "answer": "George McGovern"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1976, George H.W. Bush took over a leadership role in this organization for slightly less than a year. The Family Jewels were a set of papers about this organization. This agency trained a group of exiles called Brigade 2506, which was decisively defeated after an amphibious landing at the Bay of Pigs. For ten points, name this American organization, based in Langley, Virginia, that manages international espionage.",
      "answer": "Central Intelligence Agency or CIA"
    },
    {
      "question": "This location included a radar station at Opana Point, which was staffed by Joseph Lockard and George Elliot. This facility includes Ford Island, Hickam Field, and Wheeler Field, where grounded aircraft were destroyed by Val bombers. This facility’s Battleship Row was home to the Pacific Fleet’s Oklahoma and Arizona. For ten points, name this American naval base on Oahu that was attacked on December 7th, 1941.",
      "answer": [
        "Naval Station Pearl Harbor",
        "descriptive answers, such as “the naval base at Pearl Harbor”"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A group of people protesting Dick Wilson’s corruption occupied this site under the direction of Russell Means in 1973. Stephen Vincent Benet’s poem “American Names” references this location, noting “I shall not be there. I shall rise and pass. Bury my heart at” this location. This site in the Pine Ridge Indian Reservation was the location of a violent episode when Black Coyote refused to surrender his rifle to U.S. troops. For ten points, name this site of an 1890 massacre of Lakota Sioux.",
      "answer": [
        "Wounded Knee",
        "Bury My Heart at Wounded Knee",
        "Wounded Knee Massacre"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This cause was supported by Horace Greeley’s pamphlet “Prayer of Twenty Millions,” which urged enforcement of the Confiscation Acts. People who proposed secession and opposed this cause were called Fire-Eaters. William Lloyd Garrison burned a copy of the Constitution because it failed to support this cause, which he advocated for in The Liberator. For ten points, name this cause that was achieved via the 13th Amendment and the Emancipation Proclamation.",
      "answer": [
        "abolition of slavery",
        "word forms",
        "any answers related to freeing slaves"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A thunderbird replaced a yellow version of this symbol on a red diamond as the insignia of the 45th Infantry Division, which consisted of National Guardsmen from the American southwest. This symbol, whose name derives from Sanskrit for “auspicious,” was used by the Thule Society, which supported the DAP, or German Worker’s Party. For ten points, name this four-armed symbol, common in numerous religious traditions, that was adopted by the Nazi Party.",
      "answer": [
        "swastika",
        "tetraskelion",
        "hakenkreuz",
        "hooked cross",
        "fylfot",
        "tetragammadion"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One of the causes of this rebellion was the selective distribution of trade contracts by the Long Assembly. Thomas Larimore led a group of ships dispatched to fight this rebellion, which ended when its namesake leader died of dysentery. The perceived pro-Native American stance of governor William Berkeley incited this rebellion, whose agitators burned Jamestown to the ground in 1676. For ten points, name this first major rebellion in colonial Virginia.",
      "answer": "Bacon’s Rebellion"
    },
    {
      "question": "An 1889 attempt to build a railway along this location ended when Frank Brown drowned exploring it. John Powell named this location after leading the first American expedition to its ground floor. The glass-bottomed “Skywalk” is maintained by the Hualapai tribe in this location, which was regarded as sacred by the ancestral Pueblo that first inhabited it. The Colorado River formed, for ten points, what 277-mile long canyon in Arizona?",
      "answer": "Grand Canyon"
    },
    {
      "question": "This President averted a strike by signing the Adamson Act to grant an eight-hour workday to railroad workers. This man oversaw the deportation of over 200 anarchists on the “Soviet Ark,” many of whom were arrested in a series of raids ordered by his attorney general, Mitchell Palmer; this President’s Espionage Act, which justified those arrests, was upheld by the Supreme Court due to wartime conditions. For ten points, name this president who led the United States through World War I.",
      "answer": "Thomas Woodrow Wilson"
    },
    {
      "question": "In response to this event, the President noted “we’ve grown used to wonders in this century,” in a speech written by Peggy Noonan; that speech became known as the “face of God” speech. This event was investigated by the Rogers Commission, which included Richard Feynman [fine-man]. Schoolteacher Christa McAuliffe was killed in this event, which was caused by O-rings that failed in low temperatures. For ten points, name this 1986 tragedy in which a space shuttle exploded.",
      "answer": [
        "Space Shuttle Challenger disaster",
        "equivalents, like explosion, crash, etc."
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man beat Congressman William Stanbery with a hickory cane on Pennsylvania Avenue after Stanbery suggested that this man had defrauded Native Americans. To avoid paying fees from the resulting trial, this politician fled to Mexico, where he later led the Texan Army at the Battle of San Jacinto and captured Santa Anna. For ten points, name this Texas politician, the namesake of the most populous city in Texas.",
      "answer": "Sam Houston"
    },
    {
      "question": "The most prominent of the Townshend Acts not to be repealed in 1770 was a tax levied on this commodity. The Dartmouth, the Eleanor, and the Beaver carried this commodity from England to the American colonies. The Intolerable Acts were passed in response to the dumping of this commodity into a Massachusetts Harbor in 1773 by members of the Sons of Liberty. For ten points, identify this commodity destroyed in a namesake Boston party.",
      "answer": [
        "tea",
        "Tea Act",
        "Boston Tea Party"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In 2015, a yearly pillow fight at this location was banned after hard objects were stuffed in pillow cases, leading to two dozen injuries. This location was connected to Constitution Island by a long chain in its original design by Tadeusz Kosciuszko [tah-dah-oosh ko-SHOO-skoh]. The longest continuously occupied American military post is, for ten points, what New York location, the base of the U.S. Military Academy, which was to be betrayed by Benedict Arnold?",
      "answer": [
        "West Point",
        "the US Military Academy until mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This program gained support after a report by Herbert Hoover deemed it was infeasible to turn one nation into a “pastoral state” without the migration of 25 million people. This program, which replaced the punitive Morgenthau Plan, was announced at a Harvard commencement speech in 1947. Greece and Turkey received the first part of a disbursement of 13 billion dollars under, for ten points, what American foreign policy to help rebuild postwar Europe, named for the US Secretary of State?",
      "answer": [
        "Marshall Plan",
        "European Recovery Program",
        "ERP"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "An 1869 Supreme Court case involving this state held that its bond sales during the Civil War were invalid. The Gun Free School Zones Act was ruled unconstitutional in a case arising from this state, US v. Lopez. The Supreme Court overturned Bowers v. Hardwick in a 2003 case that struck down this state’s anti-sodomy laws. Abigail Fisher challenged the affirmative action program of, for ten points, what state that admits the top ten percent of each of its high school’s students to its main campus in Austin?",
      "answer": [
        "Texas",
        "Texas v. White",
        "Lawrence v. Texas after “Bowers” is read",
        "Fisher v. University of Texas after “Abigail” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This politician dueled fellow state representative Humphrey Marshall after a spat regarding British cloth. As Speaker, this man succeeded in convincing Southern representatives to adopt the Thomas Proviso, while also convincing Northern representatives to allow Missouri’s admission into the Union as a slave state. This coiner of the term “American System” negotiated a “corrupt bargain” that resulted in John Quincy Adams’ elevation to the presidency. For ten points, name this Kentucky politician known as the Great Compromiser.",
      "answer": "Henry Clay"
    },
    {
      "question": "In this state, John Cruger fought against Nathaniel Greene and Thaddeus Kosciuszko at the Siege of 96. Alexander Stewart led a 1781 British victory along the Santee River in this state. Banastre Tarleton was defeated by a double envelopment by Daniel Morgan at this state’s Battle of Cowpens. During the Revolutionary War, Charles Cornwallis inflicted a defeat on Horatio Gates at the Battle of Camden in this state. For ten points, name this state where, in 1780, American forces surrendered in the Siege of Charleston.",
      "answer": "South Carolina"
    },
    {
      "question": "These sites were sustained by crops harvested by “neophytes.” The establishment of these sites forced nearby inhabitants into lands called reductions, where they would continue to live when these sites were divided into the rancho system. Defended by royal forts called presidios, 21 of these sites were linked by El Camino Real [ree-all]. Junipero Serra supervised conversion efforts at, for ten points, what Spanish religious outposts in California?",
      "answer": "Spanish missions in California"
    },
    {
      "question": "George H.W. Bush gave this Cabinet position to Elizabeth Dole, which she left in 1990 to become president of the American Red Cross. Current Secretary of Transportation Elaine Chao held this position for all eight years of George W. Bush’s presidency. The first female cabinet member held this post for the entirety of FDR’s time in office. For ten points, name this cabinet position held by Frances Perkins, who oversaw the passage of laws governing overtime wages.",
      "answer": "Secretary of Labor"
    },
    {
      "question": "One philosopher from this school claimed that human mysticism was a particularly ineffable quality; that work used the example of George Fox and the Quakers to argue that the origins of a religion did not reflect its value. The author of Varieties of Religious Experience belonged to this school of thought, whose namesake maxim argued that the “practical effects” of your conception were critical to rational thought. Charles Sanders Peirce [”purse”] and William James helped found, for ten points, what American philosophical school?",
      "answer": [
        "pragmatism",
        "word forms"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man stored the remains of his long-time ally, Rwandan President Juvenal Habyarimana, at his palace in Gbadolite, this politician’s so-called “Versailles of the Jungle.” This leader deposed Patrice Lumumba and was deposed himself by Laurent Kabila in 1997. This leader changed his own name to establish pro-Africa cultural awareness and changed the name of his country to Zaire. For ten points, name this leopard print hat-wearing dictator who ruled in the Democratic Republic of the Congo.",
      "answer": "Joseph D´esir´e Mobutu or Mobutu Sese Seko Kuku Ngbendu Wa Za Banga"
    },
    {
      "question": "This kingdom was briefly controlled by Britain after the arrival of the HMS Carysfort in the Paulet Affair. Because Kalakaua had been intimidated into giving his power away, this kingdom’s legal code was known as the Bayonet Constitution. Sanford Dole was appointed president of this kingdom shortly before it was annexed by William McKinley in 1898. For ten points, name this kingdom, that was ruled by Queen Liliuokalani and became the 50th US state.",
      "answer": "Kingdom of Hawai’i"
    },
    {
      "question": "This President’s doctrine pledged support to Middle Eastern governments, including military support for Camille Chamoun of Lebanon. Earl Warren was appointed as Chief Justice by this president a year before Brown v. Board of Education overturned the doctrine of “separate but equal.” This president sent members of 101st Airborne Division to escort the Little Rock Nine. For ten points, name this president and former World War II Supreme Allied Commander.",
      "answer": "Dwight David “Ike” Eisenhower"
    },
    {
      "question": "The “United Empire” faction of these people consisted of members who migrated to Canadian provinces. These people were led into combat by Patrick Ferguson, where they were defeated at Kings Mountain. A considerable population of North and South Carolina consisted of these people, whom Charles Cornwallis hoped to gain the support of during his campaign there. For ten points, give this term for American colonists who supported Great Britain during the Revolution.",
      "answer": [
        "Loyalists",
        "Tories",
        "Royalists",
        "King’s Men",
        "descriptive answers that use the word loyal"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This initiative supplanted Directive 1067 and was in turn replaced by the Mutual Security Agency. This initiative was adopted after Herbert Hoover noted that a “pastoral state” would be the outcome of the opposing Morgenthau Plan. Greece and Turkey were the first countries to adopt this plan, and Joseph Stalin ordered Warsaw Pact nations not to accept its money. Harry Truman’s Secretary of State names, for ten points, what American plan that offered economic aid to Europe after World War II?",
      "answer": [
        "Marshall Plan or European Recovery Program",
        "ERP"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "During this year, the USS Vandalia faced off against German ships in Samoa until it was destroyed by a cyclone. The Enabling Act was signed during it to split the Dakota Territory, and the “Sooners” and “Boomers” flooded to settle Oklahoma in this year. The Great Johnstown Flood devastated Pennsylvania during it, the first year where the “Billion Dollar Congress” met. For ten points, name this year in which Benjamin Harrison began his term as US President.",
      "answer": "1889"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man ordered that the government store its funds in vaults rather than banks as part of the independent treasury he created. The popularity of this man plummeted after Charles Ogle accused him of lavish spending in the Gold Spoon Oration. This man was forced to carry out his predecessor’s Specie Circular executive order, leading to the Panic of 1837. For ten points, name this Democratic president, a Dutch-American from New York.",
      "answer": "Martin van Buren"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the final scene of this work, a blindfolded child waves a miniature American flag and the title character reads the inscription “Who cannot live with honor must die with honor” on a knife. This work’s most famous aria, “Un bel di vedremo,” describes the hope of seeing a puff of smoke on the horizon signaling the return of Lieutenant Pinkerton. For ten points, name this opera by Giacomo Puccini whose title character, Cio-Cio San, lives in early 20th century Japan.",
      "answer": "Madame Butterfly or Madama Butterfly"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man spent two weeks in the hospital before an event, causing Richard Daley to cry “they’ve embalmed him before he even died!” Dwight Eisenhower said “If you give me a week, I’ll think of one” contribution by this politician. This man’s 5 o’clock shadow and sickly frame hurt his performance in the first televised presidential debate against John F. Kennedy in 1960. For ten points, name this politician who recovered to win the 1968 and 1972 elections.",
      "answer": "Richard Nixon"
    },
    {
      "question": "Description acceptable. James Bradley notes that one participant of this event was shot by a sniper less than a month after this event; that man is Frank Sousley. Felix Wheldon used a depiction of this event for the Marine Corps War Memorial. Ira Hayes and Rene Gagnon were among the six people involved in this event, which Joe Rosenthal photographed at Mount Suribachi. For ten points, name this 1945 event in which the American colors were hoisted above a Japanese island.",
      "answer": [
        "the raising of the American flag on Iwo Jima",
        "equivalents that include all 3 parts",
        "acceptMountSuribachiinplaceof Iwo Jimabeforeit’smentioned",
        "promptonpartialanswers,including Battle of Iwo Jima"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A group of these people were tried at Destrehan after trying to seize New Orleans during the German Coast rebellion. Mosby Sheppard convinced James Monroe to use the Virginia militia against a group of these people led by Gabriel Prosser. These people were prohibited from learning to read or write in many states after Nat Turner led a rebellion. For ten points, name this class of people who were the subject of the Emancipation Proclamation, which freed them.",
      "answer": "American slaves s"
    },
    {
      "question": "This war included the controversial hanging of members of the St. Patrick’s Battalion for desertion. TheSpotResolutionswereAbrahamLincoln’sCongressionalattempttodiscoverthespotwhereAmerican troops were shot near the Nueces [nu-AY-sis] River in the leadup to this war. This war ended with the Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo, which gave California to the winners. For ten points, name this war in which the United States prevailed over its southern neighbor.",
      "answer": "Mexican-American War"
    },
    {
      "question": "After manning a machine gun during this event, Dorie Miller became the first African-American to receive a Navy Cross. A perpetrator of this event was apprehended in the Niihau incident by civilians. This event was carried out in two waves by Vals and Zeroes, who sunk the Arizona. President Roosevelt lamented “a date that will live in infamy” in a speech to Congress after, for ten points, what surprise attack that brought America into World War II?",
      "answer": "attack on Pearl Harbor"
    },
    {
      "question": "Security guard William Barry and busboy Karl Uecker failed to prevent this event. A Boris Yaro photograph of this event depicts a crouched Juan Romero, who had been shaking hands with the target at the time. This event, which occurred prior to a press conference regarding the defeat of Eugene McCarthy in the California primary, took place at the Ambassador Hotel. For ten points, name this 1968 event in which Sirhan Sirhan shot a presidential candidate.",
      "answer": "assassination or murder, shooting, etc. of Robert F. Kennedy or assassination of RFK"
    },
    {
      "question": "In opposition to this policy, Robert Taft declared that “you certainly don’t want the same gum back.” This policy inspired the Canadian “Billion Dollar Gift” and grew out of the “destroyers for bases” agreement. This policy, which was compared to giving a neighbor a garden hose to put out a fire, marked the end of the Neutrality Acts. For ten points, name this 1941 program that allowed for the United States to supply the Allies with food and weapons.",
      "answer": "Lend-Lease Act"
    },
    {
      "question": "After this event, Hyman Rickover testified that no “simple, easy gimmick” explains why his program had never experienced an event like this disaster. Former Dartmouth President John Kemeny chaired a commission investigating this event. William Scranton falsely reported that Metropolitan Edison claimed that “everything was under control” after this event, which occurred at a facility named for its distance from Middletown, Pennsylvania. For ten points, name this 1979 accident, the worst nuclear disaster in American history.",
      "answer": "Three Mile Island nuclear accident or disaster, meltdown, etc."
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1944, a ship named for this figure ran aground on a sandbank in the Thames Estuary; its masts rise above the water, and it still holds nearly 3 million pounds of live explosives. Benedict Arnold replaced this man as leader of an invasion after he was killed by a burst of grapeshot to the head and thighs, contrary to the musical Hamilton, which claimed he “took a bullet in the neck in Quebec.” For ten points, name this Irishman who fought for the colonists during the American Revolution, leading the 1775 invasion of Canada.",
      "answer": "Richard Montgomery"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man once wrote a letter to New York Congressman John J. LaFalce complaining of how “a woman can’t even carry Mace in her purse.” This man, who called for the murder of Lon Horiuchi for killing of the wife of Randy Weaver, rented a Ryder truck to carry out an attack that was co-plotted by Terry Nichols. Over 160 people were killed in a 1995 attack by, for ten points, what domestic terrorist who bombed the Alfred P. Murrah building in Oklahoma City?",
      "answer": "Timothy McVeigh"
    },
    {
      "question": "The “bat-wing” floor plan that once characterized these places was described in the Kirkbride design. After a Quaker woman died in one of these places, William Tuke founded the York Retreat, which developed the “moral treatment” method used in these places. The reform of jails, schools, and these institutions was promoted by Dorothea Dix before she worked as a nurse in the Civil War. For ten points, name these facilities where patients with disorders like schizophrenia were often abused in 19th century America.",
      "answer": [
        "psychiatric hospitals or mental hospitals",
        "mental asylums",
        "insane asylums"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "At the 1205 Battle of Adrianople, this man led a force that joined Baldwin the I of the Latin Empire to fight Tsar Kaloyan of the Bulgars. Michael Comnenus may have ordered the blinding of this man, and his daughter Anna married the king of Serbia, Stefan Nemanjic. This man, who introduced the silver grosso as currency in Venice, joined crusaders at the St. Mark’s Basilica. Isaac II was replaced with Alexius Angelus in the Fourth Crusade by, for ten points, what blind Doge of Venice?",
      "answer": "Enrico Dandolo"
    },
    {
      "question": "This President signed an Agricultural Marketing Act that created a Federal Farm Board, a plan opposed to the controversial-yet-popular McNary-Haugen plan. This man’s administration began a multi-billion dollar intervention program called the Reconstruction Finance Corporation that gave loans to railroads and banks, an active response to the nation’s worst economic performance of the 20th century. For ten points, name this US President who was replaced during the Great Depression by Franklin Roosevelt.",
      "answer": "Herbert Hoover"
    },
    {
      "question": "After this ruler ignored a plea for peace, John Dickinson drafted a “Declaration of the Causes and Necessity of Taking Up Arms.” This monarch appointed Lord Rockingham as Prime Minister in favor of Lord Grenville. The Olive Branch Petition was rejected by this ruler, who later was forced to accept peace with the United States after Lord Cornwallis’s men surrendered at Yorktown. For ten points, name this British king during the American Revolution.",
      "answer": "George III"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man defeated incumbent New Deal opponent Roscoe Patterson in a 1934 Senate election. In one speech, this man acknowledged the success of a recent economic program that started with “16 free nations;” that speech supported the Marshall Plan, which had been signed into law by this man in 1948. For ten points, name this man who won the first presidential election after World War II and succeeded Franklin Roosevelt.",
      "answer": "Harry Truman"
    },
    {
      "question": "This ship’s second to last captain, Daniel Dow, resigned from stress after the Louis and Laverock failed to escort it. The Juno arrived too late to rescue this ship’s passengers, which included Alfred Vanderbilt. Failure to follow a zig-zag pattern may have led to this ship’s sinking. William Jennings Bryan resigned after the downing of this ship, which was carrying 50 tons of shell casings at the time it was destroyed in the North Atlantic. 128 Americans drowned on this ship. For ten points, the United States entered World War I after what ship was torpedoed by a U-Boat?",
      "answer": "RMS Lusitania"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s administration is seen as the beginning of the American spoils system, because he replaced 919 officials upon election. This man supposedly declared “Marshall has made his decision, now let him enforce it” in response to the Supreme Court decision in Worcester v. Georgia. The Indian Removal Act was put into law by, for ten points, what seventh president of the United States?",
      "answer": "Andrew Jackson"
    },
    {
      "question": "The 1st Texas Infantry lost over 80 percent of its men at this battle, the highest regimental casualty rate on either side of the entire war. George Anderson was one of six generals killed at this battle, having suffered a wound while defending the Bloody Lane. This battle, commonly known as Sharpsburg in the South, took place on September 17th, 1862 and resulted in over 22,000 casualties. For ten points, name this battle in Maryland, the bloodiest single-day battle of the Civil War.",
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Antietam",
        "Battle of Sharpsburg before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was elected to the House in 1946 by labeling his opponent, Jerry Voorhis, a communist. This man won a Senate seat over “the Pink Lady,” Helen Gahagan Douglas, in 1950, but served less than a full term and resigned after successfully running for Vice President. He survived that campaign by delivering the “Checkers” speech. Dwight Eisenhower ran for President on a ticket with, for ten points, what politician who later won two Presidential elections but resigned after Watergate?",
      "answer": "Richard Nixon"
    },
    {
      "question": "In this state, Benjamin Lincoln surrendered a major city on May 12, 1780 after being besieged by British forces for over a month. Defensive structures made of palmetto wood foiled British naval bombardments at Fort Moultrie in this state. Daniel Morgan’s army routed Banastre Tarleton’s dragoons in this state at the Battle of Cowpens. Nathaniel Greene besieged Camden in, for ten points, what southern US state where the Americans surrendered Charleston?",
      "answer": "South Carolina"
    },
    {
      "question": "A failed campaign against this man’s troops was bogged down by heavy river quagmires and called the Mud March. This man rose to prominence after the Battle of Seven Pines, where Joseph Johnston was wounded. Shortly after fighting a series of defensive battles at Spotsylvania and the Wilderness, this man spoke at Appomattox Courthouse with Ulysses S. Grant. For ten points, name this commander of the Army of Northern Virginia whose surrender ended the American Civil War.",
      "answer": "Robert E. Lee"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1939, half of the United States moved this holiday a week earlier, causing a controversy that wasn’t resolved until a 1941 act of Congress. Sarah Josepha Hale helped convince Abraham Lincoln to proclaim this holiday as a federal holiday in 1863. The inspiration for this holiday was an event attended by members of the Wampanoag tribe like Massasoit and Squanto in 1621. For ten points, name this holiday celebrating the first harvest of the Pilgrims in late November.",
      "answer": "Thanksgiving Day"
    },
    {
      "question": "Preludes to this event included the El Encanto arson and a feint towards Baracoa by the Santa Ana. The president allegedly wanted to “splinter the CIA in a thousand pieces” after their failure in this event. Brigade 2506, a force composed of exiles trained in Guatemala, was tasked with carrying out this event, which prompted its target to ally with the Soviet Union. John F. Kennedy authorized, for ten points, what 1961 failed invasion of Cuba?",
      "answer": "Bay of Pigs invasion"
    },
    {
      "question": "The command to conduct this event was allegedly caught on audio tape by Terry Strubbe. This event, which may have been caused by people throwing rocks at a patrolman’s Jeep, was witnessed by John Filo, who took a photograph of Mary Ann Vecchio kneeling next to Jeffrey Miller’s body. The President’s Commission on Campus Unrest was created in the wake of, for ten points, what tragedy in which the Ohio National Guard opened fire on Vietnam War protesters?",
      "answer": "Kent State shootings"
    },
    {
      "question": "One of these events divided its participants into “new” and “old” lights based on their fervor. Another of these events led Charles Finney to describe western New York as the “burned over district.” Samuel Davies was a leader of one of these events, during which humanity was compared to a spider hanging over a fire in the “Sinners in the Hands of an Angry God” sermon of Jonathan Edwards. For ten points, name these periods of American Christian religious revival.",
      "answer": "First and/or Second Great Awakenings"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man claimed that he drew from the general theory of relativity to create a new religion called Universalism. This man came to power after a foreign power invaded in Operation Weserubu¨ng, which enabled him to succeed Johan Nygaardsvold after King Haakon VII fled the country. In 1945, this founder of the Nasjonal Samling party was executed outside Akershus fortress for his collaboration with the Nazis. For ten points, name this treasonous president of Norway.",
      "answer": "Vidkun Quisling"
    },
    {
      "question": "A politician from this state was labeled “eccentric and unpredictable” by Isaiah Berlin because he founded his state’s Progressive Party and yet was a staunch isolationist. Another politician from this state created a short-lived Progressive Party to support his bid for the 1924 Presidential election. While campaigning on the Bull Moose ticket, itself a Progressive Party, Theodore Roosevelt was shot in this state by John Schrank. For ten points, name this state where the progressive La Follette family governed from Madison.",
      "answer": "Wisconsin"
    },
    {
      "question": "As Governor of New York, this man signed an act to gradually abolish slavery that, despite stating children of slaves were free, forced them into decades of indentured servitude. In 1795, this man negotiated the removal of British troops from the Northwest Territory with a treaty fixing many of the issues of the earlier Treaty of Paris. With Alexander Hamilton and James Madison, this man wrote the Federalist Papers. For ten points, name this first Chief Justice of the United States.",
      "answer": "John Jay"
    },
    {
      "question": "Lewis Schwellenbach succeeded this figure, who had an affair with Mary Harriman Rumsey, the founder of the Junior League, until her death. After the Triangle Shirtwaist Factory fire, this woman served as executive secretary for the New York Committee on Public Safety. Eleanor Roosevelt and this woman oversaw the development of She-She-She Camps during the New Deal. This drafter of the Social Security Act of 1935 was the first woman in the line of presidential succession. For ten points, name this Secretary of Labor under Franklin D. Roosevelt, the first female member of the Cabinet.",
      "answer": "Frances Perkins"
    },
    {
      "question": "Min Chueh Chang helped Gregory Pincus create a product meant for this purpose. The Woman Rebel was written by an activist supporting this action who was prosecuted under the Federal Comstock Law. Diaphragms were illegally smuggled into the United States to aid with this action, which was promoted by a Brownsville clinic that opened in 1916. Margaret Sanger and Planned Parenthood advocate for, for ten points, what type of medical care that assists in family planning and can prevent abortions?",
      "answer": [
        "contraception",
        "birth control",
        "family planning before mentioned",
        "prompt on women’s medical care"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This leader’s reputation suffered after being ambushed by Charles “No Flint” Grey in the Paoli Massacre, but he regained his prestige by leading a daring nighttime raid at the Battle of Stony Point. In this man’s most famous victory, he defeated the forces of the Western Confederacy and Blue Jacket, after which the Treaty of Greenville was signed. This man was sent by George Washington to subdue Native Americans in the Northwest Territory. For ten points, name this winner of the Battle of Fallen Timbers a Revolutionary-era brigadier general nicknamed “Mad Anthony.”",
      "answer": "“Mad” Anthony Wayne"
    },
    {
      "question": "During this man’s administration, Jay Mazur chanted “We are one” at a rally in Columbus Park during the largest-ever strike in New York’s Chinatown. This man described another strike, involving an organization led by Robert Poli, as “a peril to national safety” and gave Poli’s group 48 hours to return to their jobs. PATCO was de-certified after striking under this president, who argued the strike was illegal. For ten points, name this president who clashed with the air traffic controller union in the 1980s.",
      "answer": "Ronald Reagan"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Body of Liberties was established as a legal code for this colony, which was bounded by the “Old Colony Line.” Midwife Margaret Jones was hanged in this colony after her patients got sicker. John Cotton was an early settler in this colony, the first American colony to legalize slavery. During the Antinomian Controversy, Anne Hutchinson was banished from this colony. Governor John Winthrop delivered the “City upon a hill” sermon in, for ten points, what English colony founded by Puritans that was centered on Salem and Boston?",
      "answer": "Massachusetts Bay Colony"
    },
    {
      "question": "This organization was founded partially in response to the Springfield Race Riots of 1908, and helped investigate the Elaine Race Riot of 1919. As a result of this group’s actions, racial restrictions on military officers were removed during World War One. In 1915, this group organized a protest against the pro-KKK film, Birth of a Nation. For ten points, name this organization founded by W. E. B. Du Bois [[doo-BOYS]] to promote civil rights for African-Americans.",
      "answer": [
        "NAACP",
        "the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Arnold Constable & Company, which New York newspapers called the “Palace of Trade,” was the first American example of this type of business. Postmaster General John Wanamaker founded one of these businesses in Philadelphia, which housed the largest pipe organ in the world. One of these enterprises was developed from a mail-order catalog by A.C. Roebuck and Richard Sears. For ten points, name these retail companies that include Kohl’s and Macy’s.",
      "answer": "Department stores"
    },
    {
      "question": "The earliest known instance of this designation was an 836 AD link between Paderborn and Le Mans. Instances of this special bond increased significantly after World War Two, when Coventry was grouped with both Stalingrad and Dresden. Boston has eleven of these international relationships, while New York has more than one hundred. For ten points, name this type of connection intended to foster understanding, friendship, and tourism between cities in different countries.",
      "answer": [
        "Sister cities",
        "Twin towns"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This state’s only remaining Native American reservation was established by Anglican missionary William Duncan and the Tsimshian [[shim-SHEE-uhn]] people. This state’s senator Ted Stevens was criticized for pushing the “Bridge to Nowhere” project. During World War Two, Japanese invaders transported natives from this state's islands of Attu and Kiska to Hokkaido. For ten points, name this state, home to various Aleut and Inuit tribes, as well as the cities of Juneau and Anchorage.",
      "answer": "Alaska"
    },
    {
      "question": "The first of these machines in the United States was completed by Ernest O. Lawrence in 1930 and was used at the University of California-Berkeley. In a 1954 address to the American Physical Society, Enrico Fermi proposed building one of these machines in stable orbit around the circumference of the Earth. The current largest of these machines is located 175 meters below ground on the border of France and Switzerland, and is seventeen miles in circumference. For ten points, name these machines used in particle physics experiments to propel charged particles.",
      "answer": [
        "Particle accelerators or Particle colliders",
        "Cyclotron prior to \"1954\""
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "As Communist Party First Secretary in Sverdlovsk, this man carried out orders to tear down the house where the Romanovs were killed. This man became a non-voting member of the Politburo in 1986 after Mikhail Gorbachev appointed him mayor of Moscow. This man’s visit to a Houston, Texas grocery store in 1989 is suspected to have contributed to the downfall of the Soviet Union. For ten points, name this political dissident and first President of the Russian Federation.",
      "answer": "Boris Yeltsin"
    },
    {
      "question": "Marian Anderson performed in this type of work only once, appearing as Ulrica. Marietta Alboni often played “breeches roles” in works of this type, whereas Adelina Patti played coloratura roles. Leontyne Price, an African-American performer in this genre, was advised to not make her debut in the stereotypical slave role of Aida, instead debuting as Leonora in Il Trovatore. For ten points, name this form of theatre, in which Camilla Williams performed as Mimi, Bess, and Madama Butterfly.",
      "answer": "Opera 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 4"
    },
    {
      "question": "Following this event, the Rogers Commission was appointed to investigate its cause. Members of that commission included Chuck Yeager, Neil Armstrong, and Richard Feynman, who demonstrated, during a televised hearing before Congress, how defective O- rings caused this event. In an emotional speech about this event, Ronald Reagan quoted the poem “High Flight.” For ten points, what space shuttle disaster claimed the lives of seven astronauts, including Christa McAuliffe?",
      "answer": "Challenger disaster"
    },
    {
      "question": "The first leader of this organization, former Treasury Secretary Thomas Ewing, Sr., served in that role under Zachary Taylor and Millard Filmore. In 1983, the leader of this department, James G. Watt, banned the Beach Boys and the Grass Roots from playing Independence Day concerts on the National Mall. If she is confirmed by the Senate, New Mexico congresswoman and Laguna Pueblo member Deb Haaland will become the first Native American to lead, for ten points, what executive department in charge of managing federal lands?",
      "answer": "United States Department of the Interior"
    },
    {
      "question": "This person lobbied for the 1831 Copyright Act, the first major revision to American copyright law. This author once edited the Federalist newspaper The American Minerva and wanted to end American reliance on British school books. This man’s “blue-backed spellers” were used to teach generations of young students to read and write. For ten points, name this man whose American Dictionary of the English Language was sold to the Merriam family after his death.",
      "answer": "Noah Webster"
    },
    {
      "question": "The only time this man held political office was as Ulysses Grant’s acting Secretary of War for seven weeks in 1869. After this man survived two bullet wounds at Shiloh, he was promoted to Major General. As he rampaged through the South, this commander employed “scorched earth” tactics to break the will of the Confederates, and captured Savannah as a “Christmas present” to President Lincoln. For ten points, name this Union leader who took Atlanta during his March to the Sea.",
      "answer": "William Tecumseh Sherman"
    },
    {
      "question": "One of the first modern arguments for this theory was advanced during the English Civil War by Thomas Hobbes in Leviathan. According to one work titled for this concept, man is \"born free and everywhere he is in chains.\" Espoused by Enlightenment thinkers such as Jean-Jacques Rousseau and John Locke, this concept is implicit in the United States Constitution. For ten points, what is this political theory suggesting that rulers derive their authority from the consent of the people?",
      "answer": "Social contract"
    },
    {
      "question": "In this state, Clark Kerr declined to expel student protestors belonging to the Mario Savio-led Free Speech movement. Allan Bakke [[BAHK-ee]] was denied entry to medical school in this state under an affirmative action policy upheld in a 1978 Supreme Court decision. In 2020, a judge ruled that this state’s university system can no longer use ACT and SAT scores as a factor in admissions. For ten points, what state’s public university system includes campuses at Irvine and Berkeley?",
      "answer": "California"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Declaration of Independence said that this practice forced Americans “to become the executioners of their friends and Brethren.” This practice, designed to fulfill needs caused by the Napoleonic Wars, was one of the chief causes of the War of 1812. Thomas Jefferson signed the Embargo Act to combat this action after it occurred between the USS Chesapeake and HMS Leopard. For ten points, name this practice perpetrated by the Royal Navy to increase the number of its sailors.",
      "answer": "Impressment"
    },
    {
      "question": "An early holder of this title in Russia, Avdotia Istomina, worked with Charles-Louis Didelot [[dee-deh-LOH]] during the Romantic period. The first major holder of this title in the United States, Maria Tallchief, was also the first indigenous woman to achieve this rank. This rank is higher than sujet [[soo-ZHAY]] or coryphée [[kor-ee-PHAY]], and is considered equivalent to the Premier Danseur Noble [[prem-YAY danh-SEUR NOH-bluh]] for men. For ten points, name this title held by Misty Copeland and Anna Pavlova, a term for excellent female performers in dance companies.",
      "answer": "Prima ballerina assoluta"
    },
    {
      "question": "This general was sent to Illinois to lead in the Black Hawk War, arriving just in time to negotiate the war’s end. This man oversaw the process of Indian Removal from Florida, and though he never graduated from West Point, this man holds the distinction of being the longest-serving general in American history. During the Civil War, this man developed the Union strategy known as the Anaconda Plan. For ten points, name this American general who defeated Santa Anna and captured Mexico City in 1847.",
      "answer": "Winfield Scott"
    },
    {
      "question": "This author of My Larger Education and The Man Farthest Down received support from Andrew Carnegie when he established the National Negro Business League in 1900. This leader faced a backlash after giving the Atlanta Compromise speech in support of white political rule. Author of the autobiography, Up From Slavery, this man was the first African- American to be depicted on a United States postage stamp. For ten points, name this first president of the Tuskegee Institute.",
      "answer": "Booker T. Washington"
    },
    {
      "question": "Edward R. Murrow ran an episode of See It Now that criticized this politician for his interrogation of Annie Lee Moss. This man, who ran for Senate on the slogan \"Congress needs a tail-gunner,\" was chastised by Joseph Welch with the question, “have you no sense of decency?” For ten points, name this Wisconsin senator who claimed to have a list of 205 known communists in the state department, driving the Second Red Scare.",
      "answer": "Joseph McCarthy"
    },
    {
      "question": "As a lawyer, this man worked on Senator John Smith's expulsion case and served as Sam Houston's attorney after the latter caned William Stanbery. This man's most famous effort came during an episode in which he was a dinner guest to Vice Admiral Alexander Cochrane [[\"COCK\"-rin]] aboard the HMS Tonnant. This man composed a song to the tune of \"To Anacreon in Heaven\" during the bombardment of Fort McHenry. For ten points, name this American composer of \"The Star-Spangled Banner.\"",
      "answer": "Francis Scott Key"
    },
    {
      "question": "In this nation, Paul Schäfer [[SHAY-fer]] led an agrarian community known as Dignity Colony that doubled as a post-war refuge for Nazis. The economic policy of a regime in this nation was influenced by the El Ladrillo [[lah-DREE-yoh]] study, first published by the \"Chicago Boys.\" A left-wing leader likely killed himself while defending this nation's Moneda [[moh-NEH-dah]] Palace. Augusto Pinochet [[pee-noh-SHEH]] took power in a 1973 coup in, for ten points, what South American nation?",
      "answer": [
        "Republic of Chile",
        "República de Chile"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In this ecosystem, deaths attributed to the mountain pine beetle created ladder fuels that resulted in a 1988 wildfire. Drawings and paintings from the Hayden Expedition and the photographs of William Henry Jackson helped make the case for this place's status. The 4900 bison which live here comprise a namesake herd that is the largest in the United States. In March 1872, the first national park status was granted to, for ten points, what Wyoming-centered home of Old Faithful?",
      "answer": "Yellowstone National Park"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man used the proceeds from his Lancaster Caramel Company to start his most famous business. This man built a namesake \"Industrial\" boarding school in a company town he established in Pennsylvania in 1903. During World War Two, this man’s factories produced \"Ration D Bars,\" a special type of confectionary designed to resist melting. For ten points, name this American founder of a chocolate bar and confectionary company.",
      "answer": "Milton Snavely Hershey"
    },
    {
      "question": "A pilot from this nation unwittingly earned a one-hundred thousand dollar prize from the U.S. Air Force when he turned over of a Soviet MiG-15 fighter. Hatchet-wielding soldiers from this nation killed American servicemen in the Joint Security Area, to which the U.S. responded by mobilizing an entire taskforce to cut down a poplar tree in Operation Paul Bunyan. The Demilitarized Zone is shared between a southern neighbor and, for ten points, what East Asian nation dominated for seven decades by the Kim family?",
      "answer": [
        "North Korea",
        "Democratic People's Republic of Korea",
        "or Chosŏn Minjujuŭi Inmin Konghwaguk",
        "or DPRK",
        "DPR Korea",
        "Bukhan"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Frederick Jackson Turner's Frontier Thesis claims \"American Democracy\" was not established on this object or the Susan Constant. The springing of a leak by the accompanying Speedwell led to William Bradford deciding to solely use this ship for a western voyage. A rudimentary government for Plymouth known as its namesake \"Compact\" was signed on this vessel. For ten points, name this ship that transported the Pilgrims to the New World.",
      "answer": "Mayflower 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 3"
    },
    {
      "question": "A representative from this U.S. state spit tobacco juice in the face of Connecticut politician Roger Griswold. This home-state of Matthew Lyon was primarily led during its time as an independent republic by Thomas Chittenden. This was the first state outside of the Thirteen Colonies to ratify the U.S. Constitution and was home to Ethan Allen and the Green Mountain Boys. For ten points, name this New England state once claimed by New Hampshire.",
      "answer": [
        "Vermont",
        "Vermont Republic",
        "or République du Vermont",
        "State of Vermont",
        "or État du Vermont"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A congratulatory email sent to this man was allegedly one of only two emails sent by Bill Clinton during his presidency. Though not John McCain, this man’s acceptance of a $200,000 loan made him a member of the Keating Five. A record three-and-a-half hour flight from L.A. to New York was conducted by this man before being chosen as a member of the Mercury Seven. The lone occupant on a five-hour flight in 1962 aboard Friendship 7, for ten points, who was this astronaut, the first American to orbit the Earth?",
      "answer": "John Glenn or John Herschel Glenn Jr."
    },
    {
      "question": "In his treatise, Thoughts on Government, this man wrote that “Politics is the Science of human happiness.” As a member of the Second Continental Congress, this man predicted that American independence would be celebrated on July 2nd. As a lawyer, this man successfully defended Thomas Preston and the other British soldiers who perpetrated the Boston Massacre. For ten points, name this Massachusetts statesman who also served as the first vice president and second president of the United States.",
      "answer": "John Adams"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city behind the Warwick Line was defended in a siege by Confederate John B. McGruder during the Peninsular Campaign of the U.S. Civil War. This city is one of three sites on Virginia’s Historic Triangle, along with Williamsburg and Jamestown. Redoubt 10 at this site was assaulted by Alexander Hamilton, and it fell after a blockade by the forces of the Comte de Grasse. For ten points, name this town that was the site of Cornwallis’s 1781 surrender during the American Revolutionary War.",
      "answer": [
        "Yorktown, Virginia",
        "Battle of Yorktown",
        "or Siege of Yorktown 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 4"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A victim of one of these attacks attempted to fold one thousand origami cranes to rid herself of a perpetual illness caused by one of these events, the orders for which were transmitted by General Thomas T. Handy. The Flying Fortress Enola Gay dropped a payload known as the \"Little Boy\" during the first of these events. For ten points, name these attacks by the United States on Japan, the only recorded nuclear bombings in history.",
      "answer": [
        "Atomic Bombings of Hiroshima and Nagasaki",
        "Atomic Bombings of Japan",
        "\"Nuclear\" in place of \"Atomic\""
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "To criticize a man holding this position, Buzz Windrip, Doremus Jessup uses the periodical The Vermont Vigilance in the Sinclair Lewis novel, It Can't Happen Here. Prior to the events of Philip K. Dick's The Man in the High Castle, the successor of John Nance Garner, John W. Bricker, held this political position but failed to prevent an Axis occupation of North America. Phyllis Wheatley wrote \"To his Excellency General Washington\" about a holder of, for ten points, what executive position?",
      "answer": [
        "President of the United States of America",
        "American President",
        "U.S. in place of United States 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 5"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Like William Jennings Bryan, this man won a significant portion of electoral votes in multiple elections without becoming president. This man negotiated an end to the Nullification Crisis with his contemporary, John Calhoun. This Whig negotiated the admission of California into the Union three decades after accomplishing a similar feat with Missouri. For ten points, name this \"Great Compromiser\" from Kentucky.",
      "answer": "Henry Clay Sr. 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 6"
    },
    {
      "question": "This politician dubbed the Smedley Butler-alleged \"Business Plot\" a \"Cocktail Putsch.\" This man's first act in office was to order the arrest of gangster \"Lucky\" Luciano, just before this man instituted a ban on the sale of artichokes. This collaborator of Robert Moses curbed the strength of Tammany Hall and was the first Italian-American to serve as mayor of a major city. A Queens airport is named for, for ten points which New York City mayor during the 1930s and '40s?",
      "answer": "Fiorello La Guardia"
    },
    {
      "question": "A subspecies of this animal named for the London Underground is thought to have caused a human encephalitis [[en-seh-fah-LAI-tiss]] outbreak in New York City. A \"wooden wonder\" manufactured by de Havilland and named for this animal was a high-speed light bomber used in World War Two. A Central American coastal kingdom that shares its name with this animal became a British protectorate before being annexed by Nicaragua. A major vector for historical and modern diseases like Yellow Fever and Malaria is, for ten points, what blood-sucking insect?",
      "answer": [
        "Mosquitoes",
        "Culicidae",
        "London Underground Mosquitoes",
        "Mosquito Coast"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The Kit Carson scouts were former members of this organization who defected to the United States. Backed by the People's Army, this force killed 3,000 pro-American citizens in Hue [[WAY]] during the Tet Offensive. A northern country supplied armaments to this organization via the Ho Chi Minh Trail. A prolonged guerilla war against U.S. forces was fought by, for ten points, what communist paramilitary group during a mid-20th century war?",
      "answer": [
        "Viet Cong",
        "National Liberation Front of South Vietnam",
        "or Mặt trận Dân tộc Giải phóng Miền Nam Việt Nam 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 8"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In self-defense, this man murdered a mutinous sailor named Blackton on the island of Tobago. Years after completing his most notable service, this man became a rear admiral in the Russian Imperial Navy under Catherine the Great. When encountering the Serapis, this man supposedly shouted, \"I have not yet begun to fight!\" For ten points, name this captain of the Bonhomme Richard [[bohn-ohm-ree-SHAHRD]] and Revolutionary War hero, sometimes called the \"Father of the American Navy.\"",
      "answer": [
        "John Paul Jones",
        "John Paul"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In an effort to promote this policy, the Technicolor film The Gang's All Here, starring Carmen Miranda, was partially subsidized by the federal government. The immediate effect of this policy ended the lengthy occupation of Haiti and terminated the Platt Amendment, which had established U.S. hegemony over Cuba. Non-interventionism in Latin America was promoted by, for ten points, which New Deal-era foreign policy?",
      "answer": [
        "Good Neighbor Policy",
        "Política de Buena Vecindad",
        "or Política de Boa Vizinhança"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This woman was travelling with Laura Havilland when she was bruised by a streetcar conductor, leading to the desegration of public transit in Washington, D.C. Earlier, this woman said she wanted to \"fill her pint of intellect\" in a speech in Akron. For 10 points, name this former slave who advocated for abolition and women's equality in the \"Ain't I A Woman\" speech.",
        "answer": "Sojourner Truth"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What attorney, who later became President of the United States upon the assassination of James Garfield, filed the suit that desegregated public transit in New York City?",
        "answer": "Chester Alan Arthur"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This woman was one of the first district attorneys in New York's Special Victims Bureau, and\nshe wrote the Democratic National Committee's rules on superdelegates. George H.W. Bush was\naccused of disrespecting her in a 1984 debate. For 10 points, name this first woman to run as a\nmajor-party Vice-Presidential candidate, appearing on the losing Walter Mondale ticket.",
        "answer": [
          "Geraldine Ferraro",
          "Ferraro"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Mondale-Ferraro ticket only won Washington, D.C. and what home state of\nMondale, which later elected Jesse Ventura governor?",
        "answer": "Minnesota"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was advised by the author of Germany is Our Problem, Henry Morgenthau, as well\nas by a man who later became a conservative, Raymond Moley. This man's unofficial advisors\nwere recruited largely from Columbia University's law school and were led by Rexford Tugwell.\nThe \"brain trust\" advised, for 10 points, what man during his four terms as U.S. President?",
        "answer": [
          "Franklin Delano Roosevelt",
          "F Roosevelt",
          "FDR"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Roosevelt was more formally advised by what Secretary of War during World War II,\nwho had previously articulated a namesake \"doctrine\" refusing to recognize Japanese conquests\nas Secretary of State?",
        "answer": [
          "Henry Stimson",
          "Stimson"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This event was ended when Attorney General Richard Olney noticed that it was interfering with delivery of the U.S. Mail, giving him broad powers to restrict it. A refusal to intervene in this event made John Peter Altgeld, the governor of Illinois, a hero to the labor movement. For 10 points, name this 1894 Eugene V. Debs-organized strike against a rail car manufacturer.",
        "answer": "Pullman Strike"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Debs received 6% of the vote in which presidential election year, the largest amount ever recorded by a 4th place candidate?",
        "answer": "1912"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Offshoots identified with this larger religion in the United States include the Five Percenters and Ten Percenters. Timothy Drew believed that a large number of Americans were descended from practitioners of this religion. Wallace Fard founded another American example of this religion. For 10 points, name this religion whose black practitioners in the U.S. included Malcolm X.",
        "answer": "Islam"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The black Muslim leader Louis Farrakhan organized what 1995 demonstration in Washington, D.C. which did not quite attract the number of people in its name?",
        "answer": "Million Man March"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This President chose to break the Great Railroad Strike. This man's election was secured when David Davis took a Senate seat, leaving Joseph Philo Bradley with the deciding vote on the Electoral Commission. This husband of the temperance advocate \"Lemonade Lucy\" won a contested election over Samuel Tilden. For 10 points, name this victor in 1876.",
        "answer": "Rutherford B. Hayes"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Tilden had come to prominence and won the Democratic nomination after crusading against what Tammany Hall boss in New York?",
        "answer": "William \"Boss\" Tweed"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This event was repeated in Charleston upon the London and Magna Carta, and in Annapolis on the Peggy Stewart. This event was begun by the code words \"this meeting can do nothing more to save the country\" and inspired the passage of the first Intolerable Act. For 10 points, name this 1773 event in which the Sons of Liberty dressed as Mohawks and raided a British cargo ship.",
        "answer": "Boston Tea Party"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What leader of the Sons of Liberty and cousin of an American President was accused of organizing the Tea Party?",
        "answer": "Samuel Adams"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A hill creatively named Cornhill provided much of the early food for this colony, which was founded near Cole’s Hill. Josiah Cotton served as this colony’s Register of Deeds for some time. Its militia was run by Miles Standish, and William Bradford served as governor for this colony. For ten points, what early colony was founded by Pilgrims attempting to find Virginia by sailing on the Mayflower?",
        "answer": "Plymouth Colony"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Samoset and this other English-speaking Native American from the Wampanoag tribe helped the first Pilgrims survive the winter, an event commemorated as the First Thanksgiving.",
        "answer": "Squanto"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "John Howard Payne chronicled this tribe in the 19th century. They fought alongside the British during the Second Tuscarora War. This tribe’s “beloved women” were allowed to serve on councils, and included Nancy Ward, who warned Revolutionary soldiers about an impending attack by her cousin, Dragging Canoe. For ten points, name this Native American group, the most populous of the Five Civilized Tribes and the subject of the Supreme Court decision Worcester v. Georgia.",
        "answer": "Cherokee"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One of these was developed by Sequoyah for the Cherokee people in the late 1810s. Many figures in it were drawn from Linear B and Cyrillic.",
        "answer": [
          "alphabet",
          "syllabary"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Battle of Amiens occurred during an offensive named for this many days, which saw the breaking of the Hindenburg Line. This number of days also names a period that began when a certain man landed near Cannes after escaping from exile on Elba. That period of this length was ended by Napoleon’s defeat at Waterloo. For ten points, name this number, which names a really long war between France and England.",
        "answer": "100"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Meuse-Argonne Offensive, part of the Hundred Days Offensive, saw the participation of the American Expeditionary Force led by this American general.",
        "answer": "John J. Pershing"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man, whose “treatment” intimidated opponents by moving uncomfortably close to them, was mentored by Speaker of the House Sam Rayburn. A close-up of a young girl’s eye cuts to a nuclear explosion in his controversial “Daisy” Ad. In a speech at the University of Michigan, this president outlined Head Start and Medicare as parts of his Great Society. For ten points, name this Texan who became president after John F. Kennedy was assassinated.",
        "answer": "Lyndon Baines Johnson or LBJ"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1968, Johnson bemoaned that he had “lost middle America” after this longtime CBS Evening News host spoke about the failures of the Vietnam War.",
        "answer": "Walter Cronkite"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Robert J. Walker bribed Congressmen to approve of this action, which was negotiated by Eduard de Stoeckel. The Julian calendar was immediately replaced after this action, and Charles Sumner delivered a post-Civil War speech in favor of this action. Until the discovery of gold in the Klondike, this event was derided as “Seward’s Folly”. For ten points, name this $7.2 million purchase, roughly equal to 2 cents an acre, in which the U.S. acquired the future 49th state.",
        "answer": [
          "Purchase of Alaska",
          "equivalents"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Many landmarks in Alaska, including the strait separating it from Russia and the land bridge that once crossed it, are named for this Danish explorer who discovered some of the Aleutian islands.",
        "answer": [
          "Vitus Bering",
          "Bering Strait"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One of these works ends with the phrase “Swell the mighty chorus to bring us nearer to victory!” Another of these works ended with the phase “together we cannot fail” and defended the creation of the FDIC. Harry Butcher coined the name for these works, which ended with the Star-Spangled Banner. “On Drought Conditions” and “On the Banking Crisis” were two of the 30 of, for ten points, what speeches delivered in a calm, familiar style over the radio to the American people from 1933 to 1944?",
        "answer": "Fireside chats"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The last fireside chat, given in June 1944, opened a sales drive for these governmental financial products.",
        "answer": "Series E war bonds"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An 1856 law allowed the United States to claim Midway Atoll because it was a source of this commodity. The Haber-Bosch process for creating ammonia was invented when German access to caliche [ca-LEE-chay] and this commodity from the Peruvian and Chilean coasts was cut off in World War I. Nitrogen and other nutrients needed for fertilizers came from, for ten points, what valuable bat and seabird excrement?",
        "answer": "guano"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In addition to nitrogen, guano is an exceptional source of this element, whose salts were once leached out from plant ashes. This was the first metal element isolated via electrolysis by Sir Humphrey Davy, shortly before his work with sodium.",
        "answer": "potassium or K"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man’s retirement was delayed by a scandal concerning Louis Wolfson. The John Birch Society put up posters urging the impeachment of this man, and his court ruled school prayer unconstitutional in Engel v. Vitale. This Supreme Court justice’s court presided over cases which greatly expanded the rights of criminals, such as Gideon v. Wainwright. For ten points, name this liberal Chief Justice, a former Governor of California, who served from 1953 to 1969.",
        "answer": "Earl Warren"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In this 1966 Warren Court case, a “warning” to inform suspects of their Fifth and Sixth Amendment rights was made mandatory for police officers in certain arresting situations.",
        "answer": "Miranda v. Arizona"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Solomon Southwick was this party’s unsuccessful nominee for Governor of New York in 1828, and it grew in popularity after William Morgan’s alleged killing by a group on the Niagara River. This earliest 3rd party in the U.S. nominated William Wirt for President in the 1832 election. For ten points, name this single-issue party that eventually merged with the Whig Party and opposed a certain secret society.",
        "answer": "Anti-Masonic Party"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Anti-Masonic Party held the first one of these events in Baltimore in 1831, endorsing Wirt and Amos Ellmaker. The Democratic Party followed suit several months later with one of these events to replace John Calhoun with Martin Van Buren.",
        "answer": "nominating conventions for Presidential candidates"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "While attacking American cannons in this battle, Robert Abercromby told his troops “Push on, my brave boys.” At the end of this battle, Charles O’Hara attempted to surrender to the Comte de Rochambeau, but was directed to Benjamin Lincoln instead. One side in this battle attempted to retreat from Gloucester Point. British losses at this battle led to the Treaty of Paris. For ten points, name this defeat for General Cornwallis, the final major battle of the American Revolution.",
        "answer": [
          "Siege of Yorktown",
          "Battle of Yorktown"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "British efforts to reinforce Yorktown were ended after Thomas Graves lost to the Comte de Grasse in this naval engagement.",
        "answer": [
          "Battle of the Chesapeake",
          "Battle of Virginia Capes"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man vowed to never travel by train again after suffering an injured leg in the Hightstown rail accident with John Quincy Adams. Gideon Welles initially refused this man’s donation of his largest personal steamship to the Union Fleet, and this owner of the Staten Island Ferry feuded with James Fisk and Jay Gould over his railroad empire. For ten points, name this 19th century American, known as “Commodore” for his extensive transportation empire, whose philanthropy founded a university in Tennessee.",
        "answer": "Cornelius Vanderbilt"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Vanderbilt captained the ship at the center of this Supreme Court case, which held that Congress’s power over interstate commerce extended to navigation.",
        "answer": [
          "Gibbons v. Ogden",
          "either"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Alfred Moore and William Cushing recused themselves from this case, whose ruling affirmed that the Supreme Court did not have the right to issue writs of mandamus, thereby rendering Section 13 of the Judiciary Act of 1789 unconstitutional. The plaintiff in this case had been denied a commission of judgeship in the District of Columbia, which he had received as one of the “midnight appointments” of John Adams. For ten points, name this Supreme Court case presided by John Marshall that established judicial review.",
        "answer": "Marbury v. Madison"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The concept of judicial review had been endorsed in Federalist Paper No. 78 by this founding father.",
        "answer": "Alexander Hamilton"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A “re-education movement” by one side after this war killed over 100,000 suspected collaborators in the Bodo League massacre. The Hangang Bridge was destroyed during this conflict by one side to prevent an offensive, leading to the deaths of over 1,000 refugees. Aerial combat in this war took place over MiG Alley, and American entrance into this war led to heavy casualties at the Battles of Heartbreak Ridge and Pork Chop Hill. For ten points, name this 1950 to 1953 war that was ended by an armistice which established a demilitarized zone on its namesake peninsula.",
        "answer": "Korean War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In Operation Chromite, Douglas MacArthur led an amphibious landing at this city in 1950, then went on to re-capture Seoul.",
        "answer": "Inchon"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This nation’s motto, “Deo Vindice,” was developed by Thomas Semmes. The Stone Fleet was sunk to blockade this nation, which had two of its diplomats captured in the Trent Affair. Texas v. White rejected the claim that the U.S. was to recognize this nation, whose only Vice President was Alexander Stephens. For ten points, name this country led by Jefferson Davis which seceded from the Union to spark the U.S. Civil War.",
        "answer": [
          "Confederate States of America",
          "the Confederacy,",
          "C.S.A."
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The H.L. Hunley, one of these vehicles owned by the Confederacy, managed to sink the USS Housatonic, but was destroyed three times before finally abandoned.",
        "answer": "submarines"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One candidate in this election year chose Nathan Sanford as his running mate. William Crawford took third in this election, the only election after the Twelfth Amendment to be decided by the House of Representatives. Its fourth-place finisher, Henry Clay, was subsequently named Secretary of State. For ten points, John Quincy Adams was elected President in what year’s election, decried as a “corrupt bargain” by the runner-up, Andrew Jackson?",
        "answer": "Election of 1824"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Prior to the election, William Crawford served in this Cabinet position, also held in the 19th century by Albert Gallatin and Robert Walker.",
        "answer": "Secretary of the Treasury"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Panic of 1873 caused the Populist Party and advocates of this resource to push for the Bland-Allison Act. John Sherman proposed an 1890 act doubling the government’s purchasing of this resource. The first major discovery of this resource in the United States was the Comstock Lode in 1859. As a bimetallist, William Jennings Bryan supported the “freeing” of this resource in his “Cross of Gold” speech. For ten points, name this precious metal.",
        "answer": "silver"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Sherman Silver Purchase Act was signed into law under this president, who served between Grover Cleveland’s two terms.",
        "answer": "Benjamin Harrison"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man served as Thomas Dewey’s Vice Presidential running mate in 1948, though Dewey famously lost to Truman. Eisenhower initially called this man’s appointment to succeed Fred Vinson a “damned-fool mistake.” In 1954, this man used the phrase “with all deliberate speed” in his ruling to desegregate schools in Brown v. Board. For ten points, name this former governor of California who served as the Chief Justice of a notably liberal Supreme Court.",
        "answer": "Earl Warren"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Warren was recently surpassed as the longest-serving Governor of California by this man, who also served as governor from 1975-83.",
        "answer": "Jerry Brown"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One possibly apocryphal story about this man states that he fired at enemy troops with a crossbow while lying ill on a stretcher. Before embarking on his most famous campaign, this man put Isaac Komnemnos in chains after a raid on Cyprus. This man was victorious at the battle of Arsuf and managed to anger Leopold V of Austria during the siege of Acre, who later imprisoned him. After failing to conquer Jerusalem, this man was forced to negotiate peace with Saladin. For ten points, name this English leader of the Third Crusade, whose nickname refers to his bravery.",
        "answer": [
          "Richard I",
          "Richard the Lionhearted"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Richard the Lionheart would have worked with this red-haired German leader in the Third Crusade, had he not drowned in the Saleph River.",
        "answer": [
          "Frederick I",
          "Frederick Barbarossa"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Public Law 88-202 compelled testimony as requested by this group, whose members included Gerald Ford, CIA director Allen Dulles, and the Chief Justice of the Supreme Court. This group’s findings were intended to dispel fears of a conspiracy, and announced that a single bullet caused John Connally’s wounds and the mortal wound of his backseat passenger. For ten points, name this Presidential commission, established on November 29, 1963, that found Lee Harvey Oswald responsible for the assassination of JFK.",
        "answer": [
          "Warren Commission",
          "The President’s Commission on the Assassination of President Kennedy"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Warren Commission studied this document of the assassination, which was shot with a Bell & Howell Zoomatic and provides the clearest view of the murder. Frame 313 of this film shows the fatal shot.",
        "answer": "Abraham Zapruder’s film"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During one campaign, this man was criticized for owing a six-figure debt to Tiffany’s. With Dick Armey, this man proposed a set of legislation that included the “Taking Back Our Streets” Act and the “American Dream Restoration” Act; that legislation is often credited with fueling the Republican Revolution of 1994. For ten points, name this politician from Georgia who failed to win the Republican nomination for President in 2012 and served as Speaker of the House from 1995 to 1999.",
        "answer": "Newt Gingrich"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Gingrich’s promised platform for the Republican-majority Congress after the 1994 elections was given this three word name.",
        "answer": "Contract With America"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Marxist thought holds that this process creates a “reserve army.” Murray Rothbard suggested that social pressures make it difficult for wages to fall to a level that would completely eliminate this phenomenon. NAIRU models its “natural rate,” and it exists in structural, frictional, and seasonal types. Stagflation involves a counter-intuitive combination of this phenomenon and inflation. For ten points, name this economic phenomenon representing the number of people in the workforce who are unable to find jobs.",
        "answer": [
          "unemployment",
          "unemployment rate",
          "other elaborations"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A period of American stagflation in the 1970s was triggered, in part, by this man’s “shocking” series of economic actions, including a 90-day freeze on wages and prices and the closing of the “gold window,” breaking the Bretton Woods system.",
        "answer": [
          "Richard Nixon",
          "Nixon shock"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man defeated an attempted coup by the Anti-Party Group, led by former premier Georgi Malenkov. While serving as a political commissar, this man supported a disastrous attack at Kharkov. This man briefly increased freedoms after denouncing his predecessor’s policies and cult of personality in the Secret Speech. In a speech addressed to Westerners, this ruler claimed that “we will bury you.” For ten points, name this leader of the Soviet Union, the successor of Joseph Stalin.",
        "answer": "Nikita Khrushchev"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1959, Khrushchev informally debated Richard Nixon at the pro-capitalist American National Exhibition in one of these locations, coining the name for the debate.",
        "answer": "Kitchen debate"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This event led to the end of the 1798 Treaty of Alliance. A woman with a feathered hat has her belongings stuffed into the “national sack” in a depiction of this event, which prompted the Quasi-War. During this event, Pierre Bellamy was chastised by Charles Pinckney, who declared “no, not a sixpence!” For ten points, name this scandal in which American diplomats were asked for a bribe in order to meet with a French diplomat.",
        "answer": "XYZ Affair"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Two of the three American diplomats involved in the XYZ Affair left without ever accomplishing their goal: speaking with this French Foreign Minister.",
        "answer": "Charles Maurice de Talleyrand-P´erigord"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Santa Clara County’s 1886 lawsuit against a corporation of this type was relied upon by the Supreme Court in the Citizens United decision. John MacDonald resigned as the first Canadian Prime Minister due to bribes from this industry. One cartoon depicted a man in this profession rolling bowling balls down Wall Street after the Panic of 1873; that man, Jay Gould, took over the Union Pacific company in this industry. For ten points, name this lucrative 19th-century business conducted by the Southern Pacific, Central Pacific, and Union Pacific lines.",
        "answer": "railroads"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Promontory Summit, site of the inauguration of the United States’ firsttranscontinental railroad, is located in this Western state.",
        "answer": "Utah"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This businessman is named Secretary of the Interior in Philip Roth’s The Plot Against America. A product made by this man’s company is taken as the name of a Betelgeusian alien who saves Arthur Dent from the destruction of Earth in The Hitchhiker’s Guide to the Galaxy. In Aldous Huxley’s Brave New World, years are dated back to the year that this man’s company first produced the Model T. For ten points, name this American automobile manufacturer.",
        "answer": "Henry Ford"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This author of the aforementioned Hitchhiker’s Guide to the Galaxy wrote a short story in which Wowbagger the Infinitely Prolonged lands his UFO at the feet of Genghis Khan, calls him a tosspot, and flies away.",
        "answer": "Douglas Adams"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A poem addressed to this person imagines “A crown, a mansion, and a throne that shine, / With gold unfading” and begins by describing a “Celestial choir! enthron’d in realms of light.” An anecdote-filled biography of this man was written by Parson Weems in 1800; that biography claims that, at the age of six, this man could not tell a lie when asked if he cut down a cherry tree. For ten points, name this first president of the United States.",
        "answer": [
          "George Washington",
          "“To His Excellency General Washington”"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The poem “His Excellency General Washington” was written by which early female African- American poet?",
        "answer": "Phyllis Wheatley"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An expedition to this country ended in failure after the Battle of Verti´eres [vair-tee-air] and thousands of deaths to yellow fever. A civil war in this country called the War of the Knives ended with the exile of Andr´e Rigaud. This country’s constitution declared its Governor-General for Life to be its revolutionary leader Toussaint L’Ouverture. For ten points, name this French colony, the site of the only slave rebellion to successfully create a free state, found on the island of Hispaniola.",
        "answer": "Haiti"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Haiti became an empire after this man, L’Ouverture’s successor and lieutenant, declared himself emperor. He ordered an 1804 massacre of the white population that terrified the American South.",
        "answer": "Jean-Jacques Dessalines"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The acceptance of these legal items is governed by the “mailbox” rule. Severability clauses influence how eager courts are to amend these documents. A promissory estoppel may be granted by a court to remedy instances when these legal documents are violated. The “right to [these]” was enshrined by the Supreme Court during the Lochner Era. These documents typically consist of an offer, acceptance, intention, and consideration. For ten points, name these legal documents which establish legal duties between private individuals.",
        "answer": "contracts"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Lochner Era of “liberty of contract” was ended by a case involving the West Coast one of these institutions v. Parrish. In 1964, a similar institution called the Heart of Atlanta was denied the right to refuse service to African-Americans.",
        "answer": [
          "hotels",
          "motels"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This state’s Halifax Resolves was the first official colonial action calling for independence. The northern half of this state was also known as the Granville district before the Revolutionary War. The construction of Tryon Palace led to the Battle of Alamance in this state in 1771, where the War of the Regulation took place. Virginia Dare, the first English baby born in the Americas, disappeared in this state’s “Lost Colony” of Roanoke. For ten points, name this state whose capital is named for Sir Walter Raleigh.",
        "answer": "North Carolina"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Lost Colony at Roanoke left behind few clues to their disappearance; the biggest clue was the carving of this word into wood in the abandoned fort.",
        "answer": "CROATOAN"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1835, this man replaced a scheduled speaker, George Thompson, who canceled due to a $100 reward for the first person to injure him; this man was then nearly lynched. This man convinced Wendell Philips to give up his law practice in favor of focusing on his social movement, which this man advocated for in a Quaker newspaper, Genius of Universal Emancipation. The American Anti-Slavery Society was founded by, for ten points, what abolitionist and publisher of The Liberator?",
        "answer": "William Lloyd Garrison"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Garrison very briefly supported this general concept, for which the ACS advocated. The city of Monrovia was founded by supporters of, and participants in, this process. Description acceptable.",
        "answer": "repatriation movement"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "At one point, this man’s base of power was the North American city of New Castle. This man was imprisoned in the Tower of London for writing the tract The Sandy Foundation Shaken, and, while in jail, he further angered his captors by penning the anti-monarchist No Cross, No Crown. He incorporated principles of his faith into a Frame of Government for a colony he founded. For ten points, name this Quaker who oversaw the planning of Philadelphia in a state that now bears his name.",
        "answer": "William Penn"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "William Penn’s charter to Pennsylvania brought him into legal conflict with Charles, a member of this English family which held the title of Baron Baltimore. George, this family’s patriarch, received the original charter for Maryland.",
        "answer": [
          "Calvert family",
          "Charles and/or George Calvert"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Battle of Yellow Tavern was a decisive clash between two units of this type. At the start of the Overland Campaign, Philip Sheridan was recalled from the west to lead a unit of this type. A commander of this type of unit, John Buford, established the Union defensive lines at the Battle of Gettysburg. J.E.B. Stuart led a Confederate unit of this type, which were often used in the Civil War for raiding and reconnaissance. For ten points, give this term for units of mounted troops.",
        "answer": [
          "cavalry",
          "mounted units before read",
          "horsemen",
          "similar answers"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Sheridan’s cavalry was split off from this main Union army to defeat J.E.B. Stuart’s forces at the Battle of Yellow Tavern. George Meade commanded this army, named for a river, at the end of the Civil War.",
        "answer": "Army of the Potomac"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The death of Anne Fairfax led to ownership of this residence falling exclusively in the hands of its most famous inhabitant. In the 1850s, this building’s namesake Ladies’ Association bought it for preservation purposes. This house’s most famous resident lived here between the French and Indian War and Revolutionary War before being called on to become Commander-in-Chief of the Continental Army. For ten points, name this Virginia plantation owned by George Washington.",
        "answer": "Mount Vernon"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One of many replicas of Washington’s home at Mount Vernon was built for this organization in Seattle. Members of this group, which infamously refused to support a concert by Marian Anderson in 1939, must prove descent from an ancestor who assisted in American independence.",
        "answer": [
          "Daughters of the American Revolution",
          "DAR"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Natives who worked near this location were put on the silver roll as opposed to the gold roll, which was reserved for Americans and Europeans. John McCain was born in a U.S. administrative zone named for this location. The Torrijos-Carter Treaties specified a twenty year time frame for this location to pass from American control to that of a Central American country. For ten points, name this waterway, opened in 1914, that connects the Atlantic and Pacific Oceans.",
        "answer": [
          "Panama Canal",
          "Panama Canal Zone"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "American interest in the Panama Canal began when this president acquired rights to the area via the Hay-Bunau-Varilla Treaty.",
        "answer": "Theodore “Teddy” Roosevelt"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man sought and received aid from Haitian president Alexandre P´etion in exchange for adopting an emancipation policy. This leader’s Organic Decree cemented his status as president-liberator of one polity. This politician wrote the Cartagena Manifesto shortly before leading the Admirable Campaign. After liberating his homeland at the Battle of Carabobo, this man met at Guayaquil with Jos´e de San Mart´ın. For ten points, name this Venezuelan liberator of many South American countries.",
        "answer": "Sim´on Jos´e Antonio de la Sant´ısima Trinidad de Bol´ıvar y Palacios"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Bol´ıvar was the first president of this massive northern South American confederation that fell apart in 1831, just after Bol´ıvar’s death. This country shares part of its name with one of its successor countries.",
        "answer": "Gran Colombia"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this state, over 150 Wintu natives were killed during the Bridge Gulch Massacre. Lawrence Graham led an expedition into what is now this state following the Southern Emigrant Trail. Samuel Brannan amassed a fortune operating stores in this state, where Levi Strauss got his start selling dry goods. A discovery made at Sutter’s Mill triggered the migration of the “Forty-Niners” to, for ten points, what West Coast state, where population booms hit cities like Sacramento?",
        "answer": "California"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Another 19th century conflict against Native Americans in California took place in the Owens Valley, found east of this mountain range that includes Mount Whitney.",
        "answer": "Sierra Nevadas"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A county in this colony was sued by James Maury in the Parson’s Cause, which involved a dispute between this state’s established Anglican clergy and its government. The defense in that case was led by a member of this colony’s legislature, the House of Burgesses, who proclaimed “Give me liberty or give me death” in 1775. Patrick Henry was a politician from, for ten points, what American colony, the most populous before the Revolution, where the House of Burgesses met in Jamestown and Williamsburg?",
        "answer": "Virginia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A decade before declaring “Give me liberty or give me death!”, Patrick Henry gave an impassioned speech in the House of Burgesses in favor of the Virginia Resolves, a response to this 1765 act of Parliament.",
        "answer": "Stamp Act"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1962’s Robinson v. California, the Supreme Court used this amendment to strike down a California law criminalizing narcotic addiction. Modern applications of this amendment often rely on the idea of “evolving standards of decency.” Excessive bail is included in this amendment as an example of a prohibition found to violate “human dignity.” 1972’s Furman v. Georgia temporarily outlawed the death penalty by applying, for ten points, what Constitutional amendment that prohibits cruel and unusual punishment?",
        "answer": "8th Amendment to the US Constitution"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Roper v. Simmons cited the 8th Amendment while restricting the use of the death penalty for people with this characteristic. While the 26th Amendment expanded a certain right to more Americans, it did not expand that right to people with this characteristic. Description acceptable.",
        "answer": [
          "being younger than 18 years old",
          "any description of being young, a minor, a juvenile, a child, etc.",
          "being a teenager, despite the possible ambiguity that 19 presents"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This location, which is called the “Six Grandfathers” by the Lakota, was seized in violation of the Treaty of Fort Laramie. The “fifth icon” of this location, Benjamin Elk, posed for photographs with thousands of tourists. Historian Doane Robinson suggested the granite pillars at the Needles for this project, but was convinced by Gutzon Borglum to use another site in the Black Hills. For ten points, name this South Dakota monument featuring the faces of four US presidents.",
        "answer": "Mount Rushmore National Monument"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Earlier in his career, Gutzon Borglum worked on a monument at what Georgia site that honors Confederate leaders and hosted a KKK revival?",
        "answer": "Stone Mountain Park"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In his early military career, this man was given the honor of escorting the captured chief Black Hawk. Officials picked for this man’s Cabinet included Stephen Mallory and Judah Benjamin. His vice president, Alexander Stephens, stated that this man’s government was founded “upon the great truth” of racial inequality. Command of the Army of Northern Virginia was given to Robert E. Lee by, for ten points, what only president of the Confederate States of America?",
        "answer": "Jefferson Davis"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Judah Benjamin was the first man to hold this post in the Confederate cabinet; the analogous honor in the United States was claimed by Edmund Randolph.",
        "answer": [
          "Confederate and/or US Attorney General",
          "descriptions of the head of the Department of Justice"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man ordered the death penalty to be carried out on a man who had destroyed his own frontal lobe, Ricky Ray Rector. One of this man’s failed investments led to Jim and Susan McDougal being investigated by independent counsel Kenneth Starr. Proceedings in a lawsuit filed by Paula Jones against this man were cited in charges of perjury and obstruction of justice brought before the Senate in 1999. For ten points, name this politician whose sexual misconduct led to the second Presidential impeachment trial in history.",
        "answer": [
          "William Jefferson “Bill” Clinton",
          "William Jefferson Blythe"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Bill Clinton’s investments in the Madison Guaranty Savings and Loan, owned by the McDougals, concerned this failed Arkansas land development project, which names the ensuing scandal.",
        "answer": [
          "Whitewater Development Corporation",
          "any additional information that mentions Whitewater"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "John DeWitt’s support of this policy including the issuing of “Military Proclamation Number One.” This policy was implemented at sites like Heart Mountain and Topaz, as well as a site photographed by Ansel Adams and Dorothea Lange, Manzanar. Gordon Hirabayashi and Minoru Yasui both brought lawsuits against this policy. Executive Order 9066 put into effect, for ten points, what American policy of forced relocation and imprisonment of people of a certain Asian nationality during World War II?",
        "answer": "Japanese-American internment"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Supreme Court ruled that Japanese internment was constitutional in this 1944 case. This case has controversially not been officially overturned.",
        "answer": "Korematsu v. United States"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The longest serving Attorney General in US history began his term under this president. William Wirt served this man, who warmed relations with Britain by starting to demilitarize the Great Lakes via the Rush-Bagot treaty. William Plumber prevented this man from becoming the second unanimously elected President. During this man’s administration, Florida was purchased by his Secretary of State, John Quincy Adams. For ten points, name this US President who limited European involvement in the Americas with his namesake doctrine.",
        "answer": "James Monroe"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Another of Monroe’s Cabinet members was this Treasury Secretary, who finished third in the 1824 election and was thus essentially irrelevant in the ensuing “Corrupt Bargain.”",
        "answer": "William Crawford"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The First Amendment was applied to this industry in the so-called Miracle case involving distributor Joseph Burstyn. Joseph Breen held a powerful regulatory position in this industry when it was governed by the Hays Code. Dalton Trumbo was among a group of ten people who were blacklisted from this industry by the House Un-American Activities Committee in 1947. For ten points, name this industry once heavily censored by the MPAA, which today rates its products with tags such as PG-13.",
        "answer": [
          "film industry",
          "equivalents like motion picture industry",
          "Hollywood",
          "Hollywood Ten"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Hays Code weakened as films pushed its limits. In particular, this 1959 Billy Wilder comedy didn’t get Code approval due to its use of cross-dressing and risque themes, but it was a smash hit and Marilyn Monroe won a Golden Globe anyway.",
        "answer": "Some Like It Hot"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A politician from this state had his right arm amputated without anesthesia after it was severed by a German soldier. That Medal of Honor recipient from this state served as President pro tempore of the Senate until his 2012 death, after which Brian Schatz was appointed to the Senate by this state’s governor, Neil Abercrombie. The first Asian-American woman elected to the Senate, Mazie Hirono, is also from, for ten points, what US state that, in 2017, renamed its Honolulu International Airport?",
        "answer": "Hawai’i"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Honolulu International Airport was renamed in honor of this aforementioned war hero and US Senator, who passed away in 2012. This man is the second-longest serving Senator in US history.",
        "answer": "Daniel Inouye , but be lenient"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This politician promised “No more appeasement” during an event known as “Bloody Thursday,” in which he called in the National Guard to put down student protests at Berkeley. This politician, who signed the Therapeutic Abortion Act as governor, supported Barry Goldwater in his “A Time for Choosing” speech at the 1964 RNC. For ten points, name this Republican politician who was elected President in 1980.",
        "answer": "Ronald Reagan"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Ronald Reagan served as Governor of this western state from 1967 to 1975, where he put down student protests at Berkeley.",
        "answer": "California"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A tariff named for a politician from this state was altered 12 years later with the Payne-Aldrich Tariff; that longest-lasting tariff in American history was named after this state’s representative Nelson Dingley. Another politician from this state left the Democratic Party in 1856 after it supported the Kansas-Nebraska Act and became the first Republican Vice President; that native of this state served in a border struggle between this state and New Brunswick. For ten points, name this US state, the site of the Aroostook War in New England.",
        "answer": "Maine"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This native of Maine served as Abraham Lincoln’s first Vice President.",
        "answer": "Hannibal Hamlin"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this election year, Governor Scott Walker survived a recall election and Tammy Baldwin was elected as the first openly LGBT Senator in US history. A remark that “there are 47 percent of Americans who will vote for the President no matter what” hurt the Republican Presidential challenger in this election year, who ran on a ticket with Paul Ryan. For ten points, name this year in which Mitt Romney ran against Barack Obama, who won a second term as President.",
        "answer": "2012"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Scott Walker, Tammy Baldwin, and Paul Ryan all served as politicians from this state. Michigan, Pennsylvania, and this state had a margin of victory under 1% in favor of Donald Trump in 2016.",
        "answer": "Wisconsin"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This event was hosted by the subject’s daughter-in-law Jane because his wife was too sick to travel. The subject of this event was 68 years old at the time, a record later surpassed by Ronald Reagan. This event included a speech of over 8,000 words delivered by a man who wore no overcoat, despite cold winds and low temperatures. For ten points, name this March 4, 1841 event, essentially the only official action of the administration of the ninth US President before his death a month later.",
        "answer": "inauguration ceremony of William Henry Harrison"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Before his death, William Henry Harrison was able to make nominations for several Cabinet posts, including Thomas Ewing in this department. Other Secretaries in charge of this department included Roger Taney, Albert Gallatin, and Salmon Chase.",
        "answer": [
          "Treasury Department",
          "Secretary of the Treasury"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This battle’s victors followed up their success with an amphibious landing on Cavite. The McCulloch lost engineer Francis Randall to a heart attack in this battle. The flagship Olympia attacked after the signal “You may fire when you are ready, Gridley” was given at the start of this battle, in which only nine Americans were wounded. For ten points, name this decisive naval battle of the Spanish-American War in the Philippines.",
        "answer": "Battle of Manila Bay"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This admiral gave the command “You may fire when you are ready, Gridley” while leading the American fleet at Manila Bay.",
        "answer": "George Dewey"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A speech by this man notes “Fondly do we hope, fervently do we pray, that this mighty scourge of war may speedily pass away.” In that speech, this man advocated for a policy of “malice toward none with charity for all.” This man noted that a “government by the people... will not perish from this earth” in a speech that began “Four score and seven years ago...” For ten points, name this President who delivered the Gettysburg Address.",
        "answer": "Abraham Lincoln"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The quote “malice towards none with charity for all” derives from this Lincoln speech, delivered near the end of the Civil War.",
        "answer": "Lincoln’s second inaugural address"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ship’s passengers became the subject of a charity fund operated by James Pennington. Shortly after Joseph Cinque seized control of this ship, it was captured off of Long Island by the Washington. This ship, owned by Ramon Ferrer, had been redirected from Cuba to New York, triggering an 1841 Supreme Court case that ruled that this ship’s Mende captives were free. For ten points, name this Spanish ship that was taken over by a slave revolt.",
        "answer": "La Amistad"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This lawyer and former President argued on behalf of the Africans on board the Amistad before the Supreme Court in 1841.",
        "answer": "John Quincy Adams"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This act, which was passed over a presidential veto, was subjected to an amendment that Thomas Eagleton introduced dealing with rescue operations. A 60 day limit was imposed as part of this act, which was once violated by Bill Clinton for his actions in Kosovo. This act requires 48 hours notice to be given before conducting military operations. For ten points, name this 1973 bill that was intended to check the president’s power to enter into war without Congressional approval.",
        "answer": [
          "War Powers Act",
          "War Powers Resolution of 1973"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In December 2018, the Senate invoked the War Powers Act to end military assistance to Saudi Arabia in the wake of the murder of this journalist in October.",
        "answer": "Jamal Khashoggi"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "James Mason read this man’s last speech to the senate, which noted the South would “part in peace” if faced with “submission or resistance.” This Secretary of State for John Tyler supported the annexation of Texas, and as Vice President, this man drew the ire of Andrew Jackson when his wife Floride ignored the wife of Jackson’s Secretary of War in the Petticoat Affair. With Daniel Webster and Henry Clay, this man formed a triumvirate in the senate. For ten points, name this politician from South Carolina who promoted the doctrine of nullification.",
        "answer": "John Calhoun"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During the Petticoat Affair, this woman was snubbed by Floride Calhoun. It was rumored her first husband, John Timberlake, was distanced from her by her second husband, Jackson’s future Secretary of War.",
        "answer": "Margaret “Peggy” Eaton"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was the founder and first head of the insurance company Pacific Life. This man claimed that he employed a “degraded and distinct people” in the wake of their immigration boom; those Chinese-Americans were hired by this man for a project that ended with this man hammering in a spike in Utah. The Central Pacific Railroad was headed by, for ten points, what business tycoon who names a university in Palo Alto, California?",
        "answer": "Leland Stanford"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The “last spike” of the transcontinental railroad was driven in by Leland Stanford at this Utah location.",
        "answer": "Promontory Summit or Promontory Point"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Forty seven years before this case, Weeks v. U.S. dealt with the same rule, but only at the federal level. The defendant of this case worked under Shon Birns, a gambling kingpin. The “Fruit of the Poisonous Tree” doctrine was added to the Exclusionary rule that this decision applied to the states. The defendant argued that paraphernalia and books were taken without probable cause in, for ten points, what Fourth Amendment case that outlawed evidence taken from “unreasonable search and seizures?”",
        "answer": "Mapp v. Ohio"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Mapp v Ohio applied the Fourth Amendment to the states in a process that involves the 14th Amendment and is known by this term.",
        "answer": [
          "selective incorporation",
          "word forms"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The art of these people prominently features falcon warriors in a non-Chilean Birdman cult that formed part of a “Ceremonial Complex.” These people were succeeded by the Woodland culture, and they succeeded the Hopewell people. These people erected a series of cedar posts dubbed Woodhenge and constructed an earthen pyramid at Cahokia. For ten points, name this pre-Columbian Native American culture that inhabited land around a namesake river.",
        "answer": "Mississippian culture"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This mound at Cahokia is the largest Mississippian-era pyramid, of comparable area to the Great Pyramid of Giza.",
        "answer": "Monks Mound"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "George Washington Cabell from Tennessee led a committee that decided to revise this act instead of preparing for war. The British violation of neutrality during the Chesapeake Affair encouraged Congress to pass this act, which was later expanded in the Non-Intercourse Act. This act was personified as a turtle in a political cartoon biting a man who says “Oh! This cursed Ograbme.” For ten points, name this economically crippling 1807 act that banned all foreign ships from entering US ports.",
        "answer": "Embargo Act of 1807"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One of this President’s final acts was revoking the Embargo Act of 1807 after fifteen ineffectual months.",
        "answer": "Thomas Jefferson"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The outcome of this conflict led Mark Twain to angrily write “The War Prayer.” During this conflict, Charles Eagan was criticized for poisoning troops by providing “embalmed beef.” The order “you may fire when ready, Gridley” was given during a decisive naval victory in this conflict during which one only American under George Dewey died. The yellow journalism of William Randolph Hearst fueled sentiment for, for ten points, what “splendid little war” that began after the Maine sank in Havana Harbor in 1898?",
        "answer": "Spanish-American War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Commanding General of the US Army led the criticism of the embalmed beef scandal during the Spanish-American War, less than a decade after his subordinate failed to handle what became the Wounded Knee Massacre.",
        "answer": "Nelson Miles"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This President was briefly served by Labor Secretary Martin Patrick Durkin, the “plumber” in his “eight millionaires and a plumber” Cabinet; the “millionaires” included Defense Secretary Charles E. Wilson, who was a former CEO of General Motors, and Secretary of State John Foster Dulles. During his presidential campaign, this man was pressured to keep his Vice Presidential candidate, despite allegations of a slush fund, after the Checkers speech. Richard Nixon ran on a ticket with, for ten points, what US President who succeeded Harry Truman?",
        "answer": "Dwight David Eisenhower"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Under Eisenhower, this Cabinet department was led by Oveta Culp Hobby, a former WAC leader who became the second female Cabinet member in history. You can give either its name prior to 1979 or its current name, which it got in 1979 when the Department of Education was split off.",
        "answer": [
          "Department of Health and Human Services",
          "HHS",
          "Department of Health, Education, and Welfare"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The 21st specific charge in Richard Nixon’s articles of impeachment concerned a $200,000 bribe to overturn the Price Commission’s ruling on a price increase on this product. Ketchup and mustard are standard on this product, which outperformed a competitor released in the 1980s by the chain A&W because many Americans misunderstood that “one-third” represented a larger, not smaller, fraction. This product is often known as a “Royal” in countries with the metric system. For ten points, name this larger companion of the Big Mac on the McDonald’s menu.",
        "answer": [
          "Quarter Pounder with",
          "without cheese"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This McDonald’s chairman paid $200,000 to Richard Nixon’s re-election campaign in summer 1972 to get permission to raise the price of the Quarter Pounder. McDonald’s exploded into a franchised behemoth after this man entered into a partnership with the original McDonald brothers.",
        "answer": "Ray Kroc"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1731, Ben Franklin founded a subscription-based one of these institutions in Philadelphia. After one of these institutions was destroyed in the British burning of Washington, D.C. during the War of 1812, Thomas Jefferson sold his personal collection to restock it. Over 2,500 of these facilities were built with Andrew Carnegie’s funds. Carnegie helped popularize the “open-shelf” style of, for ten points, what public facilities that include circulation desks and reading rooms?",
        "answer": "library"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Thomas Jefferson’s collection helped rebuild this research library in Washington, D.C., which claims to be the largest library in the world.",
        "answer": "Library of Congress"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "George Bancroft’s recommendation of this man was unanimously accepted, ending a debate between Lewis Cass and Martin Van Buren. This president’s administration was able to work with Richard Pakenham to resolve a border dispute, despite this man’s support of the slogan “54-40 or fight.” This president gained Southern support by replacing the infamous “Black” Tariff with the Walker Tariff. For ten points, name this 11th president, a believer in manifest destiny who oversaw the Mexican-American War.",
        "answer": "James Knox Polk"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "British Ambassador Richard Pakenham eventually agreed with the US on a resolution to this dispute, the subject of the “54-40 or fight” slogan. Description acceptable.",
        "answer": [
          "Oregon boundary dispute",
          "descriptions regarding the border between the Oregon territory and British territory in Canada"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Prohibition Party candidate in this election year faced the Portland Rum Riot as mayor. Neal Dow and Greenback Labor candidate James Weaver ran in this year, whose losing major party candidate was known “Thunderbolt of the Army of the Potomac” for his heroism at Gettysburg. The winner of this election year was a compromise candidate for the Half-Breeds and Stalwarts and was succeeded a year later by his running mate, Chester Arthur. For ten points, name this election year in which Winfield Scott Hancock lost to James Garfield.",
        "answer": "U.S. presidential election of 1880"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Garfield was nominated at the 1880 Republican National Convention in this city, which has hosted 14 RNCs and 11 Democratic conventions, including in 1968.",
        "answer": "Chicago"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man, who worked alongside future US Ambassador to the UN John Danforth in the Missouri state government, decried a “high tech lynching” in 1991. This man, who gained most senior status after the retirement of Anthony Kennedy, is now often considered the farthest right on the political spectrum of the current court. Sexual harassment against Anita Hill did not prevent the confirmation of, for ten points, what justice who assumed Thurgood Marshall’s seat on the Supreme Court and is known for his general silence during arguments?",
        "answer": "Clarence Thomas"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Clarence Thomas’ Supreme Court confirmation hearings were overseen by this Democrat, who was criticized for his handling of Anita Hill’s claims in his position as chair of the Senate Judiciary Committee in 1991.",
        "answer": "Joseph “Joe” Biden"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man noted that “a vast majority of mankind is entirely biased by motives of self-interest” while arguing in favor of a minority veto in his posthumous Disquisition on Government. This architect of the Bureau of Indian Affairs declared slavery to be a “positive good” during an 1837 speech to Congress. This man, angered by the 1828 Tariff of Abominations, argued in favor of nullification in an Exposition and Protest. For ten points, name this South Carolina senator and Vice President under Andrew Jackson.",
        "answer": "John C. Calhoun"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Calhoun’s Disquisition on Government was highly popular among this group of pro-slavery Southerners. Edmund Ruffin and Robert Barnwell Rhett were among the leaders of this group, which pushed for secession as early as 1850 and which was given its name by critical Northerners.",
        "answer": "Fire-Eaters"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This woman was allegedly introduced to her husband by Aaron Burr, who frequented the boarding house run by this woman’s mother. This woman holds the distinction of being the only First Lady given an honorary Congressional seat. Because he was widowed, Thomas Jefferson often relied on this First Lady to serve as hostess during official events. For ten points, name this First Lady who directed her family’s slave to save the Landsdowne portrait of George Washington during the War of 1812.",
        "answer": [
          "Dolley Todd Madison",
          "Dolley Todd Payne"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This slave of the Madison family saved the Landsdowne portrait during the burning of Washington. Daniel Webster helped this man purchase his freedom, after which he published a White House memoir in 1865.",
        "answer": "Paul Jennings"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In one speech, this man condemned a senator for taking “a mistress...polluted in the sight of the world;” after that speech, Laurence Keitt brandished a pistol to prevent a brawl from breaking out. This man used Don Quixote and Sancho Panza as comparisons for Andrew Butler and Stephen Douglas after they wrote an 1854 act. For ten points, name this Republican, a Massachusetts senator who gave “The Crime Against Kansas” speech and was caned by Preston Brooks.",
        "answer": "Charles Sumner"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "As chairman of the Senate Foreign Relations Committee, Charles Sumner helped defuse this 1861 affair, which began after the U.S. Navy captured two Confederate ambassadors to the British.",
        "answer": "Trent affair"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Bicentennial of this colony was celebrated in the Grand National Jubilee. Nikole Hannah-Jones places the consequences of slavery at the center of US history, beginning with this colony, in The 1619 Project. Tobacco seeds were brought to this colony by John Rolfe in the Third Supply, and this colony earlier had faced the \"Starving Time.\" Located a few miles southwest of Williamsburg, for ten points, name this first permanent English settlement in America.",
        "answer": "Jamestown, Virginia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Jamestown was deliberately burned during this 1675-76 rebellion of Virginia settlers, the first in the North American British colonies.",
        "answer": "Bacon's Rebellion"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A biography by Richard Norton Smith takes its title from this former president’s “Uncommon Man” speech, delivered at Wilmington College in 1948. This man was appointed by Calvin Coolidge to oversee relief efforts after the Great Mississippi Flood of 1927. During a severe economic downturn, shantytowns named for this president popped up across the nation. For ten points, name this 31st US president who served a single term during the Great Depression.",
        "answer": "Herbert Hoover"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1920, Hoover was appointed Secretary of this department which separated from the Department of Labor in 1913.",
        "answer": "US Department of Commerce"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The first observance of this holiday in the US occurred at Columbia State Park in 1863. This holiday originated from a war of which historian John Leddy Phelan claims Napoleon III wanted to create \"Latin America.” This holiday commemorates the victory of Ignacio Zaragoza against Charles de Lorencez at the Battle of Puebla, which was followed by the installation of Maximilian I and the Second Mexican Empire. For ten points, name this celebration, often associated with Mexican-Americans.",
        "answer": [
          "Cinco de Mayo",
          "Fifth of May"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The first celebration of Cinco de Mayo in the US was held by gold miners in the foothills of the Sierra Nevada in what is today this US state.",
        "answer": "California 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 2"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Sarah Hopkins Bradford wrote a biography of this person who was the victim of a gold transfer swindle by John Thomas. This woman's mother, Rit, defended her family from Edward Brodess, and this woman developed hypersomnia when an overseer threw a metal weight at her head. This person helped Colonel James Montgomery scout out Jacksonville, Florida and aided Montgomery in the Combahee River Raid. For ten points, name this Underground Railroad conductor, who was called \"Moses.”",
        "answer": "Harriet Tubman"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Tubman has been proposed to replace President Andrew Jackson who has been featured since 1928 on this US currency denomination.",
        "answer": "$20 bill"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The conditions at this battle, featured in the opening scenes of the Academy Award winning 1989 film Glory, were described by one soldier as “almost impossible for a rat to live in.” Some of the earliest fighting at this 1862 battle swirled around Dunker Church. Burnside’s Bridge and Bloody Lane are landmarks at this site, where Robert E. Lee’s first invasion of the North was stopped cold. For ten points, name this battle that occurred on the single bloodiest day of the US Civil War.",
        "answer": [
          "Battle of Antietam",
          "Sharpsburg"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Democratic nominee in the 1864 presidential election was removed from his command of the Army of the Potomac, in part due to his tactical error in failing to pursue the Confederate Army after the Battle of Antietam.",
        "answer": "George B. McClellan"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "\"Puddler Jim\" Davis headed this department, employees of which included George Edmund Haynes, the first African-American to get a doctorate from Columbia University and the first director of the Division of Negro Economics. William Wilson was the first head of this department, and Louis Freeland Post conducted the Palmer Raids for it. This department is housed in the Frances Perkins Building, named for the first female cabinet member. For ten points, name this department that deals with laws governing unions and workplaces.",
        "answer": "United States Department of Labor"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Supreme Court Justice's son, Eugene, was Donald Trump's fourth Secretary of Labor. He was the first Italian-American Justice.",
        "answer": "Antonin Scalia"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Philip Sheridan claimed he often dropped off supplies for this man on the orders of President Andrew Johnson. Catholic clergy rights and the fueros were taken away in this man's namesake law. This man's administration created \"ports of deposit\" in the McLane- Ocampo Treaty. This man faced a war over his party's Plan of Ayutla, the Reform War. This man was a member of the Liberal party and succeeded Ignacio Comonfort as president. From a Zapotec origin in Oaxaca [[wah-HAH-kah]], for ten points, name this first indigenous Mexican president.",
        "answer": "Benito Juárez"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Juárez's opposition to this president caused him to go into exile in New Orleans from 1853 to 1855.",
        "answer": "Antonio López de Santa Anna"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Richard Dobbs Spaight attacked this privilege in a correspondence with James Iredell. This privilege was set in state court via Rutgers v. Waddington. This privilege helps to counteract the “sword and the purse” in Federalist 78. A case that instituted this privilege came about following the appointment of \"midnight judges.\" John Marshall used this ability to strike down part of a 1789 act in Marbury v. Madison. For ten points, name this legal doctrine which gives the Supreme Court the authority to rule a law unconstitutional.",
        "answer": "Judicial Review"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The court used judicial review in Hollinsworth v. Virginia, though this amendment limited the court's jurisdiction. This amendment was born from Chisholm v. Georgia and restricts the ability of individuals to sue states.",
        "answer": "11th Amendment 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 1"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Peter Lawford and this man organized the Inaugural Gala for JFK, but he later changed parties and arranged the gala for Ronald Reagan in 1980. This man built the Cal Neva Lodge & Casino at Lake Tahoe and opened its Celebrity Room. Mikhail Gorbachev and Gennadi Gerasimov sarcastically named a doctrine for this man in which Warsaw Pact states gained independence. Genovese crime boss Willie Moretti was the godfather of, for ten points, what Italian-American singer, known as “Ol’ Blue Eyes”?",
        "answer": "Frank Sinatra"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Frank Sinatra won an Academy Award for this 1953 film about three US Army soldiers, played by Sinatra, Montgomery Clift, and Burt Lancaster, in the days prior to the Japanese attack on Pearl Harbor.",
        "answer": "From Here to Eternity 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 2"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A college without walls was named for this man in Mount Angel. Ferdinand Marcos gave this man an honorary doctorate at the Eastern University following a trip in which this man praised Marcos’s martial law. A group organized by this man was situated at The Forty Acres, and this man negotiated with Lionel Steinberg in the Coachella area of California. This man organized the Delano Grape Strike, and with Dolores Huerta, this man co-founded the National Farm Workers Association. For ten points, name this Mexican-American labor leader.",
        "answer": "César Chávez"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This is the rallying cry for the United Farm Workers which was created during one of Chávez's fasts. In English, it translates to \"Yes, we can.\"",
        "answer": "Sí, se puede 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 2"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This person's students included Mary Putnam Jacobi, and she founded a school with Sophia Jex-Blake. Elizabeth Garret Anderson was mentored by this person who founded a dispensary at Tompkins Square while working with Marie Zakrzewska. This person adopted Kitty Barry, on whom she tested theories of Physical Education. This woman was allowed to attend Geneva College, where she wrote a thesis on typhoid fever. For ten points, name this woman, the first to receive a medical degree in the United States.",
        "answer": "Elizabeth Blackwell"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1861, Blackwell was beaten out for the role of Superintendent of Army Nurses by this woman who made her name as an advocate for the mentally ill.",
        "answer": "Dorothea Dix"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Elmer Thomas added a \"third horse\" to this law that created an \"honest dollar\" by controlling the amount of silver. This law was amended in 1935 by allowing for school lunches in Section 32. This law enforced the 1929 Potato Control Law and was found to be unconstitutional in 1936’s United States v. Butler. Pregnant sows were sold and oranges were destroyed according to this law. For ten points, name this New Deal law meant to boost prices and lower surpluses.",
        "answer": "Agricultural Adjustment Act"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Justice Owen Roberts wrote the majority opinion in US v. Butler and was joined in that opinion by this Chief Justice, a former governor of New York, and the Republican presidential nominee in 1916.",
        "answer": "Charles Evans Hughes 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Finals"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Just after this event, a similar event occurred on the urging of Benjamin Rush in Philadelphia. This event's participants attacked the Eleanor, Beaver, and Dartmouth, and it was planned at the Old South Meeting House. Conducted by Sons of Liberty dressed as Native Americans, for ten points, what was this destructive act of protest in which a shipment of the namesake product was destroyed in a Massachusetts harbor?",
        "answer": "Boston Tea Party"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Following the Boston Tea Party, this British king quoted Julius Caesar in a letter by saying \"The die is now cast.\"",
        "answer": "King George III"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The dead of these people were buried with maize in their mouth, while this people's Caracol site shows signs of post-mortem bloodletting. Women in this culture travelled to the pilgrimage site of the fertility goddess Ixchel [[EEKS-chehl]] on the isle of Cozumel. The underworld of Xibalba [[shee-BAHL-bah]] is traversed by this people's mythic \"Hero Twins\" in the compendium, Popul Vuh. For ten points, these myths were carved in the monumental architecture of what Mesoamerican civilization?",
        "answer": [
          "Mayan",
          "K'iche Maya",
          "Classical Mayans"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Mayans built several elaborate arenas to play what popular Mesoamerican sport that extended to the Aztecs and the Caribbeans?",
        "answer": [
          "Mesoamerican BallGame",
          "ōllamalīztli",
          "or pitz"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The constitution of this nation that was in place until 1987 was written by U.S. Assistant Secretary of the Navy, Franklin D. Roosevelt. After this country's president ordered the mass execution of prisoners in 1915, he was killed by a mob, leading to a U.S. occupation. Toussaint L'Ouverture [[too-SAHN loh-vehr-TOOR]] is known as the father of this country for leading it to independence. For ten points, name this country whose President Jovenel Moïse [[jove-NEL moh-EEZ]] was assassinated in 2021.",
        "answer": [
          "Republic of Haiti or Republique d'Haiti",
          "or Repiblik d Ayiti"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This family led Haiti from 1957 until 1986 under the leadership of both \"Papa Doc\" and \"Baby Doc.\"",
        "answer": "Duvalier ] 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 10"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An annual festival featuring the mock tarring and feathering of a tax collector in Washington County celebrates this uprising. A leader during this event, James McFarlane, was shot and killed at the Battle of Bower Hill. The \"Watermelon Army\" was led into battle by a sitting president for the only time in U.S. history during this uprising. For ten points, identify this rebellion of the 1790s against a tax on a specific kind of alcohol.",
        "answer": [
          "Whiskey Rebellion",
          "\"Revolt\"",
          "\"Insurrection\" for \"Rebellion\""
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Washington County, the site of the annual celebration, is located in the western end of this state, where the Whiskey Rebellion took place.",
        "answer": "Pennsylvania"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This U.S. armed forces branch traces its history to a force raised by Samuel Nicholas, who, with Esek Hopkins, orchestrated the capture of Nassau. This branch claims that their dress uniform's \"blood stripe\" memorializes the fallen at Chapultepec [[CHAH-puhl-TEH- pek]] Castle. This branch was led by Presley O'Bannon in one battle, which is immortalized in its namesake \"Hymn.\" For ten points, name this U.S. armed forces branch that has fought \"from the halls of Montezuma to the shores of Tripoli.\"",
        "answer": [
          "United States Marine Corps",
          "USMC",
          "United States Marines"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In the Pacific Campaign of World War Two, the United States Marine corps was instrumental to the success of this strategy, in which heavily fortified Japanese islands were simply avoided in favor of cutting them off from supplies, reducing the overall loss of soldiers.",
        "answer": "Leapfrogging or Island Hopping"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One of this man's speeches included what is now known as the \"Economic Bill of Rights.\" This man served as assistant secretary of the Navy during the Wilson administration. This president attempted to curb the \"Four Horsemen\" by packing the Supreme Court. The Tennessee Valley Authority and Social Security Administration were part of this president's main domestic program. For ten points, name this four-term president who promoted the New Deal.",
        "answer": [
          "Franklin Delano Roosevelt",
          "FDR"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Constitutional amendment was ratified six years after FDR's death, limiting the office of president to two terms.",
        "answer": "Twenty-Second Amendment"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A governor of this state, who ran in the 2016 presidential primaries using the slogan \"Our American Revival,\" lost a reelection bid to Democratic educator Tony Evers. The protests following the murder of Jacob Blake led to unrest in this state's city of Kenosha, which was followed by the Kyle Rittenhouse incident. Scott Walker once governed, for ten points, what northern state that saw protests in the cities of Madison and Milwaukee?",
        "answer": "Wisconsin"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The protests in Kenosha were organized by this antiracist political and social movement which formed following the George Zimmerman acquittal.",
        "answer": "Black Lives Matter or BLM"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This was the most popular service restricted by India following a conflict near Ladakh. Along with WeChat, this service was the subject of an executive order giving it forty-five days to divest its U.S. holdings or be purchased by an American company. In 2018, this service's parent company, ByteDance, merged it with Musical.ly, a similar Chinese social media service. For ten points, name this popular video-sharing social networking service, known in China as Douyin.",
        "answer": [
          "TikTok",
          "Douyin before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "TikTok successfully filled the void created when this Twitter-owned service was discontinued. This service allowed users to share six-second long videos on a loop.",
        "answer": "Vine 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 3"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was unknowingly given small dosages of methamphetamines by Max Jacobson, who was nicknamed \"Dr. Feelgood.\" This politician defeated incumbent Henry Cabot Lodge Jr. in a 1952 Senate race. This president negotiated with Nikita Khrushchev [[KROO-shev]] during the Cuban Missile Crisis and was in office during the botched Bay of Pigs invasion. The youngest person ever elected president was, for ten points, which Massachusetts politician?",
        "answer": [
          "John F. Kennedy both underlined portions required",
          "JFK"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The name of this mythical castle of Arthurian legend was used to evoke the general positive feelings of the American public toward the Kennedy family during their time in the White House.",
        "answer": [
          "Camelot",
          "Camelot era"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 2021, the U.S. Supreme Court ruled in favor of two people of this profession who argued workers could not unionize on their property. After the U.S. Civil War, people of this profession formed the Grange advocacy group. Thomas Jefferson called people with this profession \"the chosen people of God,\" and this profession was one of the most severely affected by the Dust Bowl. For ten points, name this profession involved in growing crops and raising animals for consumption.",
        "answer": [
          "Farmers",
          "word forms",
          "Agriculturist",
          "Horticulturist"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This sagely book of the Bible, traditionally written by King Solomon, provides some advice to farmers, saying, \"Those too lazy to plow in the right season will have no food at the harvest.\"",
        "answer": [
          "Book of Proverbs",
          "Proverbs of Solomon",
          "Míshlê Shlomoh"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "John Boehner [[BAY-ner]] resigned from this position in 2015 following a speech from Pope Francis the day prior. This position is second in the U.S. line of succession following the vice president. The current holder of this position represents the 12th District of California and went viral for a GIF of her clapping at Donald Trump in 2019. For ten points, name this elected leader of the lower chamber of the U.S. Congress, which is currently held by Nancy Pelosi.",
        "answer": "Speaker of the House of Representatives"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The First Speaker of the House was Frederick Muhlenberg, whose inaccurate \"legend\" claims that he stopped what European language from becoming the official tongue of the United States?",
        "answer": "German or Deutsch 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 4"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this war, the Creel Committee sent out “four minute men” to encourage people to buy war bonds, and during this war, the USFA encouraged “Meatless Mondays.” The Sedition Act passed during this war caused Eugene V. Debs to be jailed for encouraging draft-dodging. A president urged the U.S to enter this war to “make the world safe for democracy.” For ten points, name this war in which the United States sent \"doughboys\" to fight in the trenches.",
        "answer": [
          "World War One or the First World War",
          "the Great War",
          "or Weltkrieg"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During the war, this man was appointed head of the War Emergency Division to deport supposed disloyal foreigners. He later served as the first Director of the FBI from 1924 to 1972.",
        "answer": "John Edgar Hoover"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In one of these artworks, a woman labeled \"America First\" reads a children's book titled Adolf the Wolf to impressionable kids. One of these artworks depicts a turtle known as \"O Grab Me\" biting a New Englander holding a barrel labeled \"Super Fine.\" The two symbols of the American political parties, the donkey and elephant, were first introduced through this medium. For ten points, name these graphics that depict public figures, usually expressing the artist's opinion.",
        "answer": "Political Cartoons"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Thomas Nast, perhaps America's most well-known political cartoonist, gained notoriety for his criticism of \"Boss\" Tweed, the leader of what New York political machine that was infamous for its corruption?",
        "answer": [
          "Tammany Hall or Tammany Society",
          "Society of St. Tammany",
          "or Sons of St. Tammany",
          "the Columbian Order 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 5"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The third-place finisher in this U.S. election year suffered a stroke a year prior to it, leading to his poor performance. The Tertium Quids [[TER-shum KWIDS]] were represented by that man, William H. Crawford, in this election year. This election year saw the House of Representatives swing one man's electoral votes to the eventual winner in order to keep a Tennessee politician from winning office. For ten points, name this election year in which John Quincy Adams defeated Andrew Jackson thanks to the \"corrupt bargain.\"",
        "answer": "Election of 1824"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The House of Representatives was legally justified in choosing the winner of the election due to this amendment to the Constitution, which clarified electoral procedure after the chaos of the elections of 1796 and 1800.",
        "answer": "Twelfth Amendment or Amendment Twelve"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Mehdi Bazargan resigned to protest the beginning of this event, which concluded with the signing of the Algiers Accords. The disastrous Operation Eagle Claw attempted to rescue victims of this event. This crisis ended within minutes of the inauguration of Ronald Reagan as U.S. president, following a 444 day period of imprisonment for its victims. For ten points, identify this diplomatic crisis that began when revolutionary students stormed a U.S. embassy in a Middle Eastern capital.",
        "answer": [
          "Iran Hostage Crisis",
          "Tehran Hostage Crisis",
          "descriptive answers"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In the middle of the crisis, a war broke out between Iran and neighboring Iraq, which at the time was led by this expansionist Arab nationalist politician who later invaded Kuwait, sparking the Persian Gulf War.",
        "answer": "Saddam Hussein"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A precursor to this period of history was the wartime Port Royal Experiment. The only two-term leader during this period vetoed much of the legislation that was sent to him, but several bills were overridden by the Radical Republicans. During this period, the Enforcement Act was signed into law by President Ulysses S. Grant to counter the nascent Ku Klux Klan. For ten points, name this period of rebuilding that occurred immediately following the Civil War.",
        "answer": "Reconstruction era"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This man was elected president in 1876 in a heavily-contested race. The back-door compromise that assured him the presidency promised the effective end of Reconstruction.",
        "answer": "Rutherford Birchard Hayes"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Supported by Guadalupe Victoria, this figure rose in rebellion against Emperor Augustin I [[ow-goo-STEEN the first]] in the Casa Mata Plan Revolution. This perpetrator of the Goliad Massacre gave a full military burial to his leg after it was hit by cannon fire during the Pastry War. This man captured the former mission-turned-fort of the Alamo during the War of Texan Independence. For ten points, name this Mexican general and president who resisted an 1840s invasion of his nation by the Polk administration.",
        "answer": [
          "Antonio López de Santa Anna",
          "Antonio de Padua María Severino López de Santa Anna y Pérez de Lebrón"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Santa Anna fought this inconclusive battle against Zachary Taylor at La Angostura. Once news of this battle made it to the United States, it was hailed as a great victory.",
        "answer": "Battle of Buena Vista"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man bucked the trends of post-Civil War historiography in his book Black Reconstruction in America. This thinker, who publicly debated white supremacist Lothrop Stoddard, was the founding editor of the magazine The Crisis. This man believed that full civil rights would be accomplished through the efforts of a group he dubbed the \"Talented Tenth.\" For ten points, name this American-Ghanaian sociologist who wrote The Souls of Black Folk.",
        "answer": "W. E. B. Du Bois ] or William Edward Burghardt Du Bois"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Crisis is the official magazine of what civil rights organization, co-founded by Du Bois, which refused to issue a public statement of support during his investigation by the FBI, leading to Du Bois's estrangement?",
        "answer": "NAACP or the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 7"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Union control was solidified in this U.S. state after Don Carlos Buell's strategic victory at the Battle of Perryville. According to President Lincoln, losing this state was \"nearly the same as to lose the whole game.\" This state's city of Paducah was raided in 1864 by Confederate general Nathan Bedford Forrest. Though neither man represented this state, it was the birthplace of both Jefferson Davis and Abraham Lincoln. For ten points, name this border state during the U.S. Civil War.",
        "answer": "Kentucky"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Kentucky native was James Buchanan's vice president, the youngest ever, and was nominated by the Southern Democrats to run in the hotly-contested Election of 1860.",
        "answer": "John Cabell Breckinridge"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "\"Dynamic cubist\" Jacob Lawrence painted a 60-panel series about this event, which is the subject of Isabel Wilkerson's The Warmth of Other Suns. Chester Burnett and Muddy Waters moved to Chicago during this event, which presaged the Harlem Renaissance. For ten points, name this major demographic shift in the mid-twentieth century United States, in which millions of African Americans moved out of the South.",
        "answer": [
          "Great Migration",
          "Great Northward Migration",
          "or Black Migration",
          "Migration Series",
          "or The Migration of the Negro"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What American author depicted the Black communities of the industrial North following the Great Migration in her novels The Bluest Eye and Song of Solomon?",
        "answer": [
          "Toni Morrison",
          "Chloe Anthony Wofford Morrison",
          "or Chloe Ardelia Wofford"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An 1890 filibuster which planned to seize this region intended to appoint editor Warren Hastings as Governor-General. This region's \"South\" province rebelled against U.S. occupation during the Mexican-American War until the defeat of the rebels at San José del Cabo [[KAH-boh]]. It's not Nicaragua, but this region was captured by William Walker and incorporated into the Republic of Sonora. For ten points, identify this region now split into two Mexican states, where Walker occupied such cities as La Paz and Cabo San Lucas.",
        "answer": [
          "Baja ] California",
          "Baja California Sur"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1994, presidential candidate Luis Donaldo Colosio [[koh-LOH-syoh]] was assassinated in this major Baja California tourist city on the U.S. border.",
        "answer": "Tijuana"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man's unacknowledged abolitionist son, John Pierre, was born from a tryst with his Indian servant Mary Emmons. From 1808 to 1812, this man went on a self-imposed exile to England, where he befriended Utilitarian philosopher Jeremy Bentham. This New York lawyer received the second-highest amount of votes in one election, resulting in this man becoming vice president. For ten points, name this early leader of the Democratic- Republicans, the vice president under Thomas Jefferson.",
        "answer": "Aaron Burr Jr"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Burr's infamous duel with politician Alexander Hamilton occurred in which state's city of Weehawken?",
        "answer": "New Jersey"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "STATES IN THE CIVIL RIGHTS MOVEMENT",
      "prompt": "During the civil rights era, in what U.S. state did...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Ruby Bridges integrate schools in New Orleans?",
          "answer": "Lousiana"
        },
        {
          "question": "Jackie Robinson take the field at home for the Brooklyn Dodgers?",
          "answer": "New York"
        },
        {
          "question": "The first sit-in take place in Wilmington?",
          "answer": "North Carolina"
        },
        {
          "question": "James Meredith integrate the state university in Oxford?",
          "answer": "Mississippi"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Watts riots occur?",
          "answer": "California"
        },
        {
          "question": "Bull Connor try to stop integration in Birmingham?",
          "answer": "Alabama"
        },
        {
          "question": "Orval Faubus attempt to block the integration of Central High School?",
          "answer": "Arkansas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Protestors beat a man with an American flag on a pole during an anti-busing riot?",
          "answer": "Massachussetts"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "SPOILS SYSTEM",
      "prompt": "Name the spoils system...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Embraced by what Democratic President who succeeded John Quincy Adams?",
          "answer": "Andrew Jackson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Also popular with Republican factions based in what city, the most populous in the U.S. since 1790?",
          "answer": "New York City"
        },
        {
          "question": "Blamed for the death of what President in 1881?",
          "answer": "James Garfield"
        },
        {
          "question": "An expected source of patronage by what man who shot that President?",
          "answer": "Charles Guiteau"
        },
        {
          "question": "Particularly focused on what institution which oversaw tarriff collection at a busy port?",
          "answer": "New York Customs House"
        },
        {
          "question": "Severely curtailed by what 1883 \"civil service act?\"",
          "answer": "Pendleton Civil Service Act"
        },
        {
          "question": "Opposed by what faction of Republicans who defected to Grover Cleveland in 1884?",
          "answer": "Mugwumps"
        },
        {
          "question": "Advocated by what leader of the Stalwarts and long-serving Senator in the 1870s?",
          "answer": [
            "Roscoe Conkling FOREIGN RELATIONS In",
            "with what foreign country did the United States…"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "AMERICAN IMMIGRANT GROUPS",
      "prompt": "Name the american immigrant groups...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "First fled to the British colonies when Louis XIV outlawed Huguenots?",
          "answer": "France"
        },
        {
          "question": "Founded the first pizza shop in the U.S. in 1905?",
          "answer": "Italy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Were subject to \"need not apply signs\" after emigrating during a potato famine?",
          "answer": "Ireland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Were the target of an \"exclusion act\" following their work on railroads in the West?",
          "answer": "China"
        },
        {
          "question": "Settled in Glendale and Fresno, California, after a Turkish genocide?",
          "answer": "Armenia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Brought tales of the Kalevala (KAH-leh-VAH-luh) to the Upper Peninsula of Michigan?",
          "answer": "Finland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Were the subject of the \"Gentleman's Agreement\" under Theodore Roosevelt?",
          "answer": "Japan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Include Jerry Seinfeld, Steve Jobs, and Paula Abdul and other Arab-Americans?",
          "answer": "Syria"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "PEOPLE OF 1968",
      "prompt": "In 1968, who...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was killed by James Earl Ray in Memphis after leading a civil rights action?",
          "answer": [
            "Martin Luther King Jr.",
            "King"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Won the U.S. Presidential election on his second try, defeating Hubert Humphrey?",
          "answer": [
            "Richard Nixon",
            "Nixon"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Announced he would not run for reelection as president?",
          "answer": [
            "Lyndon B. Johnson",
            "LBJ",
            "L Johnson"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was leading the Democratic primaries prior to his assassination in Los Angeles?",
          "answer": [
            "Robert F. Kennedy",
            "RFK"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the director of the year's most controversial film, 2001: A Space Odyssey?",
          "answer": [
            "Stanley Kubrick",
            "Kubrick"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Won his tenth NBA title as the center and coach of the Boston Celtics?",
          "answer": [
            "Bill Russell",
            "Russell"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Released his Electric Ladyland Album with his \"Experience?\"",
          "answer": [
            "Jimi Hendrix",
            "Hendrix"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was accused of inciting riots in Washington, D.C. a year after resigning as leader of SNCC\n(snick)?",
          "answer": [
            "Stokely Carmichael",
            "Carmichael"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "AMENDMENTS",
      "prompt": "What U.S. Constitutional amendment is or was the chief subject of...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "A witness's right not to testify against himself?",
          "answer": [
            "Fifth"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Any case discussing the right to trial by jury in criminal matters?",
          "answer": [
            "Sixth"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The 1993 case in which Santeria worshippers asserted their religious right to sacrifice\nanimals?",
          "answer": [
            "First"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Cases invoking the \"equal protection\" clause?",
          "answer": [
            "Fourteenth"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Mapp v. Ohio and other exclusionary rule cases?",
          "answer": [
            "Fourth"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Cases arguing that the military draft constitutes involuntary servitude?",
          "answer": [
            "Thirteenth"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "U.S. v Lopez which claimed \"reserved powers\" for state governments?",
          "answer": [
            "Tenth"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "2008's DC v. Heller and 2010's McDonald v. Chicago?",
          "answer": [
            "Second"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "ELECTION OF 1948",
      "prompt": "In the U.S. Presidential election of 1948, who...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was re-elected despite an erroneous Chicago Tribune headline?",
          "answer": "Harry Truman"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the Republican who lost the election, also in contradiction to the headline?",
          "answer": "Thomas Dewey"
        },
        {
          "question": "Declined an offer to run but became the winning Republican candidate four years later?",
          "answer": "Dwight Eisenhower"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the out-of-power British Conservative who lost an election after winning World War II, to whom the incumbent was frequently compared?",
          "answer": "Winston Churchill"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ran as the Dixiecrat candidate prior to becoming a long-serving South Carolina Senator?",
          "answer": "Strom Thurmond"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ran for the Progressive Party after serving as FDR's second Vice-President?",
          "answer": "Henry Wallace"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the body attacked as \"do-nothing\" by the winning candidate?",
          "answer": "U.S. Congress"
        },
        {
          "question": "Finished second at the Republican convention and was an isolationist Ohio Senator?",
          "answer": "Robert Taft NHBB B 2014-2015"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "THE FIRST GULF WAR",
      "prompt": "Who or what was…",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The dictator of Iraq during the First Gulf War?",
          "answer": "Saddam Hussain"
        },
        {
          "question": "The nation accused of “slant drilling” that was invaded by Iraqi forces in 1990?",
          "answer": "Kuwait"
        },
        {
          "question": "The codename given to the American-led offensive into Iraq?",
          "answer": "Operation Desert Storm"
        },
        {
          "question": "The leader of American forces in the conflict, given the nickname “Stormin’”?",
          "answer": "Norman Schwarzkopf, Jr"
        },
        {
          "question": "The pyrophoric, armor-piercing radioactive material used in coalition weapons thought to contribute to Gulf War syndrome?",
          "answer": "depleted uranium"
        },
        {
          "question": "The elite Iraqi military force led by General al-Rawi that included the Hammurabi armored division?",
          "answer": "Republican Guard"
        },
        {
          "question": "The road from Kuwait City to Basra used by retreating Iraqi columns that was bombed repeatedly by Coalition forces?",
          "answer": "Highway of Death"
        },
        {
          "question": "Strategy, named for a boxing move, in which flanking divisions approached Iraqi forces from the west while others ran straight through the Kuwaiti border?",
          "answer": "Left Hook"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "IMPEACHMENT OF ANDREW JOHNSON",
      "prompt": "During the impeachment of U.S. President Andrew Johnson, who or what…",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Upper chamber of Congress conducted and voted on the removal trial?",
          "answer": "U.S. Senate"
        },
        {
          "question": "Party's \"Radical\" members pushed for the impeachment?",
          "answer": "Republican Party"
        },
        {
          "question": "Decade did the events take place during?",
          "answer": "1860s"
        },
        {
          "question": "Law was Johnson charged with violating?",
          "answer": "Tenure of Office Act"
        },
        {
          "question": "Person did Johnson fire to break that law?",
          "answer": "Edwin Stanton"
        },
        {
          "question": "Position did that person hold?",
          "answer": "Secretary of War"
        },
        {
          "question": "President Pro Tem of the Senate, who names a Reconstruction bill with Henry Davis, would have become President had the removal succeeded?",
          "answer": "Benjamin Wade"
        },
        {
          "question": "Became a subject of Profiles in Courage for casting the deciding vote against removal?",
          "answer": "Edmund Ross"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Colonial America",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "colony founded by Roger Williams, now the smallest U.S. state.",
          "answer": "Rhode Island and Providence Plantations"
        },
        {
          "question": "colony home to Paul Revere, which was governed as a state by John Hancock and Samuel Adams.",
          "answer": "Massachusetts"
        },
        {
          "question": "body that appointed George Washington to lead the army.",
          "answer": "Second Continental Congress"
        },
        {
          "question": "African-American man who was the first person to die in the Boston Massacre.",
          "answer": "Crispus Attucks"
        },
        {
          "question": "period of religious revival among church members that occurred in the 1730s and 1740s.",
          "answer": "First Great Awakening"
        },
        {
          "question": "Puritan woman that was expelled from Massachusetts Bay Colony after the Antinomian Controversy.",
          "answer": "Anne Hutchinson or Anne Marbury"
        },
        {
          "question": "1754 meeting in New York where Benjamin Franklin drew the “Join or die” cartoon.",
          "answer": "Albany Congress"
        },
        {
          "question": "unfair three-word political concept that James Otis equated with tyranny.",
          "answer": "taxation without representation"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Landslide Elections",
      "prompt": "Which U.S. President overwhelmingly defeated...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Alf Landon by a margin of 523-8, the best of his four Presidential victories?",
          "answer": [
            "Franklin Delano Roosevelt",
            "FDR"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "George McGovern in 1972?",
          "answer": "Richard Nixon"
        },
        {
          "question": "no one, winning unopposed in two unanimous Electoral College results?",
          "answer": "George Washington"
        },
        {
          "question": "no one, winning unopposed during the “Era of Good Feelings?”",
          "answer": "James Monroe"
        },
        {
          "question": "George McClellan, using the phrase “Don’t change horses in the middle of a stream?”",
          "answer": "Abraham Lincoln"
        },
        {
          "question": "Walter Mondale, who only carried Minnesota and D.C.?",
          "answer": "Ronald Reagan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Adlai Stevenson, twice?",
          "answer": "Dwight Eisenhower"
        },
        {
          "question": "the author of The Conscience of a Conservative by 434 electoral votes?",
          "answer": [
            "Lyndon Baines Johnson",
            "LBJ"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "1989",
      "prompt": "In 1989, who...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "finished the second term of his U.S. presidency?",
          "answer": "Ronald Reagan"
        },
        {
          "question": "oversaw the fall of the Berlin Wall as leader of the Soviet Union?",
          "answer": "Mikhail Gorbachev"
        },
        {
          "question": "became the first African-American Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff?",
          "answer": "Colin Powell"
        },
        {
          "question": "became president of Czechoslovakia after the Velvet Revolution?",
          "answer": "Vaclav Havel"
        },
        {
          "question": "was the unnamed protestor captured on film blocking vehicles in Tiananmen Square?",
          "answer": "Tank Man"
        },
        {
          "question": "was the dictator of Panama overthrown by the U.S. in Operation Just Cause?",
          "answer": "Manuel Noriega"
        },
        {
          "question": "became the last Afrikaner President of South Africa to rule during Apartheid?",
          "answer": "Frederik Willem de Klerk"
        },
        {
          "question": "was re-buried in Budapest’s New Public Cemetery, 31 years after he was executed for withdrawing from the Warsaw Pact?",
          "answer": "Imre Nagy"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Battles on American Soil",
      "prompt": "In which American battle did...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "the “Shot Heard ‘Round the World” start the American Revolution?",
          "answer": "Battle of Lexington and Concord"
        },
        {
          "question": "a general supposedly say “Don’t fire until you see the whites of their eyes!” on Breed’s Hill?",
          "answer": "Battle of Bunker Hill"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sitting Bull’s Sioux forces cause the death of George Custer?",
          "answer": [
            "Battle of Little Bighorn",
            "Battle of the Greasy Grass"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "heavy casualties in Miller’s Cornfield lead to the bloodiest single-day battle in American history?",
          "answer": "Battle of Antietam or Battle of Sharpsburg"
        },
        {
          "question": "P.G.T. Beauregard surprise Grant’s forces near Pittsburg Landing?",
          "answer": "Battle of Shiloh"
        },
        {
          "question": "Isaac Brock and Tecumseh force the surrender of a fort in the Michigan Territory?",
          "answer": "Siege of Detroit"
        },
        {
          "question": "Daniel Morgan defeat the British, led by Banastre Tarleton, in a South Carolina grazing land?",
          "answer": "Battle of Cowpens"
        },
        {
          "question": "Pancho Villa’s Division of the North raid a New Mexico town, triggering Pershing’s expedition?",
          "answer": "Battle or Raid of Columbus"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Cuba",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "disease caused by HIV, for which Cuba has the lowest rate in the Caribbean.",
          "answer": "AIDS or acquired immune deficiency syndrome"
        },
        {
          "question": "tobacco commodity, of which John F. Kennedy purchased over a thousand prior to signing an embargo in 1962.",
          "answer": "cigars"
        },
        {
          "question": "failed 1961 coup, led by the CIA-backed Brigade 2506.",
          "answer": "Bay of Pigs Invasion or Playa Giron"
        },
        {
          "question": "Argentinian revolutionary whose militia helped Castro succeed in the 1959 Cuban Revolution.",
          "answer": [
            "Ernesto Che Guevara",
            "either"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "leader who was overthrown in the 1959 Cuban Revolution.",
          "answer": "Fulgencio Batista Zald´ıvar"
        },
        {
          "question": "1901 bill that limited Cuba’s self-rule after the Spanish-American War.",
          "answer": "Platt Amendment"
        },
        {
          "question": "1980 mass emigration of Cubans to Florida.",
          "answer": "Mariel boatlift"
        },
        {
          "question": "Governor General of Cuba during the Spanish-American War, nicknamed “Butcher.”",
          "answer": "Valeriano Weyler y Nicolau"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Calvin Coolidge was...",
      "prompt": "Name the calvin coolidge was......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Vice President under what man, whose death elevated Coolidge to the Presidency in 1923?",
          "answer": "Warren Harding"
        },
        {
          "question": "succeeded as President in 1929 by what man, his Secretary of Commerce?",
          "answer": "Herbert Hoover"
        },
        {
          "question": "was the only man to defeat what future President in a national election, on the Vice Presidential tickets in 1920?",
          "answer": [
            "Franklin Delano Roosevelt",
            "FDR"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "praised for ending a 1919 police strike in what city?",
          "answer": "Boston"
        },
        {
          "question": "served by what Secretary of State, who signed a 1928 peace pact with a Aristide Briand?",
          "answer": "Frank Kellogg"
        },
        {
          "question": "offended what union, led by Big Bill Haywood, in his mediation of the “Bread and Roses” strike?",
          "answer": [
            "Industrial Workers of the World or IWW",
            "Wobblies"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "opposed in the 1924 election by what Progressive Wisconsin senator?",
          "answer": "Robert La Follette, Sr."
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Space Race",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "American space agency that was founded in 1958.",
          "answer": "NASA or the National Aeronautics and Space Administration"
        },
        {
          "question": "Program whose eleventh mission successfully landed the first men on the Moon.",
          "answer": [
            "Apollo Program",
            "Apollo 11"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "U.S. President who inspired the race to the Moon with a 1962 speech at Rice University.",
          "answer": "John F. Kennedy or JFK"
        },
        {
          "question": "First successful Soviet satellite, whose launch sparked the race.",
          "answer": "Sputnik 1"
        },
        {
          "question": "First American in space, via the first manned Mercury flight.",
          "answer": "Alan Shepard"
        },
        {
          "question": "Family of rockets that launched American flights to the Moon.",
          "answer": [
            "Saturn family",
            "Saturn V"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Soviet family of rockets, first flown in 1966, which are now the only rockets capable of taking astronauts to the ISS.",
          "answer": "Soyuz"
        },
        {
          "question": "Operation that brought Nazi scientists to work on the American space program.",
          "answer": "Operation Paperclip"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Suffrage",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Political right sought by suffragettes.",
          "answer": "women’s right to vote"
        },
        {
          "question": "Half of Congress that originally voted down the 19th Amendment in 1918, as opposed to the House.",
          "answer": "U.S. Senate"
        },
        {
          "question": "Suffragette and friend of Elizabeth Cady Stanton who was arrested in 1872 and was honored with a dollar coin in 1979.",
          "answer": "Susan B. Anthony"
        },
        {
          "question": "1848 women’s rights convention organized by Stanton, the first in U.S. history.",
          "answer": "Seneca Falls Convention"
        },
        {
          "question": "US state where that convention took place, where Stanton lived, and where the aforementioned arrest took place in Rochester.",
          "answer": "New York"
        },
        {
          "question": "Document signed by 100 attendees of that convention, pledging that “all men and women are created equal.”",
          "answer": "Declaration of Sentiments"
        },
        {
          "question": "Quaker activist and mentor of Stanton who argued against support for women’s suffrage at that convention.",
          "answer": "Lucretia Mott"
        },
        {
          "question": "Two-word term for Alice Paul’s group of suffragettes, who quietly protested in front of the White House.",
          "answer": "Silent Sentinels"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Simo´n Bol´ıvar",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "European nation whose South American colonies he liberated.",
          "answer": "Spain"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country where he began his rebellion, supplanting a Supreme Junta in Caracas to take power.",
          "answer": "Venezuela"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country he liberated after marching into the city of Quito.",
          "answer": "Ecuador"
        },
        {
          "question": "French leader whose invasion of Spain allowed Bol´ıvar to begin his rebellion.",
          "answer": "Napol´eon Bonaparte or Napol´eon I"
        },
        {
          "question": "United South American nation that Bol´ıvar created out of the remnants of New Granada.",
          "answer": "Gran Colombia or the Republic of Colombia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Revolutionary general, “Protector of Peru,” and ally who met with Bol´ıvar at the Guayaquil Conference.",
          "answer": "Jos´e de San Mart´ın"
        },
        {
          "question": "British island where he wrote a letter to Henry Cullen, describing his vision for a free Latin America.",
          "answer": "Jamaica"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mistress who saved him from an assassination attempt by mutinous soldiers.",
          "answer": "Manuela S´aenz"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Historical Deaths in 2016",
      "prompt": "In addition to all the musicians and actors we lost in 2016, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country where Rama IX [ninth] passed away in Bangkok in October.",
          "answer": "Thailand"
        },
        {
          "question": "American boxer whose arrest for draft evasion during the Vietnam War was overturned by the Supreme Court.",
          "answer": "Muhammad Ali or Cassius Clay"
        },
        {
          "question": "Supreme Court justice whose seat remained vacant for the rest of 2016.",
          "answer": "Antonin Scalia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Astronaut and Ohio senator who became the oldest person in space in 1998.",
          "answer": "John Glenn"
        },
        {
          "question": "Anti-drug activist who served as First Lady from 1981 to 1989.",
          "answer": "Nancy Reagan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nobel Peace Prize winner and Holocaust survivor who wrote Night.",
          "answer": "Elie Wiesel"
        },
        {
          "question": "Former President of Israel who shared in the 1994 Nobel Peace Prize for the Oslo Accords.",
          "answer": "Shimon Peres"
        },
        {
          "question": "Astronomer and advocate for gender equality in the sciences who helped discover dark matter.",
          "answer": "Vera Rubin"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "OPEC",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Unofficial leader, an Arabian kingdom led from Riyadh that produces over ten million barrels of oil a day.",
          "answer": "Saudi Arabia"
        },
        {
          "question": "South American member with the largest proven oil reserves, once led by Hugo Chavez.",
          "answer": "Venezuela"
        },
        {
          "question": "1980s war between two of its members to control the vital Shatt-al-Arab waterway.",
          "answer": "Iran-Iraq War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Action often taken by OPEC against countries it wishes to punish, a refusal to trade.",
          "answer": "oil embargo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Controversial method of breaking rockbed to access oil and natural gas, causing a recent supply glut that harmed OPEC economies.",
          "answer": "hydraulic fracturing or fracking"
        },
        {
          "question": "OPEC member that suppressed a secessionist movement in its oil-rich region of Biafra in the 1960s.",
          "answer": "Nigeria"
        },
        {
          "question": "OPEC member that uses its wealth to fund the Al Jazeera media network.",
          "answer": "Qatar"
        },
        {
          "question": "Organization that promotes trade and competition, contrasting with OPEC’s mission of collusion amongst members. A 1999 conference of this body in Seattle was strongly protested.",
          "answer": "World Trade Organization"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Calvin Coolidge...",
      "prompt": "Name the calvin coolidge......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was the governor of what state, where he led from Boston?",
          "answer": "Massachusetts"
        },
        {
          "question": "Became President after what Republican suffered a cerebral hemorrhage and died in 1923?",
          "answer": "Warren G. Harding"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was succeeded by what President, who got little of the “Roaring Twenties” fun and, instead, the start of the Great Depression?",
          "answer": "Herbert Hoover"
        },
        {
          "question": "Appointed J. Edgar Hoover the head of what agency, a decade before its name change? Old or modern name acceptable.",
          "answer": [
            "Federal Bureau of Investigation",
            "FBI",
            "BOI"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Arbitrated the 1912 “Bread and Roses” strike, put on by members of what “wobbly” union?",
          "answer": "Industrial Workers of the World or IWW"
        },
        {
          "question": "Put down a 1919 strike of what public employees in Boston?",
          "answer": [
            "Police officers",
            "equivalents"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Failed to adequately respond to a 1927 flood of what river?",
          "answer": [
            "Mississippi River",
            "Great Mississippi Flood"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Agreed with what Pennsylvanian banker, his Treasury Secretary, on the benefits of low taxes?",
          "answer": "Andrew Mellon"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Battle of Antietam",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "War in which it took place, a victory for the Union over the Confederates.",
          "answer": "American Civil War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Confederate leader and head of the Army of Northern Virginia who successfully retreated after the battle.",
          "answer": "Robert E. Lee"
        },
        {
          "question": "River near which the battle was fought, well upstream of Washington, D.C., and which named the Union’s largest army.",
          "answer": [
            "Potomac River",
            "Army of the Potomac"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "State in which the battle was fought, just across that river from Virginia.",
          "answer": "Maryland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Document that President Lincoln announced after the victory, pledging to free slaves in the New Year.",
          "answer": "Emancipation Proclamation"
        },
        {
          "question": "Union general who failed to press the advantage against the retreating Confederates, costing him his job.",
          "answer": "George McClellan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Photographer who documented “The Dead of Antietam” two days after the battle.",
          "answer": "Mathew Brady"
        },
        {
          "question": "Items found with a lost copy of Special Order 191, detailing Confederate troop movements prior to Antietam.",
          "answer": "three cigars"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "American Nobel Peace Prize Winners",
      "prompt": "Given the year and a clue, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "2009: then-recently elected U.S. President.",
          "answer": "Barack Obama"
        },
        {
          "question": "2002: former American President, philanthropist, and activist with Habitat for Humanity.",
          "answer": "James Earl “Jimmy” Carter"
        },
        {
          "question": "1964: American minister and civil rights activist who was assassinated in Memphis in 1968.",
          "answer": "Dr. Martin Luther King Jr."
        },
        {
          "question": "1906: President who became the first American to win the Peace Prize.",
          "answer": "Theodore Roosevelt"
        },
        {
          "question": "2007: former U.S. Vice President for his climate change advocacy.",
          "answer": "Al Gore"
        },
        {
          "question": "1931: American suffragette and reformer who co-founded Hull House.",
          "answer": "Jane Addams"
        },
        {
          "question": "1929: American statesman who co-wrote a pact denouncing war with 1926’s co-winner, Aristide Briand.",
          "answer": "Frank Kellogg"
        },
        {
          "question": "1925: American Vice President who worked on a World War I reparations plan.",
          "answer": [
            "Charles Dawes",
            "Dawes Plan"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Bill of Rights",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Number of amendments included in the U.S. Bill of Rights.",
          "answer": "10"
        },
        {
          "question": "Amendment that protects freedom of speech and religion.",
          "answer": "1st Amendment"
        },
        {
          "question": "Amendment that protects against “cruel and unusual punishments.”",
          "answer": "8th Amendment"
        },
        {
          "question": "Amendment that demands “just compensation” when private property is taken for public use.",
          "answer": "5th Amendment"
        },
        {
          "question": "Author of the Bill of Rights and owner of a plantation at Montpelier.",
          "answer": "James Madison"
        },
        {
          "question": "People for whom pay raises are restricted by the 27th Amendment, an idea originally proposed with the Bill of Rights.",
          "answer": [
            "members of Congress",
            "Representatives and/or Senators and any equivalents"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Process by which a court uses the 14th Amendment to apply the Bill of Rights to the states.",
          "answer": [
            "selective and/or total incorporation",
            "word forms"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1833 Supreme Court case against the city of Baltimore that explicitly banned that process.",
          "answer": "Barron v. Baltimore"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Eisenhower Administration",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Year in which Eisenhower first defeated Adlai Stevenson to become President.",
          "answer": "1952"
        },
        {
          "question": "Vice President under Eisenhower during both of his terms.",
          "answer": "Richard Milhous Nixon"
        },
        {
          "question": "First Soviet satellite that launched the Space Race and led Eisenhower to create NASA.",
          "answer": "Sputnik I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Complex whose “unwarranted influence” Eisenhower warned against in his farewell address.",
          "answer": "military-industrial complex"
        },
        {
          "question": "Amendment that limited Eisenhower to two terms, ratified under his predecessor.",
          "answer": "22nd Amendment to the US Constitution"
        },
        {
          "question": "Surname of CIA director Allen and Secretary of State John Foster, who each served under Eisenhower.",
          "answer": "Dulles"
        },
        {
          "question": "SenateMajorityLeaderwithwhomEisenhower’sadministrationnegotiated,infamousforhisnamesake “treatment.”",
          "answer": [
            "Lyndon Baines Johnson",
            "LBJ"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Resolution that Congress passed at Eisenhower’s urging that ended the First Taiwan Strait Crisis.",
          "answer": "Formosa Resolution"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Cold War Spying",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Agency compromised by Robert Hanssen and earlier led by J. Edgar Hoover.",
          "answer": "FBI or Federal Bureau of Investigation"
        },
        {
          "question": "Surname of Ethel and Julius, who were executed for giving American secrets to the USSR.",
          "answer": [
            "Ethel and Julius Rosenberg",
            "the Rosenbergs"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Head of the Manhattan Project who was later accused of being a Communist spy.",
          "answer": "J. Robert Oppenheimer"
        },
        {
          "question": "Secret police force headed by Erich Mielke that operated in East Germany.",
          "answer": [
            "Stasi",
            "Ministry for State Security",
            "Ministerium fur Staatssicherheit",
            "State Security Service",
            "Staatssicherheitsdienst",
            "MfS",
            "SSD"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "American pilot released on the Bridge of Spies after his U2 spy plane was shot down over the USSR.",
          "answer": "Francis Gary Powers"
        },
        {
          "question": "US State Department official accused by Whittaker Chambers of hiding secrets in a pumpkin.",
          "answer": "Alger Hiss"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ex-KGB officer who was poisoned with polonium in 2006 in London after his defection.",
          "answer": "Alexander Litvinenko"
        },
        {
          "question": "US counterintelligence program that decrypted Soviet messages, discovering the Cambridge Ring and exposing Klaus Fuchs.",
          "answer": "Venona Project"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Curse of Tippecanoe...",
      "prompt": "Name the the curse of tippecanoe......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Supposedly meant death for the holders of what elected political office, including Abe Lincoln?",
          "answer": "US President"
        },
        {
          "question": "First struck what man, who fought at Tippecanoe and died after just 31 days in office?",
          "answer": "William Henry Harrison"
        },
        {
          "question": "Struck at intervals of how many years between elections?",
          "answer": "20 years"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was “broken” when what man didn’t die after being shot by John Hinckley in 1981?",
          "answer": "Ronald Reagan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Struck what man in Buffalo, New York?",
          "answer": "William McKinley"
        },
        {
          "question": "Struck what man via unknown causes in 1923?",
          "answer": "William Harding"
        },
        {
          "question": "Is alternately named for what leader of the Shawnee who was killed two years after the Battle of Tippecanoe?",
          "answer": "Tecumseh"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was supposedly set by what man, the brother of that Shawnee leader?",
          "answer": [
            "Tenskwatawa",
            "the Prophet"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Susan B. Anthony",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Right that Anthony and other suffragettes sought.",
          "answer": "women’s right to vote"
        },
        {
          "question": "Constitutional amendment that guaranteed that right.",
          "answer": "19th Amendment to the US Constitution."
        },
        {
          "question": "Denomination of coin on which Anthony was honored in 1979.",
          "answer": "one dollar coin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Controversial type of dress, named for activist Amelia, that Anthony briefly wore.",
          "answer": [
            "Bloomer",
            "the Turkish dress"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "State where Anthony was arrested in Rochester in 1872 and was unable to attend the Seneca Falls Convention.",
          "answer": "New York"
        },
        {
          "question": "1893 event in Chicago where Anthony served in the World’s Congress of Representative Women.",
          "answer": [
            "World’s Columbian Exposition",
            "1893 Chicago World’s Fair"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Colleague of Anthony who wrote The Woman’s Bible and co-organized the Seneca Falls Convention.",
          "answer": "Elizabeth Cady Stanton"
        },
        {
          "question": "Newspaper published for four years by Anthony and the previous answer, funded by George Train.",
          "answer": "The Revolution"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The New Deal",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Global economic downturn that the New Deal counteracted.",
          "answer": "Great Depression"
        },
        {
          "question": "President who formulated the New Deal.",
          "answer": [
            "Franklin Delano Roosevelt",
            "FDR"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "New Deal program that provides an old age pension and now includes disability benefits.",
          "answer": [
            "Social Security",
            "additional information"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Failed plan to save the New Deal by manipulating the Supreme Court.",
          "answer": [
            "court packing",
            "anything related to adding more justices to the Supreme Court"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Artist for the WPA who captured the Migrant Mother photo.",
          "answer": "Dorothea Lange"
        },
        {
          "question": "State electrified by a namesake “Valley Authority” led by David Lilienthal.",
          "answer": "Tennessee"
        },
        {
          "question": "Economic concept suspended in the New Deal and ended by the later Bretton Woods conference, allowing the convertibility of a precious metal to dollars.",
          "answer": "gold standard do not"
        },
        {
          "question": "Advisor and Commerce Secretary who oversaw the Civil Works Administration and the Works Progress Administration.",
          "answer": "Harry Hopkins"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The First US Congress",
      "prompt": "Name the the first us congress...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "City whose Federal Hall hosted its first two sessions, as well as Washington’s inauguration.",
          "answer": "New York City or NYC"
        },
        {
          "question": "Set of the first ten Constitutional amendments, introduced in the House in 1789.",
          "answer": "Bill of Rights"
        },
        {
          "question": "Representative and future President who introduced those amendments.",
          "answer": "James Madison"
        },
        {
          "question": "State with the largest House delegation, including that future President.",
          "answer": "Virginia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Branch of the Armed Forces established in 1790 as the Revenue-Marine, a customs enforcement service.",
          "answer": "US Coast Guard"
        },
        {
          "question": "Retired general confirmed as Secretary of War in 1789.",
          "answer": "Henry Knox"
        },
        {
          "question": "State whose first Congressional delegation included Robert Morris and Speaker Frederick Muhlenberg.",
          "answer": "Pennsylvania"
        },
        {
          "question": "Author of the Judiciary Act of 1789, a Connecticut Senator who was later Chief Justice.",
          "answer": "Oliver Ellsworth"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Prohibition",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Constitutional Amendment that instituted prohibition of alcohol.",
          "answer": "18th Amendment to the US Constitution."
        },
        {
          "question": "Constitutional Amendment that repealed prohibition.",
          "answer": "21st Amendment to the US Constitution."
        },
        {
          "question": "Movement, the “T” in WCTU, that advocated for prohibition.",
          "answer": [
            "temperance",
            "word forms",
            "Women’s Christian Temperance Movement"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "“Hatchet woman” whose bar-smashing tactics earned her dozens of arrests.",
          "answer": "Carrie A. Nation"
        },
        {
          "question": "1919 Congressional act that legislated prohibition once it became constitutional law.",
          "answer": "Volstead Act"
        },
        {
          "question": "Investigator who led the Untouchables and took down Al Capone in Chicago.",
          "answer": "Eliot Ness"
        },
        {
          "question": "State where mayor Neal Dow spearheaded prohibition in the 19th century.",
          "answer": "Maine"
        },
        {
          "question": "Lobbyist and leader of the Anti-Saloon League who innovated “pressure politics.”",
          "answer": "Wayne Wheeler"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Early Pennsylvania",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "City that hosted the Constitutional Convention.",
          "answer": "Philadelphia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Religious group, including William Penn, that settled Pennsylvania.",
          "answer": [
            "Quakers",
            "Religious Society of Friends"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "King of England who granted William Penn the land in 1681, some two decades after he was restored to the throne.",
          "answer": "Charles II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Line that sets the Pennsylvania/Maryland border, named for its two surveyors.",
          "answer": "Mason-Dixon Line"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mosquito-borne disease that killed thousands of Pennsylvanians in fall 1793.",
          "answer": "yellow fever"
        },
        {
          "question": "1763 rebellion opposed by western Pennsylvania settlers via smallpox-infected blankets.",
          "answer": [
            "Pontiac’s Rebellion",
            "war, revolt, and other equivalents of rebellion"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Scots-Irish vigilante group that massacred the Susquehanna at the Conestoga Massacre.",
          "answer": "Paxton Boys"
        },
        {
          "question": "Native American tribe that granted the Walking Purchase to the Penn family, and which sold Manhattan to the Dutch.",
          "answer": [
            "Lenape",
            "Delaware"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "John Adams Administration",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Man who won the Election of 1800 to end Adams’ presidency.",
          "answer": "Thomas Jefferson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Cousin of John Adams who led the Boston Tea Party, served as governor, and owned a malthouse.",
          "answer": "Samuel Adams"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country where Adams supported Toussaint L’Ouverture’s revolution.",
          "answer": "Haiti"
        },
        {
          "question": "Man he appointed Chief Justice in 1801 and served for 35 years.",
          "answer": "John Marshall"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nickname for the judges, including William Marbury, that Adams appointed at the very end of his Presidency.",
          "answer": "midnight judges"
        },
        {
          "question": "Captain defended by Adams for allegedly ordering troops to fire during the Boston Massacre.",
          "answer": "Thomas Preston"
        },
        {
          "question": "1776 book, a response to Common Sense, in which Adams proposes a three-branch system with checks and balances.",
          "answer": "Thoughts on Government"
        },
        {
          "question": "Pennsylvania man who opposed the 1798 Direct House Tax and led a rebellion in Milford.",
          "answer": [
            "John Fries",
            "Fries’ Rebellion"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "1920s",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Woman who flew across the Atlantic in 1928 and disappeared in 1937.",
          "answer": "Amelia Earhart"
        },
        {
          "question": "13 year ban on alcohol established by the 18th Amendment and overturned by the 21st Amendment.",
          "answer": "Prohibition"
        },
        {
          "question": "Trial in Tennessee in which a teacher was prosecuted for teaching evolution.",
          "answer": [
            "Scopes Monkey Trial",
            "The State of Tennessee v. John Thomas Scopes"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Organization proposed in Woodrow Wilson’s 14 points, the predecessor to the United Nations.",
          "answer": "League of Nations"
        },
        {
          "question": "Color that names the Tuesday and Thursday which started and ended the stock market crash that began the Great Depression.",
          "answer": [
            "Black",
            "Black Tuesday and/or Black Thursday"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "System used by a namesake Emergency Act in 1921 to limit immigration via the National Origins Formula.",
          "answer": [
            "quota",
            "Emergency Quota Act"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Attorney General whose namesake raids targeted radicals during the first Red Scare.",
          "answer": "Alexander Mitchel Palmer"
        },
        {
          "question": "1928 Pact which resolved not to use war to resolve “disputes or conflicts of whatever nature.”",
          "answer": [
            "Kellogg-Briand Pact",
            "General Treaty for Renunciation of War as an Instrument of National Policy",
            "Pact of Paris"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Women’s Suffrage",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Constitutional amendment that guaranteed women’s right to vote.",
          "answer": "19th Amendment to the US Constitution"
        },
        {
          "question": "US President who eventually oversaw the passage of that amendment in 1920.",
          "answer": "Woodrow Wilson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Suffragette who inspired the first attempt at an amendment in 1872, the same year she was arrested for voting in New York.",
          "answer": "Susan B. Anthony"
        },
        {
          "question": "Western state where women’s suffrage was removed by Congress as a punishment for the Mormon practice of polygamy.",
          "answer": "Utah"
        },
        {
          "question": "New York town where Lucretia Mott and Elizabeth Cady Stanton organized the first women’s rights convention in 1848.",
          "answer": "Seneca Falls Convention"
        },
        {
          "question": "Western state where women could vote in 1869 and which insisted on keeping women’s suffrage when it joined the Union in 1890.",
          "answer": "Wyoming"
        },
        {
          "question": "Suffragette and “Silent Sentinel” who led the National Woman’s Party for decades.",
          "answer": "Alice Paul"
        },
        {
          "question": "Suffragette who was elected to Congress in 1916 and who was criticized for voting against entering World Wars I and II.",
          "answer": "Jeannette Rankin"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Third Crusade",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Target city of the Third Crusade, which sought to reclaim it from the Ayyubids.",
          "answer": "Jerusalem"
        },
        {
          "question": "Reigning English King and successor of Henry II, who led the crusade with Philip II of France.",
          "answer": "Richard I or Richard the Lionheart"
        },
        {
          "question": "Catholic military order whose members fought in the Third Crusade, bearing distinctive white banners with red crosses.",
          "answer": "Knights Templar"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ayyubid Sultan who conquered the Holy Land in 1187 with unified Egyptian and Syrian forces.",
          "answer": "Saladin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Holy Roman Emperor who also led troops during the Third Crusade, but drowned in a river before reaching the Holy Land.",
          "answer": [
            "Frederick Barbarossa",
            "Frederick I"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "City in present-day Israel that was besieged by Guy of Lusignan in 1189 and eventually recaptured.",
          "answer": "Acre"
        },
        {
          "question": "Port city that crusading forces managed to capture in 1191; it also names the treaty signed to end the Third Crusade.",
          "answer": "Treaty of Jaffa or Yaffa"
        },
        {
          "question": "Crushing 1187 battle that allowed Muslim forces to re-capture most of the Crusader-held cities in the Holy Land, leading to the Third Crusade.",
          "answer": "Battle of the Horns of Hattin"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Space Race",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "US government agency responsible for the administration of the space program.",
          "answer": "NASA or National Aeronautics and Space Administration"
        },
        {
          "question": "First artificial Earth satellite, launched in 1957 by the Soviet Union.",
          "answer": "Sputnik 1"
        },
        {
          "question": "First man in space, who entered orbit in the Vostok 1 in 1961.",
          "answer": "Yuri Alekseyevich Gagarin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dog plucked off the streets of Moscow who became the first animal to orbit the Earth in 1957.",
          "answer": "Laika"
        },
        {
          "question": "American mission whose three-man crew was lost to a cabin fire in 1967.",
          "answer": "Apollo 1"
        },
        {
          "question": "First American man in space; he later hit golf balls on the Moon.",
          "answer": "Alan Shepard"
        },
        {
          "question": "First space station operated by the United States; it orbited Earth from 1973 to 1979.",
          "answer": "Skylab"
        },
        {
          "question": "African-American mathematician who verified the computer’s orbital trajectories for John Glenn’s first orbit on Glenn’s request.",
          "answer": [
            "Katherine Johnson",
            "Katherine Coleman"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "War of 1812",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "American capital that was burned by the British.",
          "answer": [
            "Washington, DC",
            "either",
            "both"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Treaty that ended the war.",
          "answer": "Treaty of Ghent"
        },
        {
          "question": "Battle won by Andrew Jackson two weeks after that treaty had been signed.",
          "answer": "Battle of New Orleans"
        },
        {
          "question": "Frigate that became known as “Old Ironsides” during the war, named for a governmental document.",
          "answer": "USS Constitution"
        },
        {
          "question": "State represented in Congress by War Hawks like Richard Mentor Johnson and Henry Clay.",
          "answer": "Kentucky"
        },
        {
          "question": "City that William Hull surrendered to Isaac Brock and Tecumseh in 1812.",
          "answer": "Detroit"
        },
        {
          "question": "American defeat in August 1814 that allowed the British to burn the capital.",
          "answer": "Battle of Bladensburg"
        },
        {
          "question": "British rocket, based on a Mysorean design, used at the siege of Fort McHenry.",
          "answer": "Congreve rocket"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "James Madison",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Home state of Madison, as well as early American presidents George Washington and Thomas Jefferson.",
          "answer": "Virginia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Set of Constitutional amendments authored by Madison.",
          "answer": "Bill of Rights"
        },
        {
          "question": "Politician who served as Madison’s Secretary of State and his successor as President.",
          "answer": "James Monroe"
        },
        {
          "question": "Set of papers that James Madison co-wrote under the pseudonym Publius in support of the U.S. Constitution.",
          "answer": "Federalist Papers"
        },
        {
          "question": "Party founded by Madison and Jefferson on whose ticket Madison ran for the presidency.",
          "answer": "Democratic-Republican Party do not"
        },
        {
          "question": "Representative who names two bills dealing with attacks on American shipping that Madison signed.",
          "answer": "Nathaniel Macon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Candidate who opposed Madison in his first bid for the presidency.",
          "answer": "Charles Cotesworth Pinckney"
        },
        {
          "question": "Slave owned by Madison who bought his freedom with Daniel Webster’s help and published a memoir in 1865.",
          "answer": "Paul Jennings"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Reconstruction",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "US President whose assassination prevented the original plans for Reconstruction.",
          "answer": "Abraham Lincoln"
        },
        {
          "question": "Group of Republicans who pushed for civil rights for former slaves and the impeachment of Andrew Johnson.",
          "answer": "Radical Republicans"
        },
        {
          "question": "President whose controversial election in 1876 ended Reconstruction.",
          "answer": "Rutherford B. Hayes"
        },
        {
          "question": "Democrat who lost the 1876 election.",
          "answer": "Samuel Tilden"
        },
        {
          "question": "Agency led by Oliver Otis Howard that provided aid to former slaves, legendarily including “40 acres and a mule.”",
          "answer": "Freedmen’s Bureau or Bureau of Refugees, Freedmen, and Abandoned Lands"
        },
        {
          "question": "1864 bill outlining re-admittance procedures that was pocket-vetoed by the president.",
          "answer": "Wade-Davis Bill"
        },
        {
          "question": "Oath that would have been required by that bill, forcing its taker to swear he had “never voluntarily borne arms” against the US.",
          "answer": "Ironclad Oath"
        },
        {
          "question": "book.",
          "answer": "Eric Foner"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Philippines",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country that held power over the Philippines until after World War II.",
          "answer": [
            "United States of America",
            "America"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Capital city whose dialect of Tagalog was defined as a national language in the 20th century.",
          "answer": "Manila"
        },
        {
          "question": "Religion of Cardinal Jaime Sin, who was instrumental in the Philippines’ regime change in 1986.",
          "answer": "Roman Catholicism"
        },
        {
          "question": "President and dictator of the Philippines from 1965 to 1986, when he was overthrown.",
          "answer": "Ferdinand Marcos"
        },
        {
          "question": "1986 campaign of civil resistance that led to the overthrow of that leader.",
          "answer": [
            "People Power Revolution",
            "EDSA Revolution"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Palacethatwasstormedduringthat1986revolution,revealingtheFirstLady’scollectionofthousands of shoes.",
          "answer": "Malacanang Palace"
        },
        {
          "question": "Family that included a senator assassinated in 1983, the first female president of the Philippines, and another president who preceded Rodrigo Duterte.",
          "answer": [
            "Aquino family",
            "Benigno Aquino Jr., Corazon Aquino, and/or Benigno Aquino III"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Name for the Muslim population of the Philippines; a namesake National Liberation Front fought for an autonomous region on Mindanao.",
          "answer": "Moro people"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Watergate",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "President who resigned after the scandal.",
          "answer": "Richard M. Nixon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Political group whose headquarters at the Watergate hotel was burgled.",
          "answer": "Democratic National Committee or DNC"
        },
        {
          "question": "Position held by Elliot Richardson until the Saturday Night Massacre, when he resigned rather than fire the special prosecutor.",
          "answer": "Attorney General"
        },
        {
          "question": "Fundraising group that paid legal expenses for the Watergate burglars, in addition to its stated purpose.",
          "answer": "CREEP"
        },
        {
          "question": "FBI agent who was the anonymous source “Deep Throat.”",
          "answer": "W. Mark Felt, Sr."
        },
        {
          "question": "Head of “the Plumbers” and organizer of the burglary, supervising it with E. Howard Hunt.",
          "answer": "G. Gordon Liddy"
        },
        {
          "question": "White House Chief of Staff who was convicted of obstruction of justice for his role in the scandal.",
          "answer": "H.R. Haldeman"
        },
        {
          "question": "Deputy who was the second to resign, after Richardson, in the Saturday Night Massacre.",
          "answer": "William Ruckelshaus"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Andrew Carnegie",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Commodity, an alloy of iron and carbon, whose industry he dominated.",
          "answer": "steel industry"
        },
        {
          "question": "Large western Pennsylvania city where his business empire was centered.",
          "answer": "Pittsburgh"
        },
        {
          "question": "Founder of Standard Oil who he passed as “richest American” after selling his company.",
          "answer": "John D. Rockefeller"
        },
        {
          "question": "American financier who bought Carnegie’s company for over $300 million in 1901.",
          "answer": "John Pierpont “J.P.” Morgan Sr."
        },
        {
          "question": "1889 essay in which Carnegie argued that industry leaders should gain, then donate, their riches.",
          "answer": "The Gospel of Wealth"
        },
        {
          "question": "Detective agency that his manager hired to put down the Homestead Strike.",
          "answer": "Pinkerton National Detective Agency"
        },
        {
          "question": "Aforementioned manager, who was nearly assassinated by Alexander Berkman.",
          "answer": "Henry Clay Frick"
        },
        {
          "question": "IndustrialistcolleagueandTreasurySecretaryunderthreepresidentswhopartiallynamesaPittsburgh university.",
          "answer": [
            "Andrew Mellon",
            "Carnegie Mellon University"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Boston Massacre",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "State where it took place.",
          "answer": "Massachusetts"
        },
        {
          "question": "Future President who defended the accused soldiers.",
          "answer": "John Adams"
        },
        {
          "question": "First casualty of the attack, a man not included in a famous Henry Pelham engraving of the event.",
          "answer": "Crispus Attucks"
        },
        {
          "question": "Boston silversmith who copied that Pelham engraving and, five years later, made a famous midnight ride.",
          "answer": "Paul Revere"
        },
        {
          "question": "British commander-in-chief who originally placed troops in Boston years earlier; he was replaced by General Howe in 1775.",
          "answer": "Thomas Gage"
        },
        {
          "question": "Street on which it took place.",
          "answer": "King Street"
        },
        {
          "question": "Politician, the namesake of a college in Maine, who wrote A Short Narrative of the Horrid Massacre.",
          "answer": "James Bowdoin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Captain of the British soldiers during the massacre; he was acquitted because he did not give an order to fire.",
          "answer": "Thomas Preston"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Republic of Texas",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country from which Texas won its independence.",
          "answer": "Mexico"
        },
        {
          "question": "River that Texas claimed as its southern border, and which is the eastern end of the modern US-Mexico border.",
          "answer": "Rio Grande"
        },
        {
          "question": "Process by which Texas joined the United States in 1845.",
          "answer": "annexation"
        },
        {
          "question": "US President who signed the bill authorizing that process, two days before he left office.",
          "answer": "John Tyler"
        },
        {
          "question": "General and first President of the republic who was ousted as Governor of Texas after it seceded from the Union.",
          "answer": "Samuel Houston"
        },
        {
          "question": "1836 battle where that general routed Santa Anna’s men in less than 20 minutes, securing independence.",
          "answer": "Battle of San Jacinto"
        },
        {
          "question": "1836 massacre where James Fannin and hundreds of prisoners of war were killed by Santa Anna’s men.",
          "answer": "Goliad Massacre"
        },
        {
          "question": "Second President of the republic, who issued “redback” currency.",
          "answer": "Mirabeau Lamar"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Cuban Missile Crisis",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Soviet leader who sparred with Kennedy during the crisis.",
          "answer": "Nikita Khrushchev"
        },
        {
          "question": "Soviet capital city connected to DC by a special hotline after the crisis.",
          "answer": "Moscow"
        },
        {
          "question": "Number of days the crisis lasted; also the title of Robert Kennedy’s memoir of the crisis.",
          "answer": "Thirteen Days"
        },
        {
          "question": "Burmese diplomat who mediated the crisis as UN Secretary-General.",
          "answer": "U Thant"
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of ballistic missile that the Americans secretly dismantled and removed as part of the crisis resolution.",
          "answer": "PGM-19 Jupiter ballistic missiles"
        },
        {
          "question": "Either of the two countries from which those missiles were secretly removed.",
          "answer": "Turkey and/or Italy"
        },
        {
          "question": "American ambassador who demanded “don’t wait for the translation!” in a heated UN Security Council meeting during the crisis.",
          "answer": "Adlai Stevenson II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Russian submarine officer who refused to authorize a nuclear strike during the crisis, saving the world from nuclear war.",
          "answer": "Vasily Arkhipov"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "19th Century US Legislation",
      "prompt": "For all answers, you need not say “Act,” “Bill,” “Law,” or similar terms. Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Ohio Congressman who introduced a massive 1890 Tariff Act, was elected President in 1896, and was shot in 1901.",
          "answer": [
            "William McKinley",
            "McKinley Tariff"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1890 Antitrust Act, named for an Ohio Senator, that was later expanded by the Clayton Act.",
          "answer": "Sherman Antitrust Act"
        },
        {
          "question": "1862 act that offered 160 acres of farmable Western land to citizens willing to improve it.",
          "answer": "Homestead Act"
        },
        {
          "question": "1850 act that required Northerners to arrest blacks suspected of having escaped slavery.",
          "answer": "Fugitive Slave Act"
        },
        {
          "question": "1883 act that reformed civil service by mostly eliminating the spoils system.",
          "answer": "Pendleton Civil Service Reform Act"
        },
        {
          "question": "1898 amendment that prevented the US from annexing Cuba during the Spanish-American War.",
          "answer": "Teller Amendment or Teller Resolution"
        },
        {
          "question": "1878 act requiring the Treasury Department to buy quotas of silver and circulate silver dollars.",
          "answer": "Bland-Allison Act"
        },
        {
          "question": "1878 act banning the Army from engaging in domestic law enforcement, given a two-word Latin name.",
          "answer": "Posse Comitatus Act"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Japanese-American Internment",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "War in which the United States started interning the Japanese-Americans after Pearl Harbor.",
          "answer": "World War II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Government program whose neighborhood-level data, collected every 10 years, was used to identify Japanese for internment.",
          "answer": "US Census Bureau"
        },
        {
          "question": "Large camp in California’s Owens Valley, the first to be constructed.",
          "answer": [
            "Manzanar War Relocation Center",
            "any additional information with Manzanar"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Executive order, issued by FDR, that implemented internment.",
          "answer": "Executive Order 9066"
        },
        {
          "question": "California politician, Attorney General until 1943 and Governor after, who publicly pushed for internment.",
          "answer": "Earl Warren"
        },
        {
          "question": "Activist who lost a 1944 Supreme Court case upholding the legality of the exclusion zones.",
          "answer": [
            "Fred Korematsu",
            "Korematsu v. US"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Justice who wrote the majority opinion of that case, holding that protection outweighed civil liberties.",
          "answer": "Hugo Black"
        },
        {
          "question": "General who oversaw the internment through his Military Proclamation Number 1, claiming it was merely an evacuation.",
          "answer": "John L. Dewitt"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Vice Presidential Fails",
      "prompt": "Name the Vice President who…...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Shot and killed Alexander Hamilton in an 1804 duel.",
          "answer": "Aaron Burr"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was not involved in the Watergate scandal but resigned in 1973.",
          "answer": "Spiro Agnew"
        },
        {
          "question": "Feuded with Andrew Jackson about tariffs before resigning.",
          "answer": "John C. Calhoun"
        },
        {
          "question": "Gave the “Checkers” speech following a campaign fund controversy.",
          "answer": "Richard Nixon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was implicated in the Whiskey Ring under Ulysses Grant.",
          "answer": "Schuyler Colfax"
        },
        {
          "question": "Infamously misspelled the word “potato”",
          "answer": "Dan Quayle"
        },
        {
          "question": "Arrived too late to make the tie-breaking vote for Coolidge's nominee for Attorney General.",
          "answer": "Charles G. Dawes"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was replaced on the incumbent ticket by Harry Truman due to his incompetence.",
          "answer": "Henry Wallace"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Cattle Ranching",
      "prompt": "Name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "American variety of the vaquero, a ubiquitous Western animal herder.",
          "answer": "Cowboy"
        },
        {
          "question": "1862 Act that allowed for settlers to claim farms, conflicting with ranchers.",
          "answer": "Homestead Act"
        },
        {
          "question": "Large Great Plains animals that were simultaneously slaughtered en masse as cattle population grew.",
          "answer": [
            "American bison",
            "American buffalo"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Metal invention of Joseph Glidden, a means of fencing in cattle.",
          "answer": [
            "Barbed wire",
            "Bobbed wire"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Term for a skilled Argentine horseman, central to South American ranching culture.",
          "answer": "Gaucho"
        },
        {
          "question": "Cattle trail on which Margaret Borland drove 2500 cattle from Texas to Wichita.",
          "answer": "Chisholm Trail"
        },
        {
          "question": "British captain who charted the coast of British Columbia and brought cattle to Hawaii.",
          "answer": "George Vancouver"
        },
        {
          "question": "Eastern island location of Deep Hollow Ranch, reputed to be the first ranch in the US.",
          "answer": "Long Island, New York 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 2"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "American Red Cross",
      "prompt": "Name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Founder of the American Red Cross.",
          "answer": "Clara Barton"
        },
        {
          "question": "Standard Oil tycoon who funded it.",
          "answer": "John D. Rockefeller"
        },
        {
          "question": "US President, also a Supreme Court Chief Justice, who was Chairperson from 1915 to 1919.",
          "answer": "William Howard Taft"
        },
        {
          "question": "2005 hurricane after which it raised more than $2 billion to aid the New Orleans area.",
          "answer": "Katrina"
        },
        {
          "question": "Disease that crippled FDR against which president Basil O'Connor fought.",
          "answer": "Poliomyelitis"
        },
        {
          "question": "Company that sued the American Red Cross over their emblem.",
          "answer": "Johnson & Johnson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Most destructive European earthquake that struck Reggio Calabria, after which it started international aid.",
          "answer": "1908 Messina earthquake"
        },
        {
          "question": "Humanitarian village the American Red Cross created after the Battle of Caporetto.",
          "answer": "Pisa Village 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 5"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Pilgrims",
      "prompt": "Name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Ship on which they sailed to Massachusetts and signed a compact.",
          "answer": "Mayflower"
        },
        {
          "question": "Rock on which they legendarily “landed” that also names their colony.",
          "answer": "Plymouth Rock"
        },
        {
          "question": "Patuxet tribe member who helped them plant maize and get fish.",
          "answer": "Squanto or Tisquantum"
        },
        {
          "question": "Native American Confederacy that Massasoit and King Philip led.",
          "answer": "Wampanoag or Wopanaak"
        },
        {
          "question": "Great Triumvirate member who gave the oration at their bicentennial and also gave the Bunker Hill Monument Oration.",
          "answer": "Daniel Webster"
        },
        {
          "question": "Five-time colony governor who succeeded the first governor, John Carver.",
          "answer": "William Bradford"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dish made of sweet corn and lima beans likely eaten at the first Thanksgiving.",
          "answer": "Succotash"
        },
        {
          "question": "Annual Massachusetts holiday celebrated by the Old Colony Club to honor the Pilgrims.",
          "answer": "Forefathers' Day 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 1"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "American Environmentalism",
      "prompt": "Name the…...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Society George Bird Grinnel founded named for a French-American bird watcher.",
          "answer": "National Audubon Society"
        },
        {
          "question": "Structures some Conservationists oppose, such as the Glen Canyon version on the Colorado River.",
          "answer": "Dam"
        },
        {
          "question": "April 22 celebration of the protection our planet, proposed by Gaylord Nelson.",
          "answer": "Earth Day"
        },
        {
          "question": "Scottish-American who preserved Yosemite and founded the Sierra Club.",
          "answer": "John Muir"
        },
        {
          "question": "Minnesota presidential candidate who the Sierra Club supported against Ronald Reagan in 1984.",
          "answer": "Walter \"Fritz\" Mondale"
        },
        {
          "question": "Reservoir in Yosemite over which Conservationists and Preservationists fought about the water supply.",
          "answer": "Hetch Hetchy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Supreme Court Justice who suggested that environmental objects like valleys can be granted personhood in the Morton case.",
          "answer": "William O. Douglas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ivy League school which operates the eBird program at its Lab of Ornithology in Sapsucker Woods.",
          "answer": "Cornell University 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 2"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Wells Fargo and the West",
      "prompt": "In the history of Wells Fargo in the Western United States, name the…...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Mail service utilizing horses that Wells Fargo controlled from 1860 to 1861.",
          "answer": "Pony Express"
        },
        {
          "question": "California state capital with Wells Fargo's second office.",
          "answer": "Sacramento"
        },
        {
          "question": "Communication method using Morse Code that hurt Wells Fargo's transportation services.",
          "answer": "Telegraphy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of horse-drawn vehicle Wells Fargo utilized to control western transportation.",
          "answer": "Stagecoach"
        },
        {
          "question": "American credit card giant that Wells and Fargo founded.",
          "answer": "American Express or AMEX"
        },
        {
          "question": "Company that built the transcontinental railroad with Union Pacific, whose Pacific Union Express was acquired by Wells Fargo.",
          "answer": "Central Pacific Railroad"
        },
        {
          "question": "New York city for which William Fargo served as mayor during the Civil War.",
          "answer": "Buffalo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Company joined with Wells Fargo and Overland in the Western mail “grand consolidation.”",
          "answer": "Holladay 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 3"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "D-Day",
      "prompt": "Concerning the invasion of France, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Major 20th-century war during which D-Day took place.",
          "answer": "World War Two or the Second World War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Supreme Allied commander and future U.S. president who masterminded the D-day landings.",
          "answer": "Dwight David Eisenhower"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dictator of the Soviet Union who demanded the Allies start a \"Second Front\" in Western Europe.",
          "answer": "Joseph Stalin or Iosif Vissarionovich Stalin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Region of northern France where the D-Day landings occurred.",
          "answer": "Normandy or Normandie"
        },
        {
          "question": "Deadliest beach where nearly 4,000 American soldiers lost their lives.",
          "answer": "Omaha Beach"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nazi field marshal known as the \"Desert Fox\" who manned the Atlantic Wall fortifications.",
          "answer": "Erwin Rommel or Johannes Erwin Eugen Rommel"
        },
        {
          "question": "Westernmost beach the Americans attacked, lying on the Cotentin peninsula.",
          "answer": "Utah Beach"
        },
        {
          "question": "Vegetable nickname given to defensive wooden poles used by the Germans to injure Allied paratroopers and gliders.",
          "answer": [
            "Rommel's Asparagus",
            "Holzpfähle",
            "Luftlandehindernis 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 1"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Women's Suffrage",
      "prompt": "Concerning Women's Suffrage, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Editor of the North Star who said he wouldn't vote as a Black man until women could vote.",
          "answer": [
            "Frederick Douglass",
            "Frederick Augustus Washington Bailey"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "American activist who once appeared on the dollar coin, later replaced by Sacagawea [[sah-kah-jah-WEH-ah]].",
          "answer": "Susan B. Anthony"
        },
        {
          "question": "New York \"Convention,\" the first major U.S. suffrage meeting, held in 1848.",
          "answer": "Seneca Falls Convention"
        },
        {
          "question": "Author of the \"Declaration of Sentiments\" who wrote the History of Women's Suffrage.",
          "answer": "Elizabeth Cady Stanton"
        },
        {
          "question": "Constitutional amendment which stopped states from denying the right to vote to women.",
          "answer": "19th Amendment"
        },
        {
          "question": "Founder of the militant National Woman's Party, a suffragist movement which later supported the ERA.",
          "answer": "Alice Paul or Alice Stokes Paul"
        },
        {
          "question": "170 mile \"hike\" undertaken by the female \"Army of the Hudson\" to petition the new governor of New York.",
          "answer": "1912 \"Hike to Albany\""
        },
        {
          "question": "Group which led a noiseless vigil in front of Woodrow Wilson's White House.",
          "answer": [
            "Silent Sentinels",
            "Sentinels of Liberty 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 10 Rise of Nazism"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Wild West",
      "prompt": "Concerning the Wild, Wild West, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Occupation of horse-riding cattle herders that became synonymous with the Wild West.",
          "answer": [
            "Cowboy or Cowgirl",
            "Cowpuncher",
            "Buckaroo"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Short-lived courier service of men on horseback who travelled between the states of Missouri and California.",
          "answer": "Pony Express"
        },
        {
          "question": "Outlaw, known by the pseudonym William H. Bonney, who was shot down by Pat Garrett in New Mexico.",
          "answer": [
            "Billy the Kid",
            "Henry McCarty"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Politician who hunted bison out West and built a Dakota cattle ranch prior to serving as vice president to William McKinley.",
          "answer": [
            "Theodore Roosevelt Jr",
            "Teddy Roosevelt"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "State, formerly known as the Indian Territory, which was opened up to white settlement in 1889, causing a land rush.",
          "answer": [
            "Oklahoma",
            "Oklahoma Land Rush"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Nickname for Black soldiers who fought in the Plains Wars of the late nineteenth century.",
          "answer": "Buffalo Soldiers"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"Thesis\" put forth by Frederick Jackson Turner that the flux experienced by the North American pioneer shaped America's national character.",
          "answer": "Frontier Thesis"
        },
        {
          "question": "Tribe of the Southern Plains which established an \"empire\" from Texas to Kansas that collapsed in the 1870s due to smallpox.",
          "answer": [
            "Comanche",
            "Comancheria",
            "Comanche Empire",
            "or Nʉmʉnʉʉ Sookobitʉ 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 2"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "War of 1812",
      "prompt": "Answer these questions about War of 1812...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Two belligerents of the War of 1812.",
          "answer": [
            "UK and the USA",
            "United Kingdom and United States"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Virginian who was president during the War of 1812.",
          "answer": "James Madison"
        },
        {
          "question": "Final major battle of the war, a victory by Andrew Jackson over Edward Packenham.",
          "answer": "Battle of New Orleans"
        },
        {
          "question": "Act signed into law by Thomas Jefferson that succeeded the Non-Importation Act, preceding the War of 1812.",
          "answer": "Embargo Act of 1807"
        },
        {
          "question": "Treaty named for a Belgian city which formally ended the war.",
          "answer": "Treaty of Ghent"
        },
        {
          "question": "State bordering Canada whose cities of Bangor and Castine were looted by several Redcoat expeditions.",
          "answer": "Maine"
        },
        {
          "question": "1814 battle in Maryland which led to the Burning of Washington D.C.",
          "answer": "Battle of Bladensburg"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ship captained by James Richard Dacres that was captured early in the War of 1812 by the USS Constitution.",
          "answer": "HMS Guerriere ] 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 4"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "California Gold Rush",
      "prompt": "Concerning the California gold rush, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "General term for communities that exploded in population in a short period of time during the Gold Rush.",
          "answer": "Boomtown"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nickname of those who participated in the Gold Rush, based on a specific year.",
          "answer": "49er"
        },
        {
          "question": "Popular clothing item manufactured by Levi Strauss.",
          "answer": [
            "Blue Jeans",
            "Denim Jeans"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Mill at which the discovery of gold sparked the Gold Rush.",
          "answer": "Sutter's Mill"
        },
        {
          "question": "Simple method used by miners to extract gold from streams by using a namesake iron apparatus.",
          "answer": "Panning"
        },
        {
          "question": "Eastern California mountain range which contained many of the goldfields targeted by prospectors.",
          "answer": "Sierra Nevada Mountains or Sierra Nevadas"
        },
        {
          "question": "U.S. author who used it as the backdrop for his short story \"The Luck of Roaring Camp.\"",
          "answer": "Bret Harte or Francis Bret Harte"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ship carrying three tons of gold which sank off the Carolina coast during an 1857 hurricane.",
          "answer": "SS Central America 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 5"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Third Crusade",
      "prompt": "Concerning the Third Crusade, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Holy city whose capture led to the call for the Third Crusade.",
          "answer": "Jerusalem"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"Lion-Hearted\" king who led the English after the death of his father, Henry II.",
          "answer": "King Richard I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Kurdish sultan whose conquests prompted the late 12th century Crusade.",
          "answer": "Saladin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ismaili sect and anti-Crusader faction in Syria who now names the English term for a \"trained killer.\"",
          "answer": [
            "Assassins",
            "Hashashins"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "German emperor who drowned in a river while heading to fight the Sultanate of Rum.",
          "answer": [
            "Frederick Barbarossa",
            "Frederick I"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Port whose successful siege by Guy [[GEE]] of Jerusalem allowed the Crusaders to launch incursions into the Holy Land.",
          "answer": "Acre ]"
        },
        {
          "question": "Twin-peaked volcano near which a Crusader army was destroyed, prompting the Third Crusade two years later.",
          "answer": [
            "Hattin or Horns of Hattin",
            "Battle of Hattin",
            "or Battle of the Horns of Hattin",
            "Hittin"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "City which names a treaty which recognized Muslim control of Jerusalem in exchange for safe Christian pilgrimage.",
          "answer": [
            "Treaty of Jaffa",
            "Treaty of Ramla 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 5 Ancient Monuments of the World"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "United States Generals",
      "prompt": "Name the U.S. general who...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was appointed to lead the Continental Army in the Revolutionary War.",
          "answer": "George Washington"
        },
        {
          "question": "Turned down the offer to lead Union troops to command the opposing Army of Northern Virginia instead.",
          "answer": "Robert Edward Lee"
        },
        {
          "question": "Declared \"I shall return\" after fleeing the Philippines to avoid Japanese capture in 1942.",
          "answer": "Douglas MacArthur"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was sent to Mexico in an attempt to capture the revolutionary Pancho Villa [[VEE- yah]].",
          "answer": "John \"Black Jack\" Pershing or John Joseph Pershing"
        },
        {
          "question": "Created the Anaconda Plan and served in the War of 1812 and the Mexican- American War.",
          "answer": "Winfield Scott"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the last to achieve the rank of Five Star General, second in command to Eisenhower during the Liberation of France.",
          "answer": "Omar Bradley Omar Nelson Bradley"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the leader of all coalition forces during Operation Desert Storm in the Persian Gulf War.",
          "answer": "\"Stormin'\" Norman Schwarzkopf or Herbert Norman Schwarzkopf, Jr."
        },
        {
          "question": "Was named for a South American liberator and died commanding troops on Okinawa, becoming the highest-ranking U.S. officer to die from enemy fire in World War Two.",
          "answer": "Simon Bolivar Buckner Jr."
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Duels",
      "prompt": "Concerning dueling in American history, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Secretary of the Treasury who was killed in a duel by Aaron Burr.",
          "answer": "Alexander Hamilton"
        },
        {
          "question": "President, nicknamed “Old Hickory,” who killed Charles Dickinson in a duel.",
          "answer": "Andrew Jackson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Man who crossed swords with Illinois politician James Shields before becoming the first Republican president in 1860.",
          "answer": "Abraham Lincoln"
        },
        {
          "question": "Hero of the Barbary Wars who was shot and killed in a duel by James Barron.",
          "answer": "Stephen Decatur Jr."
        },
        {
          "question": "Boarding stable at which Wyatt Earp and Doc Holiday shot a group of Cowboys led by the Clanton brothers.",
          "answer": [
            "O.K. Corral",
            "Gunfight at the O.K. Corral",
            "equivalents"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Dangerous Kansas cattle town where numerous duels occurred, inspiring the phrase \"Get out of [this city].\"",
          "answer": "Dodge City"
        },
        {
          "question": "Folk hero and gunslinger who was shot and killed playing poker in Deadwood.",
          "answer": [
            "Wild Bill Hickock",
            "either underlined answer"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Revolutionary War general who was shot by John Laurens in a duel after disrespecting George Washington.",
          "answer": "Charles Henry Lee 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 7"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Regarding losing U.S. presidential candidates, name the...",
      "prompt": "Concerning Regarding losing U.S. presidential candidates, name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Tennessee Democrat who was defeated in 2000 due to 537 votes from the state of Florida.",
          "answer": "Al Gore or Albert Arnold Al Gore Jr."
        },
        {
          "question": "Illinois senator who debated Abraham Lincoln years before losing to him in 1860.",
          "answer": "Stephen Arnold Douglas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Utah senator and former Governor of Massachusetts who unsuccessfully challenged Obama's second run for president.",
          "answer": "Mitt Romney or Willard Mitt Romney"
        },
        {
          "question": "Arizona conservative who lost to Lyndon B. Johnson in 1964.",
          "answer": "Barry Goldwater or Barry Morris Goldwater"
        },
        {
          "question": "Alabama governor who ran as a segregationist in 1968 and was later shot and paralyzed.",
          "answer": "George Wallace or George Corley Wallace Jr."
        },
        {
          "question": "Liberal Democrat who won only his home state of Minnesota in a landslide loss to Ronald Reagan in 1984.",
          "answer": "Walter \"Fritz\" Mondale or Walter Frederick Mondale"
        },
        {
          "question": "South Carolina Dixiecrat who finished third in 1948, losing to both Dewey and Truman.",
          "answer": "Strom Thurmond or James Strom Thurmond Sr."
        },
        {
          "question": "Governor of Ohio who ran on a ticket with FDR in 1920, losing to Republican Warren G. Harding.",
          "answer": "James M. Cox or James Middleton Cox 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 8 Medieval English Monarchs at War"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Archaeologists on this continent uncover bone \"projectile points\" made by the Clovis culture. \"Atlanteans\" are freestanding columns carved in the shape of warriors at Tula on this continent, where a circle called (20 pts)",
        "\"Woodhenge\" and Monks' Mound were in a large city made on raised earthworks at (10 pts)",
        "Cahokia. For 10 points, name this continent once home to the Mississippian culture, which was first settled by humans who crossed a land bridge across the Bering strait."
      ],
      "answer": "North America"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was speaking to a \"sewing society\" in Rochester when he asked \"What to the slave is the Fourth of July?\" This husband of Helen Pitts did not consent to his nomination as the (20 pts)",
        "Equal Rights Party's Vice-Presidential candidate on the Victoria Woodhull ticket. This survivor of the \"breaker\" Mr. Covey published The (10 pts)",
        "North Star and several autobiographies including My Bondage and My Freedom. For 10 points, name this anti-slavery orator."
      ],
      "answer": "Frederick Douglass"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This movement's leaders included the president of the Morton Salt Company and retired general Robert Wood, then an executive at Sears. A prominent spokesman for this movement discredited it by denouncing (20 pts)",
        "Jews in Des Moines. This movement was unofficially supported by the (10 pts)",
        "German-American Bund. For 10 points, name this movement which moved from promoting neutrality to Nazi sympathy in the days before World War II, and included Charles Lindbergh."
      ],
      "answer": "America First Committee"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man's campaign commercials, which were designed by Richard Wirthlin, included the \"bear in the woods ad\" advocating military preparedness. He asked \"are you better off now than you were four years ago?\" when he won the Presidency and was re-elected on the (20 pts)",
        "\"Morning in America\" campaign. This supporter of the Strategic Defense Initiative defeated (10 pts)",
        "Walter Mondale by a landslide in 1984. For 10 points, name this Republican President of the 1980s."
      ],
      "answer": "Ronald Wilson Reagan"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Governor William Lane forced the negotiation of this event, which was the high-water mark for William Marcy and other proponents of a southern route for the (20 pts)",
        "Transcontinental Railroad. This event resulted in a ten million dollar price being paid for the Mesilla Valley area. This event was negotiated by the American ambassador to (10 pts)",
        "Mexico, with Santa Anna. For 10 points, name this this 1853 land transfer of parts of Arizona and New Mexico to the United States."
      ],
      "answer": "Gadsden Purchase"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In retirement from politics, this man wrote a bizarre novel about a conspiracy to destroy the United States, entitled The Canfield Decision. This man was mocked as receiving \"the greatest deal since the Lord spared Isaac on the mountaintop\" when he was able to plead to only (20 pts)",
        "tax evasion after accepting substantial bribes, causing his 1973 (10 pts)",
        "resignation. For 10 points, name this Greek-American, and Maryland-born Vice-President under Richard Nixon."
      ],
      "answer": "Spiro Agnew"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) At one of these events, a man denounced an idea as \"thin as a homeopathic soup made\nby boiling the shadow of a pigeon that starved to death.\" These events, which were held in\ntowns such as (20 pts) ",
        "Alton, Galesburg, and Quincy, failed to prevent the (10 pts) ",
        "\"Little Giant\" from\nwinning a Senatorial election. For 10 points, what were these 1858 clashes of rhetoric in Illinois,\nwhich set up a rematch among their participants in the Presidential election of two years later?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Lincoln-Douglas debates",
        "Lincoln-Douglas"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) One leader of this nation has attempted to re-nationalize its YPF oil company, while\nanother formed the Triple-A death squad to counteract leftist elements. The Justicialist\nparty in this nation split into three parts, one of which was led by former president Carlos (20 pts) ",
        "Menem. Another leader of this nation was overthrown by Jorge Videla’s junta, which\nthen instigated the (10 pts) ",
        "Dirty War. For 10 points, name this nation once headed by Juan Peron."
      ],
      "answer": "Argentina"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) Charles Ogle mockingly accused Martin van Buren of eating with a spoon made of these\nsubstance. A speech about this substance exclaimed \"you shall not press down upon the\nbrow of labor this (20 pts) ",
        "crown of thorns.\" This substance was sought by men who went to the (10 pts) ",
        "Klondike, the 49ers, and other prospectors. For 10 points, name this substance whose\n\"standard\" was, until 1971, the basis of American money."
      ],
      "answer": "gold"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This woman signed herself \"FWOTSC\" in a letter objecting to the term \"nine old men.\" This woman was the majority leader of the Arizona State Senate prior to her appointment to the (20 pts)",
        "Maricopa County Superior Court in 1975. She was replaced by Samuel Alito after retiring in 2005. She was nominated in 1981 to take the seat of (10 pts)",
        "Potter Stewart, by President Reagan. For 10 points, name this first woman to serve on the U.S. Supreme Court."
      ],
      "answer": "Sandra Day O'Connor"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This loser of the Battle of Valcour Island fell under suspicion for marrying Peggy Shippen. This man supported Ethan Allen's Green Mountain Boys in the capture of Fort (20 pts)",
        "Ticonderoga and was a key American presence at the Battle of (10 pts)",
        "Saratoga. Later, this man conspired with John Andre to surrender West Point. For 10 points, identify this American Revolutionary War general whose name is now synonymous with treason."
      ],
      "answer": "Benedict Arnold"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An extensive study of these people was compiled by Thomas McKenney and James Hall in the 1830s. These people are the subject of Helen Hunt Jackson's book A Century of Dishonor. Scott O'Dell wrote about a woman from this general group of people in (20 pts)",
        "Island of the Blue Dolphins, and these general people are the subjects of most books by (10 pts)",
        "Vine Deloria and Sherman Alexie. For 10 points, name these people who appear in pre- Columbian North American histories."
      ],
      "answer": "American Indians"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Roswell Field took over a pro bono defense for this case after the death of David Hall. Benjamin Curtis and John McLean dissented in this case, which concerned the defendant’s time spent in (20 pts)",
        "Wisconsin. Roger Taney’s [TAW-nee’s] decision in this case was a dismissal on grounds that the defendant could not legally (10 pts)",
        "file a lawsuit. The Missouri Compromise was ruled unconstitutional by, for ten points, what 1857 Supreme Court case that ruled African-Americans were not U.S. citizens?"
      ],
      "answer": "Dred Scott v. James F. A. Sanford or Dred Scott v. Sandford"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man, who advocated for Five Principles of Peaceful Coexistence towards a northern neighbor, ordered the annexation of Goa from Portugal in 1961’s Operation Vijay. This leader of the (20 pts)",
        "Congress Party and rival of Muhammad Ali Jinnah’s Muslim League gave the (10 pts)",
        "“Tryst with Destiny” speech on the eve of his nation’s independence from Great Britain in 1947. For ten points, name this father of Indira Gandhi and first Prime Minister of India."
      ],
      "answer": "Jawaharlal Nehru"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Edward Welburn, the head of Global Design of this company, is the highest-ranking African-American in the automobile industry. The EV1 released by this company was the subject of the film Who Killed the Electric Car?. This company, which was co-founded by (20 pts)",
        "C.S. Mott and William C. Durant in 1908, survived the 2008 financial crisis by being partly owned by the U.S. government. Secretary of Defense Charles Wilson claimed that “what is (10 pts)",
        "good for [this company] is good for America”. For ten points, name this car company based in Flint, Michigan, whose brands include Chevrolet and Cadillac."
      ],
      "answer": "GM or General Motors"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Rexford Tugwell served as this territory’s governor during World War II, shortly before two of its nationalists killed policeman Leslie Coffelt in an attempt to assassinate Harry (20 pts)",
        "Truman. Its current governor, Alejandro Garcia Padilla, believes that it would turn into a “Latin American ghetto” if the (10 pts)",
        "statehood movement were to succeed. For ten points, name this U.S. Commonwealth with capital San Juan, where 834,000 citizens voted support for making it the 51st U.S. state in 2012."
      ],
      "answer": "Puerto Rico"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In a 1970’s memo, this company valued a human life at $200,000, justifying the non-installation of an $11 part that would prevent the rupture of fuel tanks in its (20 pts)",
        "Pinto model. This company produced the unpopular Edsel, named for the son of its founder, who built the River Rouge plant in Dearborn, (10 pts)",
        "Michigan and introduced the $5 daily wage. For ten points, name this American car manufacturer that introduced the Model T in 1908."
      ],
      "answer": "Ford Motor Company"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After 100 days of exercise and incantations, members of this non-American movement believed they gained invulnerability to bullets. Members of this movement sieged the Legation Quarter until the (20 pts)",
        "Eight Nation Alliance freed them. This movement was supported until 1901 by the Dowager Empress (10 pts)",
        "Cixi [see-shee] of the Qing [ching] Dynasty in hopes of ridding China of foreigners. For ten points, name this nationalist movement, also known as the Society of Righteous and Harmonious Fists."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Boxers",
        "the Society of Righteous and Harmonious Fists until mentioned",
        "Boxer Rebellion and equivalents"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Bela Lyon Pratt created a statue of this man for his namesake fort in New Haven, Connecticut. Consider Tiffany wrote about the capture of this man in a tavern by Robert Rogers; this man was (20 pts)",
        "observing the movements of British troops after the Battle of Long Island. He was purported to say, “I only (10 pts)",
        "regret that I have but one life to lose for my country”. For ten points, name this American spy who was executed during the Revolutionary War."
      ],
      "answer": "Nathan Hale"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In one speech, this man compared interviewing Jesse Jackson to boxing a glacier, then told his audience, “enjoy that metaphor, because your grandchildren will have no idea what a glacier is.” A character played by this man frequently used the nickname (20 pts)",
        "“Papa Bear” to refer to Fox News host Bill O’Reilly. “Americans for a Better Tomorrow, Tomorrow” was a super PAC founded by this comedian, who coined the term (10 pts)",
        "“truthiness” on the first episode of his namesake spin-off of The Daily Show. For ten points, name this former host of a Report on Comedy Central, the current host of CBS’s Late Show."
      ],
      "answer": "Stephen Colbert"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Peter Williamson, one of these people, was captured by Native Americans and returned to England as “Indian Peter” in the 18th century. A practice known as “blackbirding” is sometimes used to (20 pts)",
        "acquire these people. A “redemptioner” policy allowed these people to buy their freedom after a determined (10 pts)",
        "number of years, commonly seven. For ten points, name this practice where people paid for passage to the New World in exchange for a period of forced service, which was banned with slavery by the 13th Amendment."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Indentured servants",
        "word forms"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A joke about “two beautiful ladies” by the defendant fell flat during oral arguments in this case. Harry Blackmun consulted with the Mayo Clinic while writing his majority opinion in this case, whose petitioner, (20 pts)",
        "Norma McCorvey, later converted to Catholicism and began to oppose this decision. This case’s (10 pts)",
        "trimester framework was replaced in the 1992 Planned Parenthood v. Casey decision. For ten points, name this 1973 Supreme Court case which established that the right to privacy under the 14th Amendment covered a woman’s right to an abortion."
      ],
      "answer": "Roe v. Wade"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Thomas Jefferson advocated for this document, saying “half a loaf is better than no bread.” Barron v. Baltimore ruled that this document could not be applied to state governments; now, courts use the (20 pts)",
        "14th amendment to incorporate parts of this document to the states. One part of this document protects against cruel and (10 pts)",
        "unusual punishment, and its first section protects freedom of speech. For ten points, name this set of the first ten amendments to the U.S. Constitution."
      ],
      "answer": "Bill of Rights"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Former President Rutherford B. Hayes arbitrated a land dispute in the aftermath of this war, in which the losing general was killed during the battle of Cerro Cor´a. It began after the invasion of Mato Grosso, leading (20 pts)",
        "Dom Pedro II, Bartolome Mitre, and Venancio Flores to form a coalition against Francisco Solano Lopez. Over half of (10 pts)",
        "Paraguay’s population was killed in, for ten points, what war against an alliance of Argentina, Uruguay, and Brazil?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "War of the Triple Alliance",
        "Paraguayan War before Paraguay is mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This organization’s former director, Keith Alexander, dismissed claims that it held “millions of dossiers on people.” This organization was able to collect 30 days’ worth of (20 pts)",
        "phone calls from entire countries, such as the Bahamas, via its MYSTIC program; that program’s existence, like that of (10 pts)",
        "PRISM, was revealed by Edward Snowden. For ten points, name this American intelligence agency that, unlike the CIA, focuses on monitoring electronic communications."
      ],
      "answer": "National Security Agency or NSA"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This President responded to the “Capitol Crawl” by signing a civil rights law that required reasonable accommodations in the workplace. He promoted volunteerism with his “thousand points of light” speech and defeated a (20 pts)",
        "Democratic opponent with an ad featuring escaped convict Willie Horton. This man’s re-election bid was (10 pts)",
        "hampered by the failed pledge, “Read my lips: no new taxes.” for ten points, name this 41st U.S. President who defeated Michael Dukakis in 1988 and fathered the 43rd U.S. President."
      ],
      "answer": "George Herbert Walker Bush"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In a political cartoon, one of these organizations is told, “by the Great Eternal, I’ll cleave thee to the earth!” by a man wielding a cane labeled “Veto.” State, rather than federal, charters established the (20 pts)",
        "“wildcat” type of these institutions, some of which were called “pets,” as they were given excess federal (10 pts)",
        "money. Until Andrew Jackson’s intervention, Nicholas Biddle led, for ten points, what type of financial institution that, in the 19th century, issued their own currency?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "banks",
        "the Second Bank of the United States"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In the course of trying to cover up this event, Mendel Rivers called helicopter pilot Hugh Thompson a traitor for ordering his men to shoot Americans committing this event. President (20 pts)",
        "Nixon pardoned Charlie Company officer William Calley for his murder of 22 people, including (10 pts)",
        "children, during this event. For ten points, name this March 16, 1968 event in which hundreds of Vietnamese citizens were killed by U.S. soldiers, named for one of the villages attacked."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "My Lai Massacre",
        "Son My Massacre"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This group suffered heavy causalities while taking Hamburger Hill during the Vietnam War. Bad weather led to greater than expected casualties for this group during its Mission Albany, the precursor to Operation Neptune. During Operation Market Garden, this group secured (20 pts)",
        "“Hell’s Highway.” Their commanding officer, Anthony McAuliffe, replied “Nuts!” when asked to give up (10 pts)",
        "Bastogne during the Battle of the Bulge. For ten points, name this American light infantry division, also used by President Eisenhower to desegregate Little Rock Central High School in 1957."
      ],
      "answer": "101st Airborne Division"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This artist painted Pitt the Elder collapsing after giving a speech protesting American independence in his Death of the Earl of Chatham and painted General George Augustus Elliot on horseback pointing towards burning (20 pts)",
        "Spanish ships in The Siege of Gibraltar. He painted his half-brother with a pet rodent in (10 pts)",
        "Boy With a Squirrel, and depicted the rescue of a man who was attacked by the title animal in the Havana Harbor. For ten points, name this 18th century American painter of Watson and the Shark."
      ],
      "answer": "John Singleton Copley"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s former slave and valet, Paul Jennings, wrote a memoir of this man’s time in the White House. After initially vetoing the proposal, this President signed a second bill chartering a second national (20 pts)",
        "bank. As Secretary of State, this man’s refusal to deliver a commission for a judgeship led to the establishment of judicial review. He argued that large republics were better to fend off factionalism in the 10th (10 pts)",
        "Federalist Paper. For ten points, name this “Father of the Constitution” and 4th President of the United States."
      ],
      "answer": "James Madison"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man focused on Owen Lattimore in the Tydings Committee hearings, after which his charges were deemed a “fraud and a hoax.” Early in his career, this man fought wartime price controls after receiving a $20,000 personal loan from (20 pts)",
        "Pepsi, earning him the nickname the “Pepsi-Cola Kid.” After he accused the Army of being soft, Joseph Welch asked this man “Have (10 pts)",
        "you no sense of decency?” in Congressional hearings. For ten points, name this Wisconsin senator who claimed there were 205 communists in the State Department during the Red Scare."
      ],
      "answer": "Joseph McCarthy"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) James Madison vetoed this man’s proposed 1817 Bonus Bill. As Secretary of War under James Monroe, this man created the Bureau of Indian Affairs. This man’s involvement in the (20 pts)",
        "Petticoat Affair led to his resignation as vice president. As a senator, he rejected the Compromise of 1850, claimed slavery was a “positive good,” and was a chief advocate for states’ rights during (10 pts)",
        "the nullification crisis. For ten points, name this member of the Senate’s “Great Triumvirate,” a senator from South Carolina."
      ],
      "answer": "John Caldwell Calhoun"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Early in this king’s reign, John Wilkes was forced into exile after publishing libel against this man’s advisor, the 3rd Earl of Bute. After failing to find agreement on the emancipation of Catholics, William (20 pts)",
        "Pitt resigned from this king’s government. This probable sufferer of porphyria lost the favor of some subjects when he allowed his prime minister, George Grenville, to impose the (10 pts)",
        "Stamp Tax. For ten points, name this mad English king who lost control of the American colonies."
      ],
      "answer": "George III"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This event was sparked by the death of Mathias J. Degan after John Bonfield threatened the assembled crowd. The newspaper Arbeiter-Zeitung was heavily criticized after this event for having (20 pts)",
        "incited violence. James Oglesby eventually commuted the death sentences of two of this event’s perpetrators. This event occurred during a rally in front of the (10 pts)",
        "McCormickHarvestingcompanyinChicago.Fortenpoints,namethis1886riot,triggeredwhenanarchists threw homemade bombs at Chicago police."
      ],
      "answer": "Haymarket Square Riot"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Clarence Brandenburg, a member of this group, was arrested for threatening a march on Congress but had his conviction reversed by the Supreme Court on First Amendment grounds. This group’s methods of (20 pts)",
        "voter intimidation prompted the Force Acts of the 1870s, and four members of this group perpetrated the 16th Street Church (10 pts)",
        "bombing in Birmingham in 1963. A Grand Wizard leads, for ten points, what American white supremacist group known for wearing white hoods and burning crosses?"
      ],
      "answer": "Ku Klux Klan or KKK"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A popular movement in this state led to the Supreme Court case of Luther v. Borden and an uprising put down by a militia called by this state’s governor, Samuel Ward King. Thomas Wilson Dorr fought for democratic reform in this state, which was the site of the Great (20 pts)",
        "Swamp Fight and the burning of the Gaspee during the colonial era. In the 1630s, the Narragansett Indians sold the land that would make up this state to (10 pts)",
        "Roger Williams. For ten points, name this U.S. state, the site of Providence Plantation and the smallest U.S. state."
      ],
      "answer": "Rhode Island and Providence Plantations"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This organization operates the connected Sackler and Freer Galleries of Art. As of November 2016, this organization has run two successful Kickstarter campaigns, raising funds to preserve (20 pts)",
        "Judy Garland’s ruby slippers from The Wizard of Oz and Neil Armstrong’s Apollo 11 spacesuit, which were each donated to this organization. The (10 pts)",
        "National Mall is the home of 11 facilities run by this organization, including one devoted to Air and Space. For ten points, name this group of American historical museums that is largely centered in Washington, D.C."
      ],
      "answer": "Smithsonian Institution"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man responded to criticism from hippies by noting that he was “killing fascists while [they] were in diapers.” In order to circumvent a two-term tenure limit, this man convinced his wife (20 pts)",
        "Lurleen to succeed him. This Independent Party candidate in the 1968 Presidential Election rose to fame after declaring a commitment to “segregation (10 pts)",
        "now, segregation tomorrow, and segregation forever” at a 1963 inaugural address. For ten points, name this governor who performed the “stand in the schoolhouse door” against the integration of the University of Alabama."
      ],
      "answer": "George Wallace"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s treasury secretary, Benjamin Bristow, exposed widescale bribery involving taxes on alcohol. This President was manipulated by James Fisk and Jay Gould in the (20 pts)",
        "“Black Friday” scheme to corner the gold market. During this man’s re-election campaign against Horace Greeley, his opponents railed against his vice president, Schulyer Colfax, and others for taking bribes from a (10 pts)",
        "railroad construction company. For ten points, name this U.S. president whose administration was plagued by the Whiskey Ring and Credit Mobilier [moh-beel-yay] scandals, but whose reputation as a Union general earned him re-election."
      ],
      "answer": "Ulysses S. Grant"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was accused of working with John van Vossen and Robert Rose in aiding the Cherokees, a charge that prompted him to beat accuser William Stanberry with a cane. He was replaced by (20 pts)",
        "Mirabeau Lamar in his highest post after he refused to lend support to the Confederacy. During a revolution against (10 pts)",
        "Mexican rule, this man masterminded a victory over Santa Anna at San Jacinto. For ten points, name this first president of the Texan Republic, honored as the namesake of Texas’ most populous city."
      ],
      "answer": "Sam Houston"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This party split into two separate factions after 1956 when its final presidential candidate, Darlington Hoopes, won fewer than 6,000 votes. Walter Lippmann founded the National Party to (20 pts)",
        "oppose this party after World War I. Assisting the ARU during the Pullman strike got a candidate from this political party (10 pts)",
        "imprisoned; that same member was later arrested under the Espionage Act of 1917. For ten points, name this American political party, sponsored by progressives and labor unions, for which Eugene Debs ran for President five times."
      ],
      "answer": "Socialist Party of America"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) For one post, this man was selected over William Paterson as a replacement for Oliver Ellsworth. John Adams claimed that the “proudest act of my life” was gifting this man to the American people. This man (20 pts)",
        "changed a previous tradition of delivering opinions seriatim. In one decision, he argued that a writ of mandamus could not be issued because the Judiciary Act of (10 pts)",
        "1789 was unconstitutional, thus establishing the power of judicial review. For ten points, name this third Chief Justice of the Supreme Court the author of the opinion in Marbury v. Madison."
      ],
      "answer": "John Marshall"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The winning side of this war controversially suffered non-battle casualties when Nelson Miles’ soldiers ate spoiled “embalmed beef.” The telegraphed instruction (20 pts)",
        "“furnish the pictures and I’ll furnish the war” allegedly helped prompt this conflict, as the (10 pts)",
        "yellow journalism of William Randolph Hearst raised tensions after the sinking of the USS Maine. Puerto Rico and Guam were ceded to the United States following, for ten points, what 1898 war against a European power that had controlled Cuba?"
      ],
      "answer": "Spanish-American War"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Because of her connections to this person, boarding house owner Mary Surratt became the first woman to be executed by the U.S. government. This man was treated for a broken (20 pts)",
        "leg by Samuel Mudd before dying in a shootout with federal troops on a farm in northern Virginia. This man’s reputation as an (10 pts)",
        "actor allowed him to sneak into a performance at Ford’s Theatre, where he jumped onto the stage and shouted “Sic Semper Tyrannis” after shooting a U.S. president. For ten points, name this assassin of Abraham Lincoln."
      ],
      "answer": "John Wilkes Booth"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this election year, Harold Stassen was told “you can’t shoot an idea with a gun” after supporting a mandatory communist registry in this election year. Strom Thurmond ran on the breakaway (20 pts)",
        "Dixiecrat ticket in this election year. In a famous photograph taken in this year, a man holds up an early edition of the (10 pts)",
        "Chicago Daily Tribune announcing the wrong outcome of the presidential election. For ten points, name this election year in which Thomas Dewey actually lost to Harry Truman, who thus earned a full second term in office."
      ],
      "answer": "U.S. Presidential Election of 1948"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A member of this family replaced William Belknap as Secretary of War under Ulysses Grant. John F. Kennedy’s Profiles in Courage commended a senator from this family for criticizing the (20 pts)",
        "Nuremberg Trials; that senator from this family co-sponsored a 1947 labor relations act with Fred (10 pts)",
        "Hartley. The Chief Justice of the Supreme Court for almost all of the 1920s was from this family. For ten points, name this Ohio family of Alphonso and Robert, as well as William Howard, who succeeded Theodore Roosevelt as president."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Taft family",
        "Alphonso Taft",
        "William Howard Taft",
        "Robert Taft"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man called off the CODESA negotiations after the Boipatong massacre, carried out by members of the Inkatha Freedom Party. Quartus de Wet oversaw a trial in which this man declared “I have cherished the ideal of a democratic and free society [...] it is an ideal for which (20 pts)",
        "I am prepared to die.” This man was “Accused #1” in that 1963 trial, which was held in Rivonia. (10 pts)",
        "F.W. de Klerk released this man from prison in 1990; four years later, this man won the presidency in his country’s first post-Apartheid elections. For ten points, name this first black President of South Africa."
      ],
      "answer": "Nelson Rolihlahla Mandela"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s death was indirectly caused by the publishing of Charles D. Cooper’s letters. James Callender wrote about this man’s affair with Maria [mah-RYE-uh] (20 pts)",
        "Reynolds. This man, who urged consolidation of state and federal debt in his “First Report on Public Credit,” joined George (10 pts)",
        "Washington to put down a rebellion in Pennsylvania over a whiskey tax that this man implemented. The First Bank of the United States was founded by, for ten points, what first Secretary of the Treasury who was killed in a duel with Aaron Burr?"
      ],
      "answer": "Alexander Hamilton"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Between his stints on the Supreme Court, Charles Evans Hughes served in this Cabinet position under Harding and Coolidge. In this position, Elihu Root helped design the 1901 (20 pts)",
        "Platt Amendment, and another holder of this Cabinet position named John Hay formalized the Open Door Policy to keep trade with (10 pts)",
        "China balanced. Under Taft, a holder of this position promoted loans to countries in Latin America as part of “dollar diplomacy.” For ten points, name this Cabinet position that oversees foreign policy."
      ],
      "answer": "Secretary of State"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The terms of this legislation were debated by delegates from nine southern states in the Nashville Convention. By the terms of this legislation, Texas gave up claims to western lands in exchange for trading off ten million dollars of debt. In this legislation, (20 pts)",
        "California was admitted as a free state, but the New Mexico and Utah Territories were established under (10 pts)",
        "popular sovereignty. For ten points, name this deal brokered by Henry Clay and Stephen Douglas that many historians believe postponed the Civil War for a decade."
      ],
      "answer": "Compromise of 1850"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Luxembourg Compromise ended this leader’s withdrawal from the European Economic Community during the Empty Chair Crisis. In another role, this leader advocated for a mobile professional force in The (20 pts)",
        "Army of the Future, panning his nation’s usage of the Maginot Line. After Philippe (10 pts)",
        "Petain took power as the head of the Vichy puppet state, this man led his country’s “Free” forces against the Nazis during World War II. For ten points, name this first president of the French Fifth Republic."
      ],
      "answer": "Charles de Gaulle"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Planes intercepted over this facility are often forced to land in nearby Hagerstown. This facility is officially designated NSF Thurmont and was known as “Shangri-La” in the (20 pts)",
        "1940s. In 1978, this facility hosted meetings that created two frameworks: the first was condemned by the UN, but the second earned (10 pts)",
        "Menachim Began and Anwar Sadat a shared Nobel Prize. For ten points, name this Maryland facility, a Presidential retreat where Jimmy Carter hosted Middle East peace talks that produced a set of Accords. ANSWER:Camp David (accept NavalSupportFacility Thurmont before mentioned; accept Shangri- La before mentioned) (7) A speech advocating for this action was given “at a college noted for knowledge, in a city noted for progress, in a state noted for strength.” This action was compared to “climb[ing] the highest mountain,” “fly[ing] the Atlantic,” and (+) “Rice play[ing] Texas” in a 1962 speech that noted “we choose to” do this “in this decade.” The development of the (*) Saturn V [five] propulsion system was instrumental in performing this action, which was last done by the Challenger lander in 1972. For ten points, name this exploration first done by Buzz Aldrin and Neil Armstrong aboard Apollo 11."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "going to the Moon",
        "equivalents related to a manned Moon landing",
        "any additional information related to John F. Kennedy’s push for Americans/NASA going to the moon"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1946, this figure noted “there is a somber point in the social outlook of Americans” in a lecture against racism at the historically black Lincoln University. This figure’s literary rights were bequeathed to the Hebrew University of Jerusalem, which he helped establish. This man (20 pts)",
        "signed a 1939 letter written by Leo Szilard [zee-lard] that was sent to President Roosevelt, warning him of the threat of (10 pts)",
        "German nuclear bombs. For ten points, name this physicist who won a Nobel Prize for his work on the photoelectric effect and who also developed the theory of special relativity."
      ],
      "answer": "Albert Einstein"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was the first African American to be honored with a national memorial, placed in Diamond, Missouri. This man gained fame overnight after he testified in 1921 Congressional tariff hearings. This man, who advertised a massage oil (20 pts)",
        "cure for polio in the 1930s, promoted the cultivation of legumes and (10 pts)",
        "sweet potatoes in the South to alternate with cotton farming. For ten points, name this agricultural researcher at the Tuskegee Institute who developed numerous peanut-based products, but did not actually invent peanut butter."
      ],
      "answer": "George Washington Carver"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Three years after it was decided, the verdict in this Supreme Court case was used to justify the closing of an educational facility in Richmond, Georgia in Cumming v. School Board. This case was decided 7-1 over John Marshall (20 pts)",
        "Harlan’s dissent, which originated the concept of constitutional colorblindness. Albion Tourge´e [tour-zhay] represented the plaintiff of this case, a one-eighth (10 pts)",
        "black man sponsored by a New Orleans citizens’ committee to ride in a whites-only train car. For ten points, name this 1896 case that established the “separate but equal” doctrine."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Plessy v. Ferguson",
        "either",
        "both underlined portions"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) As part of this movement, Thomas Campbell and his son Alexander founded a sect called the Disciples of Christ. A massive log hall was built in Cane Ridge, (20 pts)",
        "Kentucky by the followers of Barton Stone to house a camp meeting during this movement. The so-called “burned-over district” referred to areas saturated by (10 pts)",
        "Baptist and Methodist converts during this movement. For ten points, identify this Christian revival in early 19th-Century America, so named because it followed a similar movement in the mid-1700s."
      ],
      "answer": "Second Great Awakening"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In one of this man’s speeches, he lamented the suppression of the writings of Scott Nearing, Max Eastman, and John Work. In Canton, Ohio, this leader compared Wall Street to the German (20 pts)",
        "Junker class and urged people to resist the draft, after which he was prosecuted under the Sedition Act. The (10 pts)",
        "Pullman Strike was organized by, for ten points, what socialist who earned three percent of the popular vote in the 1920 Presidential election, despite being in prison?"
      ],
      "answer": "Eugene Victor Debs"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This politician’s constitutional authority was the subject of the Humble Petition and Advice. This figure’s massacre of civilians during the siege of (20 pts)",
        "Drogheda [drow-duh] led him to be reviled in Ireland. This man and his son-in-law, Henry Ireton, commanded the left and right wings of Thomas Fairfax’s (10 pts)",
        "New Model Army during a victory at Naseby. For ten points, name this Lord Protector of England following the English Civil War."
      ],
      "answer": "Oliver Cromwell"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Since 1977, the holder of this position has lived in Number One Observatory Circle on the grounds of the US Naval Observatory. Electoral votes are counted by the holder of this position. The Constitution did not explain how to (20 pts)",
        "fill vacancies in this position until the 25th Amendment was ratified. The holder of this position also serves as (10 pts)",
        "President of the Senate, where they hold tiebreaking power. For ten points, name this office of the executive branch whose holder is first in line of Presidential succession."
      ],
      "answer": "Vice President of the United States"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man supposedly introduced his friend and former classmate James Madison to his future wife Dolley Payne. Anthony Merry and James Wilkinson were alleged co-conspirators in this man’s plot to take over (20 pts)",
        "land in the southwest to form his own country. This man represented New York in the Senate after winning an election against Philip (10 pts)",
        "Schuyler [sky-ler], the father-in-law of a man who thwarted this man’s presidential ambitions by backing Thomas Jefferson in the election of 1800. For ten points, name this politician who won a duel against his rival, Alexander Hamilton."
      ],
      "answer": "Aaron Burr"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This figure hired a group of men all named Elmer so that when he called for them, they would all show up. This man was said to have drilled holes in maple trees with two huge mosquitoes he had caught. This man owned a cow named (20 pts)",
        "Lucy, as well as an animal that he found freezing in the snow that turned a certain color when exposed to his fireplace. This owner of (10 pts)",
        "Babe the Blue Ox was said to have created the Grand Canyon while dragging his axe behind him. For ten points, name this giant lumberjack of American folklore."
      ],
      "answer": "Paul Bunyan"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Alexander Gardner’s “Sketchbook of the War” focuses on this conflict, during which James Gibson took an iconic photograph of a hospital at Savage Station. Another photographer, Timothy O’Sullivan, showed the corpses at one of this war’s decisive battles in “The (20 pts)",
        "Harvest of Death.” Over $100,000 was spent on photographic efforts during this war by a man who popularized the daguerreotype technique in (10 pts)",
        "America. Mathew Brady was a prominent photographer during, for ten points, what war which was the subject of pictures like The Dead at Antietam?"
      ],
      "answer": "American Civil War"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Roger Hilsman Jr. drafted a proposal to kill a leader of this country, which was authorized by Dean Rusk while the president was on vacation. Cable 243 targeted a ruler of this nation after that ruler alienated (20 pts)",
        "Buddhist monks in a series of pagoda raids. In 1963, this republic’s first leader, Ngo Dinh Diem [yiem], was assassinated with CIA aid. This nation, which was bounded by the 17th Parallel, fought the (10 pts)",
        "Viet Cong under Ho Chi Minh’s control. For ten points, name this American-backed republic that survived until Saigon fell in 1975."
      ],
      "answer": "South Vietnam"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man agreed to put his troops under the command of the Australian John Monash during the Battle of Hamel. During his early service, this man captured Datu Amil in the Moro Rebellion and fought with the (20 pts)",
        "Buffalo Soldiers of the 10th Cavalry, granting him his nickname. This man later led the Punitive Expedition to (10 pts)",
        "avenge the raid on Columbus and sought to capture Pancho Villa in 1916. For ten points, name this leader of the American Expeditionary Force in World War I, a general nicknamed “Black Jack.”"
      ],
      "answer": "John “Black Jack” Pershing"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Candice Bergen claimed that this man gave a “perfectly intelligence speech” [sic] when he criticized the show Murphy Brown for “mocking the importance of fathers.” After comparing his length of Congressional service to a former president, this man was scolded by (20 pts)",
        "Lloyd Bentsen, who said “Senator, you’re no Jack Kennedy.” Despite that incident, this man became (10 pts)",
        "vice president after the defeat of Michael Dukakis in 1988. For ten points, name this vice president who served under George H.W. Bush."
      ],
      "answer": "Dan Quayle"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Adam Hochschild alleged that the country ruled by this man underwent a “Great Forgetting” after his death. A Mark Twain pamphlet titled for this man’s soliloquy publicized the practice of severing human (20 pts)",
        "hands that was carried out by this leader’s military force, the Force Publique. The Stokes Affair damaged this ruler’s reputation, as did the Casement Report, which announced the brutal treatment of (10 pts)",
        "rubber plantation workers in a state that this leader established during the Berlin Congress. The Congo Free State was ruled by, for ten points, what Belgian king?"
      ],
      "answer": "Leopold II"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Due to his struggles with dyslexia, Mike Gravel had to stop his Senate reading of these documents, which were obtained by a colleague of Anthony Russo who worked at RAND Corporation. These documents were the subject of the (20 pts)",
        "Supreme Court case New York Times Co. v. United States. These documents included a memo claiming that “[avoiding] a humiliating (10 pts)",
        "defeat” was Lyndon Johnson’s main reason to continue a certain war. Daniel Ellsberg released, for ten points, what controversial documents about the Vietnam War prepared by the Department of Defense?"
      ],
      "answer": "Pentagon Papers"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This election year marked the first time a party’s national convention was televised. The winner of this election won support by claiming the 80th Congress had stuck a “pitchfork in the farmer’s back.” During this year’s Democratic convention, 30 (20 pts)",
        "southern senators walked out over a civil rights dispute and instead nominated “Dixiecrat” Strom Thurmond. In this year, a (10 pts)",
        "photograph was taken of a man holding a Chicago Daily Tribune newspaper that incorrectly reported Thomas Dewey as the victor. For ten points, name this year in which Harry Truman won a full term in office."
      ],
      "answer": "US Presidential election of 1948"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A million-acre grant owned by this man was sold in the Bingham Purchase. This man, who died in 1806 after swallowing a chicken bone, was sent with Gouvernor Morris on a mission to Elizabethtown to negotiate prisoner exchanges. This man became the (20 pts)",
        "youngest major general in the Continental Army after his service at Yorktown. This man, who was succeeded in his highest post by Timothy Pickering, had earlier employed eighty yoke of (10 pts)",
        "oxen to transport artillery to Boston during a namesake expedition. For ten points, name this American general who later served as the first Secretary of War."
      ],
      "answer": "Henry Knox"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A Reconciliation Park at the site of the Tulsa Race Riot is named for an African- American historian of this surname. From Slavery to Freedom author John Hope had this surname, as did William, a Loyalist leader during the American Revolution who was the (20 pts)",
        "last colonial governor of New Jersey. A man with this surname was appointed postmaster of the (10 pts)",
        "American colonies in 1753 and founded the Pennsylvania Gazette. For ten points, give this surname of founding father and inventor Benjamin."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Franklin",
        "John Hope Franklin, William Franklin, and/or Benjamin Franklin"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A woman who married into this family had tomatoes thrown at her in Switzerland while on her “Rainbow Tour.” Supporters of a leader from this family were killed in the Ezeiza Massacre. (20 pts)",
        "Jorge Videla led a coup against a leader of the Justicialist party from this family, which was supported by the “shirtless ones,” the (10 pts)",
        "descamisados. After a champion of women’s suffrage died of cancer in 1952, the patriarch of this family re-married Isabel in 1961. For ten points, name this surname shared by Evita and her husband, a 20th century Argentinian president named Juan."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Per´on family",
        "Eva “Evita” Per´on",
        "Juan Per´on",
        "Isabel Per´on"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One side in this battle was aided by domineering artillery fire from Combs’ Hill. Charles Lee was court-martialed for failing to secure a decisive outcome in this battle, which failed to prevent Henry (20 pts)",
        "Clinton from withdrawing to New York. During the second day of this battle, artilleryman William Hays collapsed of (10 pts)",
        "heatstroke and his wife, Mary Hays, took his place loading the cannon, a feat that is often conflated with her transporting water to soldiers. For ten points, name this 1778 Revolutionary War battle that spawned the myth of Molly Pitcher."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Monmouth Courthouse"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Rosalynn Carter persuaded politician Wayne Townsend to approve this legislation in Indiana. The court case Idaho v. Freeman concerned the passage of this legislation, which was opposed by the Eagle Forum founded by (20 pts)",
        "Phyllis Schlafly. This legislation failed to become law since only 35 of 38 states ratified it before its (10 pts)",
        "1979 deadline. The N.O.W. supported this legislation at the urging of its author, Alice Paul. For ten points, name this proposed Constitutional amendment that intended to prohibit sex discrimination."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Equal Rights Amendment",
        "ERA"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This battle was preceded by the Battle of Lake Borgne and involved a defensive line behind the Rodriguez Canal. The losing side in this battle stranded many senior officers in no man’s land when they forgot their (20 pts)",
        "ladders. A group of smugglers from Barataria led by Jean Lafitte helped (10 pts)",
        "American forces in this battle defeat and kill Edward Pakenham. For ten points, name this victory for future president Andrew Jackson, a battle that was fought without knowledge of the Treaty of Ghent, which ended the War of 1812."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of New Orleans"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A politician from this state was gifted a 1947 Cadillac that was paid for with fifty $25 checks; that man served as the longest-serving Speaker of the House and mentored a man who intimidated his colleagues with (20 pts)",
        "“the treatment.” A politician from this state spoke at the University of Michigan, announcing several progressive policies as part of his (10 pts)",
        "“Great Society” in 1964. For ten points, name this home state of Sam Rayburn and Lyndon B. Johnson, the latter of whom was inaugurated as President in this state’s city of Dallas."
      ],
      "answer": "Texas"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This speech attacks a governor whose “lips [drip] with the words of interposition and nullification.” The writer of this speech claims to have received a check from America that was marked (20 pts)",
        "“insufficient funds” but goes on to describe former slaves and slaveowners sitting together at the “table of brotherhood.” The hope that future generations “will not be (10 pts)",
        "judged by the color of their skin but by the content of their character” is proclaimed in, for ten points, what speech given at the 1963 March on Washington by Martin Luther King, Jr.?"
      ],
      "answer": "I Have a Dream speech"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This President berated Charles Forbes as a “double crossing bastard” for selling off Veterans Bureau medical supplies. Jess Smith committed suicide after this President confronted him about his crimes; Smith was an unofficial aide to this man’s Attorney General, Harry (20 pts)",
        "Daugherty. Nan Britton claimed to have given birth to this man’s illegitimate daughter, one of several controversies surrounding this man that came to light after his death from (10 pts)",
        "“apoplexy,” or a massive heart attack. The corrupt Ohio Gang served, for ten points, what US President who died before the Teapot Dome scandal exploded?"
      ],
      "answer": "Warren Gamaliel Harding"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man and his sons killed James Doyle, two of Doyle’s sons, and two other men in a May 24th, 1856 attack that was inspired by the sacking of Lawrence a week prior. The (20 pts)",
        "Pottawatomie Massacre was led by this man, who declared that he was “quite certain” that America’s crimes will “never be purged away but with blood” on the morning of his (10 pts)",
        "hanging in 1859. Robert E. Lee led a Marine detachment that ended this man’s brief occupation of a federal armory, which he had hoped would lead to an armed slave uprising. For ten points, name this violent abolitionist who led the raid on Harper’s Ferry."
      ],
      "answer": "John Brown"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man, who defended his actions in a series of letters in the National Intelligencer newspaper, was investigated by the Covode Committee that looked for ways to impeach him. This man sent the army to confront the Mormons in the Utah War, and the (20 pts)",
        "Mountain Meadows massacre occurred during his administration. This president supported the Lecompton Constitution in his attempts to make Kansas a slave state. The end of his tenure was marked by (10 pts)",
        "South Carolina’s secession. For ten points, name this US president who is often criticized for failing to prevent the Civil War and was succeeded by Abraham Lincoln."
      ],
      "answer": "James Buchanan"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this year, Jim Sasser and Harris Wofford lost their seats in the Senate. A document released in this year proposed the Citizen Legislature Act, which would have introduced congressional term limits. In this year, Alabama senator Richard (20 pts)",
        "Shelby switched parties and became a Republican. The Heritage Foundation worked with Larry Hunter, Tom DeLay, and Newt Gingrich in this year to write the (10 pts)",
        "Contract with America. For ten points, name this midterm election year during Bill Clinton's first term."
      ],
      "answer": "1994"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1996, this man's campaign ran ads warning voters to \"Get BeSheared.” In his first senatorial election, this man narrowly defeated Walter Dee Huddleston. This man controversially called the Families First Coronavirus Response Act an \"ideological wish list.\" This man's (20 pts)",
        "wife, Elaine Chao, served as Secretary of Transportation in the Trump administration. This man blocked the hearings for Merrick (10 pts)",
        "Garland as Senate Majority Leader. For ten points, name this Kentucky senator and Senate Minority Leader as of January, 2021."
      ],
      "answer": "Mitch McConnell"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man declared that “Education is the key to opportunity in our society” and signed a bill doubling federal spending on education. A namesake Texas law he helped pass allowed this man to win reelection to the US Senate and the Vice Presidency in the (20 pts)",
        "same election. Three years following that election, this 36th US president became the first to be sworn in by a (10 pts)",
        "woman, doing so while aboard Air Force One in 1963. For ten points, name this man who took office following the assassination of John F. Kennedy."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Lyndon Baines Johnson",
        "LBJ,"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) According to South Dakota v. Dole, it is constitutional to withhold federal funding for these structures in locations where the drinking age is under 21. One of these structures in Lower Manhattan, proposed by Robert Moses, was never built due to protests by activists like Jane (20 pts)",
        "Jacobs. Congress’s 1956 bill to fund more of these structures contributed to \"white flight.\" After studying the (10 pts)",
        "Autobahn, Dwight Eisenhower backed the creation of, for ten points, what high-speed roads?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Highways or Freeways",
        "or Interstates Highway System,"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "This amendment has never been the primary basis of a Supreme Court decision and wasn’t even interpreted by a US court until 1982’s Engblom v. Carey. Justice William O. Douglas used this amendment, along with other parts of the (*) Bill of Rights, as part of the decision in Griswold v. Connecticut as an example of freedom from undue influence by the state. Proposed in 1789 in opposition to laws regarding the (*) British army, for ten points, name this Constitutional amendment prohibiting the quartering of soldiers in civilian homes."
      ],
      "answer": "Third Amendment to the US Constitution"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Until 2019, this state had only one female senator, white supremacist Rebecca Latimer Felton, who served for one day in 1922. In 2017 a special election in this state was the costliest congressional race ever. That contested seat from this state had belonged to the new HHS Secretary, Tom (20 pts)",
        "Price, and the loser in that election was elected to the Senate in 2020. In this state’s other 2020 Senate race, the owner of the WNBA’s Dream lost to the 10th (10 pts)",
        "African-American elected as US Senator. For ten points, what state elected Senators Jon Ossoff and Raphael Warnock?"
      ],
      "answer": "Georgia"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This holiday honors the date on which District Commander Gordon Granger read General Order No. 3 at Ashton Villa. Texas House Bill 1016 declared this date an official state holiday, while New York, Pennsylvania, and Virginia recognized it as a day of paid leave, following the death of (20 pts)",
        "George Floyd. John F. Callahan constructed a posthumously-released 1999 novel by Ralph Ellison (10 pts)",
        "which is titled for this holiday. For ten points, what holiday originated in Galveston and commemorates the emancipation of slaves in Texas on June 19, 1865?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Juneteenth",
        "Freedom Day, Jubilee Day, Emancipation Day,",
        "Liberation Day before “novel”"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) More than 1,200 people who took part in this event were interviewed by American journalist Isabel Wilkerson for her book The Warmth of Other Suns. The Museum of Modern Art and The Phillips Collection co-own a 60-panel series titled for this event by “dynamic (20 pts)",
        "cubist” painter Jacob Lawrence. Like the earlier Exodusters movement, this ongoing movement led to the growth of northern neighborhoods like Bronzeville, Chicago. This (10 pts)",
        "mass exodus of African-Americans from the rural South to the urban North is known, for ten points, by what name?"
      ],
      "answer": "Great Migration"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Languages in this family are not usually written by their native speakers but have used the Roman alphabet when they are written since the late 16th century. In 1975, a South American government adopted a new orthography for this language family which uses five vowels (20 pts)",
        "rather than the traditional three. Due to the spread of this language family, it blended with other indigenous languages, such as Aymara, and influenced dialects of (10 pts)",
        "Spanish. For ten points, name this South American indigenous language family, spoken by the Inca."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Quechuan languages or Runasimi,",
        "People’s Language"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s travels with US Army surgeon John Emerson took him to the free state of Illinois and the free territory of Wisconsin. This man, who died of tuberculosis in 1858, worked as a porter at a St. Louis hotel after then-State Senator Taylor Blow (20 pts)",
        "manumitted him in 1857. The legal arguments produced in this man’s freedom suit were later adopted by (10 pts)",
        "Abraham Lincoln and influenced the creation of the Emancipation Proclamation. For ten points, name this man, whose landmark US Supreme Court case ruled the Missouri Compromise unconstitutional."
      ],
      "answer": "Dred Scott 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 1"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Donald Trump circumvented this act by using \"Schedule F appointments\" when he signed an October 2020 Executive Order, an act being described by political scientists as “open cronyism.” The Franklin Pierce administration developed a predecessor to this act by creating a (20 pts)",
        "civil service exam for Cabinet staff. Deranged office seeker Charles J. Guiteau's assassination of President James Garfield led to (10 pts)",
        "reformers pushing this act through in 1883. For ten points, name this civil service reform that attempted to weaken the spoils system in American politics."
      ],
      "answer": "Pendleton Civil Service Reform Act"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Don Antonio Coronel told this woman about Mission Indians, and she was recommended as an agent by Hiram Price. After a lecture on the removal of the Ponca in Nebraska by Standing Bear, this woman started targeting federal officials like Interior Secretary Carl (20 pts)",
        "Schurz. A Scottish-Native American orphan named Ramona was created by this author, who also told seven tribal histories in (10 pts)",
        "A Century of Dishonor. For ten points, name this poet, author, and activist for Native Americans."
      ],
      "answer": "Helen Hunt \"H.H.\" Jackson"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This person studied Native American cultures through the lens of \"Apollonian\" and \"Dionysian\" viewpoints. This author worked with Gene Weltfish to write a pamphlet analyzing how brain size does not impact intelligence titled \"The Races of (20 pts)",
        "Mankind.” Another of this woman's works explains why Japanese POWs did not try to contact their families and explains Japan's (10 pts)",
        "\"shame\" culture in contrast with American \"guilt\" culture. For ten points, name this anthropologist who wrote The Chrysanthemum and the Sword."
      ],
      "answer": "Ruth Fulton Benedict"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) While this man was enrolled at West Point, he designed the M1913 Cavalry Saber and competed in the 1912 Summer Olympics. This man controversially organized Task Force (20 pts)",
        "Baum to rescue his son-in-law, John K. Waters. This general died shortly after being paralyzed in a low-speed car wreck. Infamously chastised for slapping two shell-shocked (10 pts)",
        "soldiers, for ten points, name this successful American general known as \"Old Blood and Guts.\""
      ],
      "answer": "George Smith Patton Jr."
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Several members of this party who opposed a provisional constitution of Massachusetts were derisively called the Essex Junto. Timothy Pickering and Josiah Quincy, members of this party, proposed secession for one region during the Hartford (20 pts)",
        "Convention. This party's only official member who became president signed the Alien and Sedition Acts into law and served after (10 pts)",
        "George Washington. For ten points, name this party of John Adams which opposed the Jeffersonians."
      ],
      "answer": "Federalist Party or Federalists"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This U.S. Constitutional amendment was ratified following a vote in Nebraska. Congress passed the Volstead [[VOHL-sted]] Act to (20 pts)",
        "enforce this amendment’s provisions. This amendment resulted from decades of activism by groups like the Anti-Saloon League and Woman's Christian Temperance (10 pts)",
        "Union, though in 1933 it became the only amendment in U.S. history to be repealed. For ten points, name this constitutional amendment that began Prohibition and banned alcohol in the United States."
      ],
      "answer": "Eighteenth Amendment or Amendment XVIII"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "Dominique de Gourgues [[GOORZH]] temporarily reestablished French hegemony in the north of this state by seizing Fort Caroline. A 1521 voyage to this modern state ended with its leader dying following a skirmish with the Calusa people. (*) The oldest continuously inhabited settlement in the U.S. is in this state. The conquistador Juan Ponce de Leon searched for the \"Fountain of (*) Youth\" in, for ten points, which Southern U.S. state that contains St. Augustine?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Florida",
        "La Florida",
        "or Floride"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Jerome Connor created a tribute to the more than 600 nuns who nursed soldiers during this conflict, and Loreta Janeta Velázquez likely masqueraded as a male soldier during this conflict. The only woman to ever receive the Medal of (20 pts)",
        "Honor, Mary Walker, served as a surgeon during this war, as did the founder of the American Red Cross and \"Angel of the Battlefield,\" (10 pts)",
        "Clara Barton. For ten points, name this war, during which Belle Boyd provided valuable information to Stonewall Jackson."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "United States Civil War",
        "War Between the States",
        "War of Northern Aggression",
        "American",
        "U.S. in place of \"United States\""
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The case [this U.S. state] v. Mitchell held that the government could not force a state to lower the voting age to eighteen. This state's largest city performed a mock- evacuation during Operation Greenlight after officials deemed the (20 pts)",
        "Willamette [[wih-LAM-et]] Valley a possible Soviet bombing target. In 2021, this state's eastern counties, including Malheur [[MALL-heer]], Sherman, and Grant, passed a measure promoting secession to form \"Greater (10 pts)",
        "Idaho.\" For ten points, name this U.S. state governed from Salem."
      ],
      "answer": "Oregon 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 5"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Fears of this person's influence led people to believe that Black men would knock down white women on this person's \"Tuesdays.\" Pauli Murray and this person worked to appeal for Odell Waller, though he was still executed in Virginia. Mary (20 pts)",
        "McLeod Bethune and this person often walked arm-in-arm. This woman resigned from the Daughters of the American Revolution after Marian (10 pts)",
        "Anderson was not allowed to sing in Constitution Hall. For ten points, name this Depression-era First Lady."
      ],
      "answer": "Eleanor Roosevelt or Anna Eleanor Roosevelt"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This merchant was taken to court after his ship, the Liberty, was captured and he was accused of not paying fees under Townshend Acts. This colonial leader chaired a committee that demanded the removal of British troops following the (20 pts)",
        "Boston Massacre. This protégé of Samuel Adams served as the first governor of (10 pts)",
        "Massachusetts. For ten points, name this president of the Continental Congress who provided the first and largest signature on the Declaration of Independence."
      ],
      "answer": "John Hancock"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this election year, volunteers were encouraged to “go clean for Gene” while supporting Eugene McCarthy in the New Hampshire primary. Curtis LeMay earned controversy for suggesting the use of (20 pts)",
        "nuclear weapons in this year as the vice- presidential nominee for George Wallace’s third-party run. Richard Daley was accused of using “Gestapo (10 pts)",
        "Tactics” at this year’s DNC in Chicago, which nominated Hubert Humphrey. For ten points, name this election year when Richard Nixon won his first term in office."
      ],
      "answer": "1968"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Historian Walter LaFeber [[lah-FEE-ber]] wrote that U.S. intervention in this overseas conflict marked “the origins of modern presidential powers.” Five thousand troops from the U.S. were sent by President McKinley to quell this rebellion sometimes called the (20 pts)",
        "Yìhétuán [[YEE-HEH-TWAHN]] Movement. This armed conflict arose from increasing tensions between foreign missionaries and (10 pts)",
        "Chinese rebels. For ten points, name this late 19th-century Chinese rebellion led by the Righteous and Harmonious Fists."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Boxer Rebellion or Boxer Uprising",
        "Yìhétuán Movement",
        "Yìhétuán yùndòng before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This thinker debated fellow pragmatist John Dewey after publishing Democracy and Social Ethics. This thinker espoused pacifism in books such as Newer Ideals of Peace. This first U.S. woman to win the Nobel (20 pts)",
        "Peace Prize drew on the ideas of England's Toynbee Hall when expanding the use of \"friendly visitors\" at an institution she co-founded with Ellen Gates Starr in (10 pts)",
        "Chicago. For ten points, name this pioneering social worker who founded Hull House."
      ],
      "answer": "Jane Addams or Laura Jane Addams"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This politician and one-time New York governor names a Cornell Law School building. When David Brewer died, William Howard Taft nominated this man to replace him in his highest office. This man resigned from the Supreme Court in 1916 to unsuccessfully (20 pts)",
        "run for president against Woodrow Wilson, and in 1921, this man became Warren Harding's (10 pts)",
        "Secretary of State. For ten points, name this man who returned to the court to serve as Chief Justice from 1930 to 1941."
      ],
      "answer": "Charles Evans Hughes, Sr. 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 9"
    }
  ]
}